<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Maiesties poeticall exercises at vacant houres</title>
            <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14379</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108288</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843949</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843949</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04260)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 251:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Maiesties poeticall exercises at vacant houres</title>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
                  <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur, 1544-1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[124] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue printer to the Kings Maiestie. Cum priuilegio regali,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1591]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>His Majesty = James I.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>The first work, "The furies", is translated from Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur Du Bartas.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi⁴ [A]⁴ B-L⁴ (L4 + "M"1 (=P2)) M-O⁴ P²  (-P2).</note>
                  <note>"The Lepanto of Iames the sixt, King of Scotland" and "La Lepanthe de Iaques VI· Roy d'Escosse, faicte francoise par le Sieur Du Bartas" each has separate title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lepanto, Battle of, 1571 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>HIS MAIES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIES POETI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL EXER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes at vacant houres.</p>
                  <p>AT EDINBVRGH PRINTED BY <hi>Robert Walde-graue</hi> printer to the Kings Maiestie.</p>
                  <p>Cum Priuilegio Regali.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>title page border not found in McKerrow: At left, Love wearing a crown and holding a heart; at right, Peace holding an olive branch; other decorations at top and bottom center</figDesc>
                     <p>AMOR</p>
                     <p>PAX</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PACIS alumnus</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>INFESTA malis.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="author_to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:2"/>
                  <head>THE AVTHOVR TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eceaue heere beloued Reader, a ſhort Poetique diſcourſe, which I haue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and tranſlated, from amongſt the reſt of the works of <hi>Dv'BARTAS:</hi> as a viue mirror of this laſt and moſt decreeped age. Heere ſhalt thou ſee clearlie, as in a glaſſe, the miſeries of this wauering world: to wit, the curſed nature of mankinde, and the heauie plagues of God. And ſpeciallie heere maye thou learne not to flatter thy ſelfe, in cloaking thy odious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with the delectable coulour of vertue: an errour, allace, ouer common in this hypocriticall age, not onlie in particular men of all degrees: but euen generallie in rankes, eſtates, and offices. But that this Treatiſe may ſeeme the les obſcure vnto thee, I haue inſert before the ſame, the Authours Praeface and Exord of the whole woorke, that thereby thou may rightlie conceaue the comming in of this portion thereof. And in caſe thou finde aſwel in this work, as in my <hi>LEPANTO</hi> following, many incorrect errours, both in the dytement and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thography, I muſt pray thee to accept this my reaſonable excuſe, which is this. Thou conſiders, I doubt not, that vpon the one part, I compoſed theſe things in my verie
<pb facs="tcp:8720:3"/> young and tender yeares: wherein nature, (except ſhee were a monſter) can admit no perfection. And nowe on the other parte, being of riper yeares, my burden is ſo great and continuall, without anie intermiſsion, that when my ingyne and age could, my affaires and faſherie will not permit mee, to re-mark the wrong orthography committed by the copiars of my vnlegible and ragged hand, far les to amend my proper errours: Yea ſcarſlie but at ſtollen moments, haue I the leaſure to blenk vpon any paper, and yet not that, with free and vnuexed ſpirit. Alwaies, rough and vnpoliſhed as they are, I offer them vnto thee: Which beeing well accepted, will moue mee to haſt the preſenting vnto thee, of my <hi>APO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALYPS,</hi> and alſo ſuch nomber of the <hi>PSALMES</hi> as I haue perfited: &amp; incourage mee to the ending out of the reſt. And thus (beloued Reader) recommending theſe my labours to thy freindlie acceptation: I bid thee hartelie Fare-well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:3"/>
                  <head>TO THE KING OF SCOTLAND.</head>
                  <l>VVHere others hooded with blind loue do flie,</l>
                  <l>Low on the ground with buzzard CVPIDS wings,</l>
                  <l>A heauenlie loue, from loue of loue thee brings,</l>
                  <l>And makes thy MVSE to mount aboue the skie.</l>
                  <l>Young Muſes be not woont to flie too hie,</l>
                  <l>Age taught by time, ſuch ſober ditties ſings,</l>
                  <l>But thy youth flies from loue of youthfull things,</l>
                  <l>And ſo the wings of time doth ouerflie.</l>
                  <l>Thus thou diſdainſt all worldlie wings as ſlow,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thy MVSE with Angels wings doth leaue</l>
                  <l>Times wings behind, and CVPIDS wings below,</l>
                  <l>But take thou heed, leaſt Fames wings thee deceaue.</l>
                  <l>With all thy ſpeed from Fame thou canſt not flee,</l>
                  <l>But more thou flees, the more it followes thee.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HENRIE CONSTABLE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SONET</hi> TO THE ONELY ROYAL POET.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHere ſhall the limits lye of all your fame?</l>
                     <l>Where ſhall the borders be of your renowne?</l>
                     <l>In Eaſt? or where the Sunne again goeth down?</l>
                     <l>Or ſhall the fixed Poles impale the ſame?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where ſhall the pillars which your praiſe proclame</l>
                     <l>Or Trophees ſtand, of that exſpected crowne?</l>
                     <l>The Monarch firſt, of that triumphant towne</l>
                     <l>Reuiues in you, by you renewes his name.</l>
                     <l>For that which he performd in battels bold,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To vs his bookes with wonders doth vnfold.</l>
                     <l>So we of you far more conceaue in minde,</l>
                     <l>As by your verſe we plainelie (Sir) may ſee.</l>
                     <l>You ſhall the writer and the worker be,</l>
                     <l>For to abſolue that CAESAR left behinde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>M. W. FOVLER.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Muſa Coelo beat.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:5"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>IN</hi> SERENISSIMVM INVICTISSIMVMQVE SCOTIAE REGEM JACOBVM SEXTVM.</head>
                  <lg xml:lang="grc">
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Τ</seg>ουνόματος τὶς πέζα τεοῦ χωρησεν ἐπούνους ,</l>
                     <l>Παμβασιλεῦ? σοφίας τίς κλέος αἰπὺ τεῆς?</l>
                     <l>Αρ Υπεριονίδαο σελασφόρον ἄντυγα Φοίβου</l>
                     <l>Πρῶτα θεασαμενοι? μὴ Ζεφύροιο δόμος?</l>
                     <l>Αρα πόλων κρυεροῖς πεφρικυῖαι πειρασιν ἄρκτοι,</l>
                     <l>Οψονται πτεροεν κῦδος ἔνερθε τεόν?</l>
                     <l>Σὸν δὲ πρὸς αὶθαλόεσσαν ἀνίπταται αιθερος αἴγλην</l>
                     <l>Εῦ̓χος, ἀπειρεσίου πάντα διῇξαν ὅρον.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>ΑΔΡΙΑΝΟΣ Ο ΔΑΜΜΑΝ.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="encomium">
                  <head>IDEM LATINE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>QVae Regio in terris Rex inuictiſsime laudes</l>
                     <l>Aut capiat mentis lumina clara tuae?</l>
                     <l>Anne Hyperionide qui primùm orientia Solis</l>
                     <l>Fulgura percipiunt? an Zephyritis humus?</l>
                     <l>Anne Polis quae frigutiunt glaciali bus Arcti,</l>
                     <l>Luce tuum videant conſerere arua iubar?</l>
                     <l>At tua in aetherios penetrat ſe gloria coetus,</l>
                     <l>Fecit vt immenſum totius orbis iter.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HADR. DAMMAN à BISTERVELT Gandauenſis Flander.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:6"/>
                  <head>Aliud eiuſdem.</head>
                  <l>PAllados armiferae digitis in fortibus vrbem,</l>
                  <l>Temporibus priſcis impoſuêre patres:</l>
                  <l>Scilicet auſpicijs animi, &amp; foelicibus armis,</l>
                  <l>Vrbibus immenſae conciliantur opes.</l>
                  <l>Sed meliùs numqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mentem Dea iunxit &amp; arma</l>
                  <l>Scotigenûm Regi quàm ſociata dedit:</l>
                  <l>Et quis in optandis regnum floreſcere rebus,</l>
                  <l>Et nitidos Scotis non videt ire dies?</l>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <head>TO THE KINGS MAIESTIE OF SCOTLAND.</head>
                  <l>IF ALEXANDER ſighed vvhen he came,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Tomb vvhere fierce ACHILLES lay:</l>
                  <l>If he had cauſe, that bleſſed age to blame,</l>
                  <l>Since HOMER lacks his merites to diſplay.</l>
                  <l>If he vvith teares his ſorrovves did bevvray,</l>
                  <l>To ſee his Father PHILIP conquer all,</l>
                  <l>And that more Worlds behinde there did not stay,</l>
                  <l>Which for revvard of his deſerts might fall:</l>
                  <l>Then may I mone, our times, our iudgement ſmall,</l>
                  <l>Vnvvorthy records of your ſacred skill:</l>
                  <l>Then muſt our Poets on nevv Muſes call,</l>
                  <l>To graunt them guifts to imitate your quill.</l>
                  <l>I like the flie, that burneth in the flame,</l>
                  <l>Should shevv my blindnes to attempt the ſame.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HENRIE LOK.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:6"/>
                  <head>THE EXORD, OR PREFACE OF THE SECOND VVEEK OF DVBARTAS.</head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou mightie God that of the worlde</l>
                  <l>The birth did make me ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vnfold her cradle alſo now,</l>
                  <l>Her childhead ſhow to me:</l>
                  <l>And make my Spreit to walke athort</l>
                  <l>The turning flouriſht wayes</l>
                  <l>Of ſauorie Gardens, wherinto</l>
                  <l>Still crook't but any ſtaies</l>
                  <l>Of Riuers foure the courſes quick:</l>
                  <l>Declare me what offence,</l>
                  <l>From Eden both chas'd ADAMS ſelfe</l>
                  <l>And ſeed for his pretence:</l>
                  <l>And tell who of immortall did</l>
                  <l>Himſelf a mortall macke</l>
                  <l>To bring from heauen the Antidote</l>
                  <l>To vs which we did lacke:</l>
                  <l>Giue thou me grace the ſtorie of</l>
                  <l>The Church to ſing aright,</l>
                  <l>And als the ſtorie of the Kings,</l>
                  <l>And graunt that by thy might</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:7"/>
                  <l>I guide the world vnto her graue,</l>
                  <l>My purpoſe making leſt,</l>
                  <l>Euen from the firſt of Sabboths all,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the hind moſt reſt.</l>
                  <l>Well know I that this ſurgie ſea,</l>
                  <l>Is lacking march or ground,</l>
                  <l>But ô thou holie Pilote great,</l>
                  <l>Will guide me ſafe and ſound</l>
                  <l>Vnto the port of my deſire,</l>
                  <l>Where drouked then I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Extoll thy mercies manifolde,</l>
                  <l>And pay my vowes withall.</l>
                  <l>O SACRED Floure-delis whoſe youth</l>
                  <l>Doth promiſe to vs all,</l>
                  <l>That euen thy famous Lawrels greene</l>
                  <l>Match Alexanders ſhall,</l>
                  <l>Since that (for to obey thy will,)</l>
                  <l>I flie vnto the skies,</l>
                  <l>Conuoy my courſe with louing eie,</l>
                  <l>And help the faultes that riſe</l>
                  <l>From my too blunted fruteleſſe pen,</l>
                  <l>In Pampeloun ſo ſomeday,</l>
                  <l>Mot thou win home thy crowne againe,</l>
                  <l>The which was reſt away:</l>
                  <l>So of thy neighbours euermore</l>
                  <l>Mot thou the honour be,</l>
                  <l>The loue of all thy ſubiects true,</l>
                  <l>And foes to feare for thee:</l>
                  <l>So neuer mot the heauen againſt</l>
                  <l>Thee ſhew his wrathfull face,</l>
                  <l>But the Eternall be thy arme,</l>
                  <l>His Spirit thy guiding trace:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:7"/>
                  <l>So with my ſhearing ſword in hand</l>
                  <l>And fighting at thy ſide,</l>
                  <l>Mot I ore-cled with blood and ſtoure</l>
                  <l>So boldlie by thee bide</l>
                  <l>As for to cleaue the Spaniſh Hoſt,</l>
                  <l>Or force ſome ſieged Towne,</l>
                  <l>The combat done for Virgill ſerue</l>
                  <l>To publiſh thy renowne.</l>
                  <l>GOD did not onelie (ſoueraigne Prince)</l>
                  <l>The whole command beſtow,</l>
                  <l>On our forefather ADAM of</l>
                  <l>This earth, and all below:</l>
                  <l>In making ſubject to his yoak</l>
                  <l>The skealie ſwimming race,</l>
                  <l>Who with their little ſinnes do cleaue,</l>
                  <l>The frothie Seas apace:</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that haue no other hold,</l>
                  <l>But horrour of deſerts:</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that bricoll through the waiſt</l>
                  <l>Of aire that fedders parts:</l>
                  <l>But chus'd him als a dwelling place,</l>
                  <l>Which happie was, and more</l>
                  <l>With climat temperate and faire,</l>
                  <l>The which the deintie flore</l>
                  <l>With variant ameling paimented</l>
                  <l>Of ſpringing floures moſt ſweet,</l>
                  <l>Adornd with Pomons fruicts, and als</l>
                  <l>With Zephyrs ſmells repleet:</l>
                  <l>Where God himſelf did leuell juſt,</l>
                  <l>The allees with his lyne,</l>
                  <l>Ore-couered all the hilles with trees,</l>
                  <l>With Haru'ſt the vallies ſyne,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:8"/>
                  <l>And with the ſound of thouſand brookes</l>
                  <l>Adiornd the ſweeteſt ſleepe</l>
                  <l>Made cabinets faire at proofe of Sunne</l>
                  <l>Which out his beames did keep:</l>
                  <l>He ſquared a yard, and als he did,</l>
                  <l>Plant, clenge, and labour ſyne</l>
                  <l>The euerliuing fairneſſe of</l>
                  <l>A fertill Orchard fine:</l>
                  <l>The Sacred Riuers courſes als</l>
                  <l>He parted here and there,</l>
                  <l>And with a thouſand coulors paints</l>
                  <l>The face of Meddowes faire.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="translators_invocation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:8"/>
                  <head>THE TRANSLATORS <hi>INVOCATION.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>O Thou that mightilie does toone</l>
                  <l>My warbling holie Harpe,</l>
                  <l>And does ſublime my Poëme als</l>
                  <l>That I thereon do carpe,</l>
                  <l>And marying ſo my heauenly verſe</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Harpes accords,</l>
                  <l>Inſpires my ſacred Muſe to ſing</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Lord of Lords.</l>
                  <l>O now inflame my furious Spreit,</l>
                  <l>That furiouſly I may</l>
                  <l>Theſe Furies (mankinds plagues allace!)</l>
                  <l>With furious Pen diſplay:</l>
                  <l>That I his fame doe not betray,</l>
                  <l>Who Azure Skie doth decke</l>
                  <l>With blazing lights, and on the earth</l>
                  <l>His Trophees doth erect:</l>
                  <l>The loue of Heauen, the honour of earth,</l>
                  <l>The wonder of our age,</l>
                  <l>Who whill that furious bloodie MARS</l>
                  <l>Doth in his Countrey rage</l>
                  <l>(Alluring ORPHEVS) with his ſongs</l>
                  <l>He ſweetlie doth inchaunt</l>
                  <l>The MVSES nyne to leaue their leeds</l>
                  <l>That they before did haunt</l>
                  <l>And take them to his vulgare toung,</l>
                  <l>Their Ethnique heades withall</l>
                  <l>He crownes with holie twiſts and faire</l>
                  <l>Of LIBAN Cedres tall.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:9"/>
                  <l>Then ô thou guider of my Spreit,</l>
                  <l>And leader of my pen,</l>
                  <l>Graunt, that as he his ſubject faire</l>
                  <l>Doth (liberall) to me len,</l>
                  <l>That ſo he len his loftie ſtile,</l>
                  <l>His golden draughts, his grace,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith in variant coulors he</l>
                  <l>Adornes the papers face,</l>
                  <l>That I may viuelie paint him forth:</l>
                  <l>Peace PAN, peace pratling Muſe,</l>
                  <l>Heare PHOEBVS in a borrowed tongue</l>
                  <l>His owne diſcourſes vſe.</l>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:9"/>
                  <head>THE FVRIES.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here am I caried to? in world</l>
                     <l>No more may I be found:</l>
                     <l>The earth that I do tread vpon,</l>
                     <l>And all this vaulted round,</l>
                     <l>Which bringing home, &amp; guiding back</l>
                     <l>The daies and nights againe,</l>
                     <l>Be wrathfull now with me, reguides</l>
                     <l>My longſum woe and paine:</l>
                     <l>The aire I breath by longeſt draughts,</l>
                     <l>The Sea I ſwimme into,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Is not now of the firſt borne dayes</l>
                     <l>The work moſt glorious lo.</l>
                     <l>This wretched roundnes can not be</l>
                     <l>The plenteous worlde no more,</l>
                     <l>Which God with orn'ments brauelie deckt,</l>
                     <l>So diuers and in ſtore:</l>
                     <l>No, this is but a Priſon vyle,</l>
                     <l>A Hell fulfild with fray,</l>
                     <l>And of the firſt worlde but the tombe</l>
                     <l>Moſt miſerable alway.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> O SPRITE that quickens all, great God,</l>
                     <l>That in thy juſtice maid,</l>
                     <l>(Transformd from father myld in Iudge:)</l>
                     <l>This changement that I ſaid,</l>
                     <l>Change me, and caſt me ouer againe,</l>
                     <l>Addres my feeble hand,</l>
                     <l>And make that into my diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>No humane thing may ſtand.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:10"/>
                     <l>That I thy inſtrument may bee,</l>
                     <l>And eloquentlie ſyne,</l>
                     <l>To our poſteritie may ſing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>This doolefull change of thyne.</l>
                     <l>BEFORE our firſt fore-father had,</l>
                     <l>Too impudentlie bold,</l>
                     <l>His back turnd vnto God, his face</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Serpent olde:</l>
                     <l>Euen all this WHOLE, was like vnto</l>
                     <l>Ane inſtrument in toone,</l>
                     <l>Well ſet, and well accorded iuſt:</l>
                     <l>And when as that was doone,</l>
                     <l>So learn'dlie plaid on, as the ſound <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Moſt rarelie dulce alway,</l>
                     <l>Proclam'd the praiſe of God, who on</l>
                     <l>The ſame did freedonne ay.</l>
                     <l>The man in ſeruing God, was ſeru'd</l>
                     <l>Of all the world apace:</l>
                     <l>The bodies dead and liuing als,</l>
                     <l>Did ſtriue in euerie cace</l>
                     <l>To nouriſh ſtill that holie peace,</l>
                     <l>And with ane ardent loue,</l>
                     <l>To pleaſe their double head, each other <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Embraſt for that behoue.</l>
                     <l>The loweſt of a concord bleſt</l>
                     <l>Reſounded with the hie,</l>
                     <l>The wak with dry, the cold agreed</l>
                     <l>With that which hotteſt be.</l>
                     <l>And ſyne that ſacred innocent,</l>
                     <l>The bright ASTREA Queene,</l>
                     <l>It faſtned faſt with maſtik firme,</l>
                     <l>Of holie loue that beene.</l>
                     <l>This CVPID hid, that maries yet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>By ſtraiteſt bonds and olde</l>
                     <l>The Adamant ſtone with heauie yrne,</l>
                     <l>Quick-ſiluer with the golde:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:10"/>
                     <l>The Ambre with the ſtraw or chaff,</l>
                     <l>And in the wauie raigne,</l>
                     <l>PINNE with her ſpie, the Whaile with her</l>
                     <l>That guides her through the Maine:</l>
                     <l>That makes the Sperge ſo freindlie with</l>
                     <l>The boſſe and trembling Reed,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> The Mirt with Oliue tree, the Elme</l>
                     <l>With boughs that wine doe breed.</l>
                     <l>That makes the earie Buſtard with</l>
                     <l>The galliard horſe confether,</l>
                     <l>And the Parroquets painted makes</l>
                     <l>With Wolues to liue together.</l>
                     <l>That ioynes the Moore-hen with the ſwift</l>
                     <l>And feirie futted Hart,</l>
                     <l>The Goat with Sargone, Partrichis</l>
                     <l>With Does into ane part:</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> All this is but a ſpunke, a glance,</l>
                     <l>A ſhaddow and a trace,</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a loue as raignd into</l>
                     <l>The formeſt age allace:</l>
                     <l>Where as our Muſes low from heir</l>
                     <l>With moſt harmonious ſounds,</l>
                     <l>Deuinely ſang with them aboue</l>
                     <l>Into the circled rounds.</l>
                     <l>But Man as being the ſpeciall, and</l>
                     <l>The moſt reſounding ſtring</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="90"/> Of this WHOLES Lute, too bended out</l>
                     <l>Of toone doth with it bring</l>
                     <l>The reſt of brangling ſinewes all,</l>
                     <l>As now it rendre macks,</l>
                     <l>In place of ſweet enchanting air,</l>
                     <l>So great and murmuring cracks,</l>
                     <l>As ENYON makes aſtoniſht quyte,</l>
                     <l>Euen cruell ENYON who</l>
                     <l>The old debaits of CHAOS does</l>
                     <l>Renew with greener wo.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:11"/>
                     <l>The Heauen that euer fair did blincke <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="100"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Vpon his maiſtreſſe ay,</l>
                     <l>That nought but MAN and Honny in</l>
                     <l>Her breſt did powre alway,</l>
                     <l>Now ſweeps her with his floods, and with</l>
                     <l>His yce her doſinnis quyte,</l>
                     <l>And beatis her with his haill, and gaigs</l>
                     <l>Her with his fires in ſpyte:</l>
                     <l>And with his ſnow doth make her olde,</l>
                     <l>And ielouſlie doth darde,</l>
                     <l>Both night and day vpon her bones, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="110"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>His thundring fyerie farde.</l>
                     <l>And RHEA that doth birſt for ſpyte,</l>
                     <l>And cholere in theſe daies,</l>
                     <l>A thouſand vapours blacke againſt</l>
                     <l>The Heauen now doth ſhe raiſe:</l>
                     <l>And by the port halfe open of</l>
                     <l>The gulfe profound and how,</l>
                     <l>Does ſudle all his brow with clouds,</l>
                     <l>And miſts that of her grow.</l>
                     <l>The Cocke ſenſyne doth with his voyce <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="120"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>The Lyon bold effray,</l>
                     <l>The Glead, the Chicken: and the Sheepe,</l>
                     <l>That baiſdlie trembles ay,</l>
                     <l>Flees from the rau'ning Woolfe: and in</l>
                     <l>Great NEPTVNES fleeting plaine,</l>
                     <l>The Lobſter feares for Polipus:</l>
                     <l>And Polipus againe</l>
                     <l>For Congre-Eels feares: and neertheleſſe,</l>
                     <l>The ſelfe ſame Lobſter to</l>
                     <l>Ouercums this Eele, who victor is, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="130"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Euen of her victor lo:</l>
                     <l>Yea, euen do, by a ſecret MARS,</l>
                     <l>Moſt noyſome quarrels ludge</l>
                     <l>In very ſenſeleſſe ſtocks of plants,</l>
                     <l>Reteining ſtill their grudge.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:11"/>
                     <l>Thou DENYS, euermore a childe,</l>
                     <l>O Father ſleepie ſtill,</l>
                     <l>If plant beſide the leauie keall</l>
                     <l>Thy fertill ſtocke they will,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="140"/> He drawes himſelfe abacke beliue,</l>
                     <l>And paile growne all his leaues,</l>
                     <l>For ſpite, or feare, by flight himſelfe</l>
                     <l>From neighbourhead ſuch bereaues.</l>
                     <l>As in like maner, to reuenge</l>
                     <l>The branches bearing wine,</l>
                     <l>Neere Rew, and Origane, planted keal,</l>
                     <l>By them is killed ſyne.</l>
                     <l>The tree Dodonean, and the tree</l>
                     <l>By ATTIQVE land beloued,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="150"/> The traces leaues of ancient pickes,</l>
                     <l>Remaining vnremooued</l>
                     <l>Euen in their widdow holes. O thou</l>
                     <l>Invincible debate,</l>
                     <l>That makes the one, ne liue can, where</l>
                     <l>The other liu'd of late:</l>
                     <l>That raignes into the verie tombe,</l>
                     <l>Doth to the PARQVES reſiſt,</l>
                     <l>And neuer does thy hatred waſh</l>
                     <l>In flouds of LETHES miſt.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="160"/> Euen ſo a Tambour cou'red with</l>
                     <l>A ſimple muttons skinne,</l>
                     <l>Doth burſt affraidlie, onely at</l>
                     <l>The ſound and ratling dinne</l>
                     <l>Of bloodie rauening Woolfs-skinne: And</l>
                     <l>Sick-like the trypes well throwne</l>
                     <l>Of that ſo glutton brigand, breakes</l>
                     <l>With ſecret force vnknowne</l>
                     <l>The guts of ſheepe: whome in the place</l>
                     <l>Of longſome bleating ſtill,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="170"/> They after hend their death make on,</l>
                     <l>A ſweet Lute ſpeake at will.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:12"/>
                     <l>And of the royall Egle als</l>
                     <l>The ſtrange deuouring plume,</l>
                     <l>Does wondrouſly the fethers of</l>
                     <l>All other foules conſume.</l>
                     <l>The Heauen, firſt mobile, with the ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Doth carie and remoue</l>
                     <l>More ſwifter farre then any wind,</l>
                     <l>By this his courſe aboue</l>
                     <l>The reſt of all the heauens: backdrawing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="180"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Their Torches giuing light,</l>
                     <l>From ALEXANDERS Alters, to</l>
                     <l>The Pillars HERCVLES pight.</l>
                     <l>But mortall ADAM, as the king</l>
                     <l>Of all things heere belaw,</l>
                     <l>He being ſtraied, vnto the way</l>
                     <l>Of death does all things draw:</l>
                     <l>And, blinded Pilot, on a Sea</l>
                     <l>Moſt deadlie and in fire,</l>
                     <l>This worlds Ship guides againſt the rocks <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="190"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Of furious heauenlie ire:</l>
                     <l>Which ſoftlie ſliding of before,</l>
                     <l>Was fleeting euer ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Both vnder-a skilfull Skipper, and</l>
                     <l>A Zephyre calme at will.</l>
                     <l>For or he did reuolt, he could</l>
                     <l>Not caſt his wondring eies</l>
                     <l>Vpon no part, but through it all</l>
                     <l>Almightie God he ſees.</l>
                     <l>He finds him in the earth, as to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="200"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>The Seas, he feeles him there,</l>
                     <l>Contemplats him in Heauen, and ſees</l>
                     <l>Him painted in the air.</l>
                     <l>Our world was nothing, but a great</l>
                     <l>Large Shop, that open ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Where magnifiquelie God diſplaid</l>
                     <l>His treaſures fair and good.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:12"/>
                     <l>This WHOLE was but a mirrour fair,</l>
                     <l>Which bright on euery ſide,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="210"/> The goodnes repreſented viue,</l>
                     <l>With great God that doth bide.</l>
                     <l>But man vnhappy can not find,</l>
                     <l>Since this his ſinne and fall,</l>
                     <l>Plant, ſtone, or liuing creature,</l>
                     <l>Yard, wood, nor flood at all,</l>
                     <l>Plaine, Feild, Hill, Dale, Sea, Shore, or Hauen,</l>
                     <l>Where he may draw his breath,</l>
                     <l>That hath not written into the brow</l>
                     <l>The hard doome of his death.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="220"/> In ſhort, euen all the compaſſe of</l>
                     <l>This Fabrique large and round,</l>
                     <l>Is but a very ſtore-houſe of</l>
                     <l>Gods wrath that doth abound.</l>
                     <l>Man, in rebelling thus againſt</l>
                     <l>The ſoueraigne great, I ſay,</l>
                     <l>Doth feele his ſubjects all enarm'd</l>
                     <l>Againſt him euerie way.</l>
                     <l>The air by winds ſturr'd, AMPHITRITE</l>
                     <l>Doth ſtormie make a gild,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="230"/> The Heauen moſt ſadlie black, The earth</l>
                     <l>With brierie thornes fulfild,</l>
                     <l>As fredd now from the oth of their</l>
                     <l>Fidelitie and truſt,</l>
                     <l>The honour doe reuenge on him</l>
                     <l>Euen of the Godhead juſt.</l>
                     <l>The influence maligne of ſtarres,</l>
                     <l>Coniured doth prouide,</l>
                     <l>A ſecret Hangman for to plague,</l>
                     <l>His arrogance and pride.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="240"/> The Moone doth deaze and fundie him,</l>
                     <l>Her brother roſts him quite,</l>
                     <l>The air, when he lookes for it leaſt,</l>
                     <l>Purſues him in a ſpite.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:13"/>
                     <l>By brimſtoned thunders, and by raines,</l>
                     <l>By blaſting of the cornes,</l>
                     <l>By froſts confirmd, hair-rimmes, and Snowes,</l>
                     <l>And hailſtones ſharpe as thornes.</l>
                     <l>And VVLCANE whiles fallin out of Heauen,</l>
                     <l>Whiles irritate by art,</l>
                     <l>Whiles kindled vnder richeſt roofes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="250"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>By chance in anie part,</l>
                     <l>Whiles vom'd out of a mountaine, whoſe</l>
                     <l>Tempeſtuous gulfe hath ſtore,</l>
                     <l>Both of Saltpeeter and of Pitch,</l>
                     <l>And Brimſtone byting ſore,</l>
                     <l>Doth rage againſt him: ſtartling ſtill,</l>
                     <l>For furie, as appeares,</l>
                     <l>And wrackes in leſſe ſpace then a day,</l>
                     <l>The labour-of thouſand yeares.</l>
                     <l>The Sea by her debording ſteales <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="260"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>His Iſles from him withall,</l>
                     <l>His flockes vp-ſwallows, and ore-whelmes,</l>
                     <l>His townes and makes them fall.</l>
                     <l>The Earth all wearie on her face</l>
                     <l>Such burthen for to keepe,</l>
                     <l>(A burthen curſed and prophane,)</l>
                     <l>Whiles ſinks in darkeſt deepe</l>
                     <l>A whole great countrie, and withall,</l>
                     <l>The windie tops and hie</l>
                     <l>Of proudeſt Palices, into <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="270"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Her entrailes hid they be.</l>
                     <l>IT IS in hatred euen of him,</l>
                     <l>That after manie wayes,</l>
                     <l>Shee doth ingratelie barren haru'ſts</l>
                     <l>Produce vs now a dayes.</l>
                     <l>And for the corne, that we do ſow,</l>
                     <l>(Deceitfull) doth vs pay</l>
                     <l>With thirſles burning corne, and with</l>
                     <l>The vaprous Darnell ay.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:13"/>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="280"/> And with the Fitches ſmoaring corne,</l>
                     <l>With ſticking Burres and rough,</l>
                     <l>And guylefull hope of Windle-ſtray,</l>
                     <l>That's but an emptie ſlough.</l>
                     <l>All this were little, if that, as</l>
                     <l>Step-mother cruell, ſho</l>
                     <l>Would not produce the Wort-berrie,</l>
                     <l>Our furious enemie. Lo</l>
                     <l>The Hen-bane blacke, and Ches-bow als,</l>
                     <l>That cold-ryfe doth vs keepe</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="290"/> Doufe, yeuking fleſh, and ſhuddring colde,</l>
                     <l>And makes vs euer ſleepe.</l>
                     <l>The ſtonniſhing Carpaſe, Humlocke als,</l>
                     <l>That ſmores vs by his might,</l>
                     <l>Yee-feet, Yce-hands, and makes vs isk,</l>
                     <l>And dims our cleareſt ſight.</l>
                     <l>Sardonien Percell, Sennon-drawer,</l>
                     <l>And with a laughing cheere,</l>
                     <l>The Wolfe-bane, Burne-toung, ſwelling lips,</l>
                     <l>And crying ſtill with heere.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="300"/> The weeping Aconitum, and</l>
                     <l>The Ixia binding ſore,</l>
                     <l>Sad hearted Flacke-wort, foſterer of</l>
                     <l>Hydropſie more and more.</l>
                     <l>March-Lillies als, that yeukars be,</l>
                     <l>Of flancks the gnawers rude,</l>
                     <l>The Mandragore full colde, and Ew,</l>
                     <l>That kendles vp the blude.</l>
                     <l>Plants, who doe by their root, their ſuck,</l>
                     <l>Or by their little ſeed,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="310"/> A death vnmercifull, before</l>
                     <l>The time vnto vs breed.</l>
                     <l>The Earth that knowes we loue (as we</l>
                     <l>Were bred, of brutiſh kindes,)</l>
                     <l>Our life leſſe, and our honour, then</l>
                     <l>Her mettals hid in mindes:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:14"/>
                     <l>She with her hooks, deceitfullie,</l>
                     <l>Doth mixe for vs and mell</l>
                     <l>The ſcumme of Siluer and Arsnicke:</l>
                     <l>With cruell poyſon fell</l>
                     <l>Our inward parts deuours: and ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="320"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Doth juſtlie puniſh right</l>
                     <l>Our couetous luſts with torments ſharpe,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe makes on vs light.</l>
                     <l>So as, whiles, from one onely mind,</l>
                     <l>They (fooliſh) draw apace,</l>
                     <l>The tortour of ſoule, and martring of</l>
                     <l>Our bodie both, allace.</l>
                     <l>And what more ſhall I ſay? but that</l>
                     <l>A Pilot full of skill,</l>
                     <l>And aided by the breathing of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="330"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>A friendlie wind at will,</l>
                     <l>He cannot with leſſe trauell guide</l>
                     <l>The winged fleeting Ship,</l>
                     <l>That ſoftlie on the azure ſalt</l>
                     <l>Of humide field doth ſlip.</l>
                     <l>And that the jugler fine, ſo well</l>
                     <l>Can no waies make to dance,</l>
                     <l>Make skarmuſhes, runne, and retire,</l>
                     <l>And ſyne againe aduance</l>
                     <l>His little Marmoſets, whome to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="340"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>His auarice doth giue</l>
                     <l>A Sprite, that by the onely art</l>
                     <l>And workemanſhip doth liue,</l>
                     <l>As we moſt happy did command</l>
                     <l>The ſilent flocks, that do,</l>
                     <l>All skalie, cleaue the ſtormie fluds,</l>
                     <l>That they doe ſwimme into:</l>
                     <l>And all the flying ſongſters ſweet,</l>
                     <l>And the rebellious bands,</l>
                     <l>That ruſh out through the woods, or runnes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="350"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Athwart the baireſt lands:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:14"/>
                     <l>And at the wind euen of our voyce,</l>
                     <l>They trembled faſt afraid,</l>
                     <l>And each winke of our eies, to them</l>
                     <l>A law was they obaid:</l>
                     <l>And to their holie office ſo</l>
                     <l>They bent were night and day,</l>
                     <l>As euen they vncommanded did</l>
                     <l>Vs ſeruice euery way.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="360"/> But by the ſhappering that fell out</l>
                     <l>Our Parents light among,</l>
                     <l>Alas, they of our ſlaues are now</l>
                     <l>Become our tyrants ſtrong:</l>
                     <l>The fearefull hideous Whale, if that</l>
                     <l>We ſaile vpon the Maine,</l>
                     <l>In weltring with a ſtroake, euen all</l>
                     <l>At once, the bulluring plaine,</l>
                     <l>Doth bury vnderneath the waues</l>
                     <l>Our fleeting Caſtell fair,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="370"/> That plaies the Dolphin on the Seas,</l>
                     <l>And Eagle in the air.</l>
                     <l>And if we go into the feilds,</l>
                     <l>So manie deadlie bands</l>
                     <l>Of ſpotted venoms, and of Peſts</l>
                     <l>Cyniphien, on all hands</l>
                     <l>Do lie into embuſcade dern'd.</l>
                     <l>The Wolfe on other ſide,</l>
                     <l>With Lyon, Sanglier, and with Beere</l>
                     <l>And Leopard doth abide,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="380"/> Moſt iealous of the right diuine,</l>
                     <l>Againſt their head conſpire,</l>
                     <l>And pitieleſſe teare him, in reuenge</l>
                     <l>Of the eternall ire.</l>
                     <l>The Forreſts thick, they haue no buſh,</l>
                     <l>Nor thicket great at all,</l>
                     <l>That doth not hide a hangman, to</l>
                     <l>Giue vs our death and fall.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:15"/>
                     <l>We euery cauerne do ſuſpect, and</l>
                     <l>Euery hedge we ſee,</l>
                     <l>The ſmalleſt branch, that ſtighles, makes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="390"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Vs ſore afraid to be.</l>
                     <l>If that, we dwelling be at home,</l>
                     <l>The ſpitefull Maſtie bolde,</l>
                     <l>The Bull wood-headed, and the Horſe,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe courage cannot folde,</l>
                     <l>With teeth, with horned brow, and with</l>
                     <l>Their feet do make vs warre</l>
                     <l>Moſt ſorie: ſeeing Tyrants ſuch</l>
                     <l>On earth, promenney darre.</l>
                     <l>No: There is not ſo ſmall a midge, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="400"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>That boldlie gainſt vs cleene,</l>
                     <l>Will ſpare to ſhoot the arrowes of</l>
                     <l>His little furie keene.</l>
                     <l>ALAS: what hideous fraiſome ſhapes?</l>
                     <l>What horrible ghoſts I ſee?</l>
                     <l>What thundring loud? what roring cries?</l>
                     <l>What terrible howlings hie?</l>
                     <l>Am I not on the elriſh Shore</l>
                     <l>Of PHLEGETON, braying in Hell?</l>
                     <l>O TISIPHON, MEGERE, ALECTO als, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="410"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou furie ſad and fell,</l>
                     <l>What denne makes you the cauernes quite</l>
                     <l>Moſt fraiſome and profound</l>
                     <l>Of darkeſt Hell? ô monſters moſt</l>
                     <l>Abhominable vnder ground,</l>
                     <l>Yee Miniſters of PLVTO, with</l>
                     <l>The throwne and ſtormie brow,</l>
                     <l>O Daughters of the ſhadie night,</l>
                     <l>What heere then do yee now?</l>
                     <l>The man alas, without your croſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="420"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Your whips and tortours ſore,</l>
                     <l>Doth he not feele the horrours els</l>
                     <l>Of paines anew, and more?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>For our fore-beer, no ſooner left</l>
                     <l>The ſacred ſoile of grace,</l>
                     <l>To liue into this earth, or rather</l>
                     <l>Tombe and loweſt place,</l>
                     <l>Where raignes a thouſand deaths, when as</l>
                     <l>The voice eternall ay,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="430"/> Els thundring ſummond did the troupes,</l>
                     <l>That guiltie were alway.</l>
                     <l>That Sulphurd STYX and PHLEGETON, drinks</l>
                     <l>All burning in a fire,</l>
                     <l>Thicke ACHERON, and COCYTE als,</l>
                     <l>All in a bloodie ire.</l>
                     <l>O Siſters with the eddrie haire</l>
                     <l>O Eumenids cruel yee,</l>
                     <l>What? Of your ſelues for euermore,</l>
                     <l>Will yee the tortourers be?</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="440"/> Soone quite me all the horrour of</l>
                     <l>Your curſed houſes paile,</l>
                     <l>Come vomit heere your poyſons blacke</l>
                     <l>In this vnhappy vaile.</l>
                     <l>Haue yee no feare to languiſh heere,</l>
                     <l>For exerciſes lake,</l>
                     <l>For ADAM builds you a hundreth Hels</l>
                     <l>Here for his vices ſake</l>
                     <l>FROM top to bottom eat theſe words</l>
                     <l>AVERNE all trembled apace:</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="450"/> The ſweireſt night, her horrours did</l>
                     <l>Redouble in euerie caſe.</l>
                     <l>And als that ſtincking goulfe, where fraies</l>
                     <l>Do raigne for euermore,</l>
                     <l>Was ſuddaine fil'd with pitch, with Sulphre,</l>
                     <l>And rozen in great ſtore.</l>
                     <l>The GORGONES, SPHINX, and HYDRAES, and</l>
                     <l>The Pythons, monſters rair,</l>
                     <l>The cauerns deepe did open of</l>
                     <l>Their glutton bellies thair:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:16"/>
                     <l>Euen as the fire that hid into <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="460"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>A vapour thicke remaines,</l>
                     <l>Doth grudging murmure at the cloud,</l>
                     <l>That preſsing it retaines,</l>
                     <l>Doth Cannon, thunder, aſtoniſh als,</l>
                     <l>And whirling long in round,</l>
                     <l>Doth, wrathfull, make the Element</l>
                     <l>That windie is, reſound.</l>
                     <l>Euen ſo, theſe Siſters three, theſe three</l>
                     <l>Moſt hideous rages vile,</l>
                     <l>Do raiſe a thouſand tempeſts, boun <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="470"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>To leaue their hell a whyle.</l>
                     <l>And each of them alreadie goes,</l>
                     <l>And hurles his yrnie cart,</l>
                     <l>Vpon the Bridges barres of yrne,</l>
                     <l>Ay brangling on all part.</l>
                     <l>That nine times Planks Stix, and in priſon</l>
                     <l>Where horrible darknes tumbles,</l>
                     <l>With braying, running, wandring ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Moſt terrible horrible rumbles.</l>
                     <l>Then fraifull HYDRE, and CERBERE als, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="480"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>That muttin makes a ſturre,</l>
                     <l>Who on one bodie hath the heads,</l>
                     <l>Both of a Maſtich curre,</l>
                     <l>A Serpent, Bull, and of an Ounce,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe cruell eies do pearce,</l>
                     <l>And of a Woolfe, a Horſe, a Beare,</l>
                     <l>And of a Lyoneſſe fearce.</l>
                     <l>With brangle of lights doth bark, doth whiſle,</l>
                     <l>And route doth euermore,</l>
                     <l>Make murmuring, loudlie howle and bray, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="490"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>And rummiſh faſt and rore.</l>
                     <l>Such Pell-mell dinnes, and ringing reards,</l>
                     <l>And tempeſts ſtrange to heare,</l>
                     <l>Do from one corps proceed at once,</l>
                     <l>That manie heads doth beare.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:16"/>
                     <l>Then hauing of our day atteind</l>
                     <l>Vnto the calmed port,</l>
                     <l>Then wings of Aquilo they with</l>
                     <l>A whirre more ſuddaine ſhort</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="500"/> Flee towards man: wherewith their hands</l>
                     <l>Sore tortring they aſſay,</l>
                     <l>Who cruelleſt paines can forge for him</l>
                     <l>To ſuffer euerie way.</l>
                     <l>OF ATROPOS the verie ſhape,</l>
                     <l>Lo, Hunger comes at ones,</l>
                     <l>Her blackned skinne is pearced with</l>
                     <l>The ſharpe points of her bones:</l>
                     <l>She euer greedie longing gants,</l>
                     <l>With hollow ſuncken eie,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="510"/> With cheekes togeather clapped cloſe,</l>
                     <l>And in her mouth they ſee</l>
                     <l>Her wide-ſet teeth come Saffron hew'd:</l>
                     <l>Her emptie bowels cleare,</l>
                     <l>Do through the rinckles of her skinne</l>
                     <l>Tranſparantlie appeare.</l>
                     <l>And for her bellie, hath ſhe nought</l>
                     <l>Of bellie but the place,</l>
                     <l>Her knees and elbows hideleſſe on</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="520"/> Her carcaſſe ſwels a pace.</l>
                     <l>A monſter moſt inſatiable,</l>
                     <l>Whome to, but for a fill,</l>
                     <l>All that is liuing heere below,</l>
                     <l>But skarcelie ſuffice will.</l>
                     <l>Her ſwallowing throat goes ſeeking ſtill</l>
                     <l>Her meat in verie meats:</l>
                     <l>One diſh another ſummonds, and</l>
                     <l>Her gourmand entrails eats,</l>
                     <l>And toomes at once. The verie fleſh</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="530"/> Euen of her children young,</l>
                     <l>May skantlie ſtanch her raging luſt,</l>
                     <l>Thus of her hunger ſprung:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:17"/>
                     <l>But euen ſometimes (ô gluttonie</l>
                     <l>Of ſtrangeſt ſort and rare)</l>
                     <l>To fill her foule-ſome guts, to eat</l>
                     <l>Her guts ſhe doth not ſpare:</l>
                     <l>That ſhe thereby, may make it more,</l>
                     <l>She makes her body leſſe,</l>
                     <l>And to our father cruell ſo,</l>
                     <l>She doth her ſelfe addreſſe.</l>
                     <l>And furthermore, from hels ſhe brings <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="540"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Vnto this combat heere,</l>
                     <l>The rage, the weaknes, and the thriſt,</l>
                     <l>Her likeſt ſiſters deere.</l>
                     <l>THE warre comes after, bruzing lawes,</l>
                     <l>And bruzing maners all,</l>
                     <l>Loue-teares, ſhed-blood, and burning Innes,</l>
                     <l>And raizing euery wall:</l>
                     <l>In-under his braſen feet, the earth</l>
                     <l>All creepes and trembles faſt,</l>
                     <l>His mouth it is a firie coale, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="550"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>His voice a thunders blaſt:</l>
                     <l>Each finger of his hand, it is</l>
                     <l>A Cannon that doth bray,</l>
                     <l>And euerie awfull looke of his</l>
                     <l>A lightning flaming ay.</l>
                     <l>The great diſorder, and the fray,</l>
                     <l>Diſpair, and flight, do poſte,</l>
                     <l>And winged euer, go before</l>
                     <l>His cruell murthering Hoſte:</l>
                     <l>As burnings, and the ſwelling pride, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="560"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>And great impietie vile,</l>
                     <l>The quarrelous ſciſme, ſacke, and all</l>
                     <l>Impunitie for a while.</l>
                     <l>The crueltie, the horrour, the</l>
                     <l>Deſtruction and ruine,</l>
                     <l>Though all accompanie him, whereas</l>
                     <l>He barbrous marches ſyne.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:17"/>
                     <l>The doole, the ſolitarines, with</l>
                     <l>The pouertie that peeps,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="570"/> The bloodie footſteps of his hoſt</l>
                     <l>Vndaunted following keeps.</l>
                     <l>AND if that I be not deceau'd,</l>
                     <l>Another furie lo</l>
                     <l>That doth a battrie dreſſe againſt</l>
                     <l>Our firſt forefather to,</l>
                     <l>Of thouſand thouſand Cannons, I</l>
                     <l>Heare, feele, though not in ſight,</l>
                     <l>The more that ſhe is weake, the more</l>
                     <l>Hath ſhe of force and might:</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="580"/> All vlcer'd, feuerous, blind, and fond,</l>
                     <l>And fooliſh is ſhe nam'de.</l>
                     <l>Sad, deafe, crooke-backed, and of legs</l>
                     <l>And armes, both is ſhe lam'de.</l>
                     <l>The poyſon with the manie names,</l>
                     <l>Deaths miniſter alace,</l>
                     <l>That comes at poſting gallope, and</l>
                     <l>Returnes at ſloweſt pace.</l>
                     <l>Il-fauoured, troubling reſt, and als</l>
                     <l>Fantaſtike, miſerable eke,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="590"/> She kils, but cracke betraies the heart,</l>
                     <l>Vnſatiable blood doth ſeeke</l>
                     <l>The daughter of intemperance, and</l>
                     <l>Of Heauen miſorder'd cleene,</l>
                     <l>A cruell euill diſcouerd, but</l>
                     <l>More cruell hid vnſeene.</l>
                     <l>IN SOMMER Meidowes, Graſhoppers</l>
                     <l>Haue not ſo many aboue,</l>
                     <l>So manie Creikets vnder, as did</l>
                     <l>Infernall voyces moue,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="600"/> And murmure round about, nor vnder</l>
                     <l>A calmed Heauen and ſtill,</l>
                     <l>The King enamailed of the people,</l>
                     <l>That gather Honnie will:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:18"/>
                     <l>So many little buzzing burds</l>
                     <l>Guides not, when he doth caſt</l>
                     <l>Euen of his little hollow ludge</l>
                     <l>The firſt foundations faſt,</l>
                     <l>As this effraying monſter hath</l>
                     <l>Of Soldats at command,</l>
                     <l>That raging charge the man abaiſd <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="610"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>At euery part and hand.</l>
                     <l>So as a regiment incens'd,</l>
                     <l>And horrible giuing fraies,</l>
                     <l>Now for to yoke a skarmiſh hot,</l>
                     <l>The firſt of all aſſaies</l>
                     <l>Gainſt ADAMS head, which is the houſe</l>
                     <l>Moſt holy hallowed ay,</l>
                     <l>Of all the faculties of the ſoule,</l>
                     <l>And reaſons forth, and ſtay.</l>
                     <l>A King that neighbour will bereaue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="620"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Another Kings Empire,</l>
                     <l>Before he fight into the feilds,</l>
                     <l>Or open warres deſire,</l>
                     <l>He firſt corrupts by richeſt gifts</l>
                     <l>His Counſels truth at length,</l>
                     <l>Well knowing that a Counſell good</l>
                     <l>Is of a King the ſtrength.</l>
                     <l>Euen ſo, this Furie baniſht from</l>
                     <l>The CHAOS darke and low,</l>
                     <l>Do for Forerinners, Freneſie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="630"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>And Madnes als let go:</l>
                     <l>Whereof the one in heating much,</l>
                     <l>The other drying ſore</l>
                     <l>The weake braines, they do ſtop the courſe,</l>
                     <l>And blunt do more and more</l>
                     <l>The ſharpnes of mans judgement, and</l>
                     <l>Engrauing makes remaine</l>
                     <l>(Abuſers) in the Spreit, a Squadre</l>
                     <l>Of CHIMERS fancies vaine.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:18"/>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="640"/> The CAROS, POPLESIE, and the</l>
                     <l>LETHARGIE ſleeping ay,</l>
                     <l>As caſten of hazarders, aſſailes</l>
                     <l>Their foe the beſt they may,</l>
                     <l>At former part, but yet by armes,</l>
                     <l>That are contrary clene,</l>
                     <l>For making yci-colde the braines,</l>
                     <l>His brethren doſened bene,</l>
                     <l>And makes the liuing man like to</l>
                     <l>A dead in euery ſort,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="650"/> If of forgetfull LETHE, he</l>
                     <l>Do not repaſſe the port.</l>
                     <l>The Palſie els doth vndertake</l>
                     <l>A warre and battaile bolde,</l>
                     <l>Els Spaſmus ſturres, the one doth ſlacke,</l>
                     <l>The other ſtrait doth holde</l>
                     <l>The Senewes of weake ADAM, els</l>
                     <l>They doe the paſſage dit,</l>
                     <l>Vnto the liuing ſubtill Spreits,</l>
                     <l>That would go downe by it.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="660"/> Then euen as he, who hand to hand,</l>
                     <l>And onely man to man</l>
                     <l>Com'd to a Combat ſet, aſſaies</l>
                     <l>All kind of wards he can,</l>
                     <l>Eſchewes, rebaits, ſtrikes out, and doth</l>
                     <l>Obſerue his times aright,</l>
                     <l>And caſting whiles, doth make vpon</l>
                     <l>The ſparkling eies to light</l>
                     <l>Of this his foe his clocke, ſyne with</l>
                     <l>The farre end of his blead,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="670"/> Doth ſteadfaſt make his life to part</l>
                     <l>In guſhing ſtreames and read.</l>
                     <l>The ſicknes, to the end that ſhe</l>
                     <l>May haue the better skair,</l>
                     <l>Of our forefather tied to bed</l>
                     <l>(Who ſcarſe can turne him thair)</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:19"/>
                     <l>Els with ſo many bonds ſhe doth,</l>
                     <l>The Ophthalmie let go,</l>
                     <l>Which with a ſeething blood within</l>
                     <l>The ſight as cruell ſo,</l>
                     <l>Giues thouſand ſtogs, ſhe alſo breeds <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="680"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>The Pearle vpon the eie,</l>
                     <l>That dimmes the ſhine, and Cataract,</l>
                     <l>That darke and cloudie bee:</l>
                     <l>Whereof the one by gathering of</l>
                     <l>To groſſe ane humour pight</l>
                     <l>Within the bright Spreits guider, doth</l>
                     <l>The dore cloſe of the light.</l>
                     <l>The other doth as with a cloath,</l>
                     <l>Enuious ſyle and hide,</l>
                     <l>The Chriſtall ſhining humour, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="690"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Doth in his eies abide.</l>
                     <l>This done, euen with a gird to our</l>
                     <l>Fore-beer flees withall,</l>
                     <l>This cruell Dragon mercileſſe,</l>
                     <l>Whome ſqueinancy they call:</l>
                     <l>That ſcoaps vnto his throat, and with</l>
                     <l>Blood loppred lacking heat,</l>
                     <l>He hauing of the how-throat bolle,</l>
                     <l>The Muskles boldned great:</l>
                     <l>In him alone doth giue a proofe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="700"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Of his ſo obſtinate ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>Wherewith he is to fight, againſt</l>
                     <l>His future race at length.</l>
                     <l>Like HERCVLES, who when as yet,</l>
                     <l>In ſwadling cloathes he lay,</l>
                     <l>Buire on his brow engrau'd his great</l>
                     <l>Vndaunted courage ay:</l>
                     <l>Beginning with his hands, no hand</l>
                     <l>But ſtrongeſt turkeſſe els,</l>
                     <l>Moſt boldlie wraithfull for to ſmoare <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="710"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>The Dragon bearing ſhels,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:19"/>
                     <l>A maiſter ſtick that promiſes</l>
                     <l>The Trophee Lernien ſure,</l>
                     <l>The Spaignoll triumph, and the firre</l>
                     <l>Cleonien that they bure.</l>
                     <l>The ſecond regiment ſets on</l>
                     <l>By deadlie forces fell,</l>
                     <l>Beginning with the Squadre of all</l>
                     <l>The vitall partes to mell;</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="720"/> That in the ſtomack camped are.</l>
                     <l>And els that humour groſſe</l>
                     <l>Lights-ſtopper, him ASTHMATIQVE makes</l>
                     <l>Ay panting in a Croſſe.</l>
                     <l>And the Corrozîue flowing of</l>
                     <l>A gutter dropping ſlow,</l>
                     <l>His ſpongious lightes doth vlcerate, and</l>
                     <l>Him dries cum'd Ptiſick ſo.</l>
                     <l>The Peripneumonie withall</l>
                     <l>A hote conſuming braize,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="730"/> Goes cruell in his breathing boares</l>
                     <l>And heat doth kendle and raize.</l>
                     <l>And als the pittileſſe Empiem doth</l>
                     <l>Him ſeaſe among the reſt,</l>
                     <l>With an Apoſtume filling vp</l>
                     <l>The howeſt of his breſt.</l>
                     <l>And furthermore the Pleuriſie</l>
                     <l>Doth brod him in the ſides,</l>
                     <l>In making euer boile that blood</l>
                     <l>Which vnder his ribbes abides.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="740"/> The Mare therefter ſmores him and</l>
                     <l>With thickeſt fleume doth he,</l>
                     <l>As Spreit importune, heauie, preſſe</l>
                     <l>His breſt that panting be.</l>
                     <l>MY GVIDE Vrania oracle</l>
                     <l>That chaſsis errors vaine,</l>
                     <l>Name me this warriour trembling ay,</l>
                     <l>For furie and diſdaine.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:20"/>
                     <l>And whoſe enarmed hand doth not,</l>
                     <l>With firie torch aſſaile,</l>
                     <l>The wings but euen the armies heart <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="750"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>And ouer it doth preuaile.</l>
                     <l>Who for hir campions hath the Cough,</l>
                     <l>The irkeſum ganting lo,</l>
                     <l>The Souning ſwerfis, thriſt, ſhuddering, and</l>
                     <l>The colde-rife trembling to.</l>
                     <l>The bating of the pulſe, the heat,</l>
                     <l>The rauing ſtrange withall</l>
                     <l>And paine of head. O is not this</l>
                     <l>The furie whome we call</l>
                     <l>The burning perrilous Feuer, who <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="760"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Inconſtantlie doth take</l>
                     <l>Mo faces then VERTVMNVS, and</l>
                     <l>Who (fine) her ſelf can make</l>
                     <l>Continuall whiles, whiles tierce, whiles quart,</l>
                     <l>And whiles but for a day,</l>
                     <l>Whiles ſlow, whiles kindled vp, euen as</l>
                     <l>The mater as they ſay</l>
                     <l>Which in our feeble bodies is</l>
                     <l>The cauſe of all this change,</l>
                     <l>Hath ſlow, or promptlie readie hath <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="770"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>This ſecreet motion ſtrange.</l>
                     <l>Well ought I for to know thee, ô</l>
                     <l>Thou traitrous maſtiſh vile,</l>
                     <l>Who four yeares had thee in my hart,</l>
                     <l>For hoſteſſe all the while.</l>
                     <l>So as I beare as yet euen of</l>
                     <l>Thy greateſt force, allace,</l>
                     <l>The markes into my ſoule, and in</l>
                     <l>The bodie manie a trace.</l>
                     <l>For leauing that thou ſoucked out, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="780"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>And cruellie did ſeeke</l>
                     <l>The blood out of my veines, and of</l>
                     <l>My bones the Marrey eik,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:20"/>
                     <l>I of my Spreit the vertue feele</l>
                     <l>All ſlokened to be fall,</l>
                     <l>The vigour of my Spreit cum'd gourd,</l>
                     <l>The ſharpnes blunted all.</l>
                     <l>And als my memorie, the which</l>
                     <l>Was ſomewhat yet before,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="790"/> Is like (ô dolour juſt) vnto</l>
                     <l>The water, where a ſcore</l>
                     <l>Is als ſone vaniſht quite as drawne.</l>
                     <l>Yea, ſurelie, I almoſt</l>
                     <l>My former ſtudies, to my ſhame,</l>
                     <l>And greateſt grief, haue loſt.</l>
                     <l>And als my Spreit a Table like,</l>
                     <l>That voide, hath but a frame,</l>
                     <l>Like Coruin, Trapeſuntius, or</l>
                     <l>Like Gaze, forgot my name,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="800"/> That Greek, whoſe learned voice, and whoſe</l>
                     <l>Moſt facond hand and pen,</l>
                     <l>Did teach the Romane language to</l>
                     <l>The verie Romane men.</l>
                     <l>And for that cauſe in ſpite of my</l>
                     <l>Moſt carefull ſtudies ay,</l>
                     <l>My verſe are feuerous now become,</l>
                     <l>By habitude alway.</l>
                     <l>Verſe, ſometimes animated, with</l>
                     <l>A furie moſt deuine,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="810"/> And ſometimes ſhuddering, with a moſt</l>
                     <l>Vnlearned coldneſſe ſyne.</l>
                     <l>BVT OF the Regiment that is third</l>
                     <l>The cruell Squadres fall,</l>
                     <l>Vnto the quarter, that conteines</l>
                     <l>The vertues naturall all:</l>
                     <l>The vertues that do piece and piece</l>
                     <l>Moſt happely procure,</l>
                     <l>Als-well our nouriſhment, as our</l>
                     <l>Vp-growing alway ſure.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:21"/>
                     <l>The Boulime whiles, whiles lacks of meat <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="820"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Through ANOREXIA will,</l>
                     <l>Dog-hunger whiles, whiles lyes his meat</l>
                     <l>Through BRADIPEPSIA ſtill.</l>
                     <l>Whiles ſhe that makes the appetite,</l>
                     <l>So monſtrous and ſo great,</l>
                     <l>In how parts of our ſtomack, doth</l>
                     <l>She take her lodging ſeat.</l>
                     <l>Then after with the Liuer doth</l>
                     <l>The ſaffrond Gulſoch fight,</l>
                     <l>For hauing ſtopt way to the Gall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="830"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Chollerick, by his might</l>
                     <l>He doth his kindled venome skaill</l>
                     <l>Throughout the corps. (In place</l>
                     <l>Of fineſt blood.) which outwardlie</l>
                     <l>Turnes yeallow hewed apace.</l>
                     <l>In contrare doufe Hydropſie makes</l>
                     <l>Him like for colde to ſterue,</l>
                     <l>Whill time it make the Fleume in place</l>
                     <l>Of pureſt blood to ſerue.</l>
                     <l>But I the ſliddrie bowels ſee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="840"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Below (allace) by foes</l>
                     <l>Aſſaild, that are a thouſand times</l>
                     <l>Far mutinaire then thoſe:</l>
                     <l>The Colick with hir preſon'd windes</l>
                     <l>Breids them a raging paine,</l>
                     <l>The dolour Iliack doth throw</l>
                     <l>Them ſore, moſt inhumaine</l>
                     <l>Doth ſtop their purging conduits, and</l>
                     <l>Deteſtable ſhe makes</l>
                     <l>Euen of manns mouth a peſtilent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="850"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>And filthie ſtinking jakes.</l>
                     <l>The read diſſenterie all enarmd</l>
                     <l>With throwings ſore againe,</l>
                     <l>Doth painefullie draw out the blood</l>
                     <l>Of manie an opned vaine.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:21"/>
                     <l>The Stonie grauell doth the neares</l>
                     <l>On other part inuade,</l>
                     <l>By gathering of an humour, which</l>
                     <l>The rigour of heat hath made</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="860"/> To change into a Stone, which ſtops</l>
                     <l>(Malicious) without more</l>
                     <l>The ſliddrie vreter, carier of</l>
                     <l>Salt vrine skalding ſore,</l>
                     <l>Euen as the Diabete doth, by</l>
                     <l>The contrair louſe at laſt</l>
                     <l>The greace of all our bodie in</l>
                     <l>The vrine ſeething faſt,</l>
                     <l>And cauſing thirſt, diſtils as much,</l>
                     <l>As all the matter may,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="870"/> Full bruddie furniſh raine vnto</l>
                     <l>The gutter running ay.</l>
                     <l>And to the members that vs makes,</l>
                     <l>For ages following heere,</l>
                     <l>Leaue of our bodies dead, ſo quicke</l>
                     <l>And manie Mirrours cleere,</l>
                     <l>Yoakes fiercely the vnablenes</l>
                     <l>To liue in VENVS law:</l>
                     <l>And the continuall flowing of</l>
                     <l>The ſeed vnripe and raw.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="880"/> Who preaſis (reſtleſſe Tyrants) for</l>
                     <l>To leeſe and to deſtroy</l>
                     <l>The vnconceaued Babes thereby,</l>
                     <l>Their Parents to anoy.</l>
                     <l>THE SQADRE fourt, wherein the Chouks,</l>
                     <l>As Soldats do remaine,</l>
                     <l>The vile deuouring Cancer, and</l>
                     <l>The Gout a cruell paine,</l>
                     <l>Together with the Hyues, and with</l>
                     <l>The boudned Oedems cleare,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="890"/> Plouks, Shirres, and atrie Phlegmons, ſends</l>
                     <l>A hundreth brags with beare</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:22"/>
                     <l>Vnto the place aſsieged, and ſyne,</l>
                     <l>Their blind rage doth them make,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe they cannot harme the fort,</l>
                     <l>The plaine field for to ſacke.</l>
                     <l>From hand in ſheath ô cruell foes,</l>
                     <l>Your mightleſſe Swords let fall,</l>
                     <l>The death a thouſand times hath both</l>
                     <l>Of blood and ſenews all,</l>
                     <l>Bereft your foe, and nought the leſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="900"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Without all hold or ſtay</l>
                     <l>Your pitileſſe hand his beautie doth</l>
                     <l>Diſhonour euery way</l>
                     <l>His members all makes laidlie, and does</l>
                     <l>With blunted knife beginne</l>
                     <l>To ſaw his joynts, and Leiths, and for</l>
                     <l>To hacke his wrinckled skinne.</l>
                     <l>I thinke I ſee into the mid'ſt</l>
                     <l>Of wilde and open lands,</l>
                     <l>Of Wolues, and ſuttle Foxes als <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="910"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>The cruell craftie bands,</l>
                     <l>Who hauing on the ſofteſt Sand,</l>
                     <l>By chance of meeting found</l>
                     <l>The Lyon ſtreaked, who on lyue</l>
                     <l>Commanded all the ground,</l>
                     <l>And whoſe moſt horrible auſtrun face</l>
                     <l>(Retaining former ſpite)</l>
                     <l>Did melt a far, euen with his beames,</l>
                     <l>Their former boldnes quite:</l>
                     <l>They (cruell) teare him, and againſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="920"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Their King that is deceaſed,</l>
                     <l>Affraidly prooues, to practiſe that,</l>
                     <l>Whereat, they feeblie preaſed.</l>
                     <l>Shall I among theſe dwynings count,</l>
                     <l>(Whoſe cruell boldnes fell,</l>
                     <l>Seemes, as it were, with outward ſcroofe</l>
                     <l>Of vexed man to mell?)</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:22"/>
                     <l>The ouglie lowſie Phtiriaſe: ô</l>
                     <l>The ſhamefull plague and vile,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="930"/> That euen makes Kings more filthie then</l>
                     <l>Their Beggers all the while:</l>
                     <l>Who clad with clouts, and eaten vp</l>
                     <l>With Vermin euer ſtill:</l>
                     <l>Both night and day, for yeuking are</l>
                     <l>Compel'd to fidge their fill.</l>
                     <l>Kings ſwarming all with Lice, when as</l>
                     <l>The rubbing cannot ſtay,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet oft changed beds can giue</l>
                     <l>Them ſlaiking any way.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="940"/> For euen as from a Surge, the Waues</l>
                     <l>Are ſliding after Waues:</l>
                     <l>So ſwarme doth follow after ſwarme,</l>
                     <l>Their fleſh too fertill craues</l>
                     <l>His owne deuourers to produce,</l>
                     <l>And whill ſpent be the blood,</l>
                     <l>It of it ſelfe the ſelfe doth make</l>
                     <l>The execrable food.</l>
                     <l>But what? Thinke not that Fortune blind,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe turning Wheele ſtill ſlides.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="950"/> The Campe of third EVMENIDE fell</l>
                     <l>Confus'dlie pell-mell guides:</l>
                     <l>I of her Soldats ſee, who as</l>
                     <l>Conducted well by reaſon,</l>
                     <l>Makes choyce, aſwell of nature, age,</l>
                     <l>As of the quartered ſeaſon,</l>
                     <l>The Portugall is bruddie ſo,</l>
                     <l>In Phtiſiques as we ſee,</l>
                     <l>The Ebre in Chouks, the Arne in thoſe</l>
                     <l>That Epilepticke be:</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="960"/> One Inde into Grangores, Sauoy in</l>
                     <l>Goitrous doth abound,</l>
                     <l>In peſt-folkes Sardine, Lepruſe are</l>
                     <l>In Aegypt many found.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:23"/>
                     <l>The places manners like, or the</l>
                     <l>Strong influence aloft</l>
                     <l>Of mightie Heauen that gouerns all.</l>
                     <l>So tender childhood ſoft,</l>
                     <l>Is gnawn with Wormes, the children that</l>
                     <l>Their rawnes gender will,</l>
                     <l>And for their weakenes hes their wombe,</l>
                     <l>That looſe runnes euer ſtill:</l>
                     <l>The Skall vpon their head doth of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="970"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Their ſalteſt fleumes proceed.</l>
                     <l>They for a time beare many a blybe,</l>
                     <l>Of worſſome that doth breed</l>
                     <l>Euen of the menſtruall humour, which</l>
                     <l>As new wine raging faſt,</l>
                     <l>In ſeething in the bodie, makes</l>
                     <l>A plouckie skinne at laſt.</l>
                     <l>The youth into Hemorragie</l>
                     <l>Moſt eaſilie doth fall,</l>
                     <l>In Feuers hot, in Dwinings, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="980"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>In Phreneſie withall.</l>
                     <l>And feeble age hath commonly</l>
                     <l>For his too irkſome Hoſts,</l>
                     <l>The coldrife bloodleſſe ſhakings, and</l>
                     <l>The faſhious coughing hoaſts,</l>
                     <l>Katharres and Gouts. So likewiſe the</l>
                     <l>Sciaticke, hard to mend</l>
                     <l>The Feuer, that the humour of</l>
                     <l>Melancolie doth ſend.</l>
                     <l>The bloodie fluxis, Peſts, and als <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="990"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>The watrie ſwelling great,</l>
                     <l>Are nuriſhed with vs when weake</l>
                     <l>Autumnus brookes his ſeat.</l>
                     <l>The Fike, the Skab, the Langour als</l>
                     <l>Of ALCIDE doth vs take,</l>
                     <l>And raging charge vs in the ſpring,</l>
                     <l>That both is hot and wake.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:23"/>
                     <l>And then the Diarrhee, with the</l>
                     <l>Hot-euill, a ſeeknes ſore,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1000"/> Aſſailleth vs importunatlie</l>
                     <l>In Sommer euermore.</l>
                     <l>As Pleuriſie, the hoaſt and rheume</l>
                     <l>Do ſeeldome make repaire,</l>
                     <l>But couered with the whiteſt flocks</l>
                     <l>Of heauenlie fethers fair,</l>
                     <l>And Souldiers ſweirlie keeping home</l>
                     <l>Into the houſe do hold</l>
                     <l>Of gelded ſonne to aigit yeir,</l>
                     <l>Thair garniſon full cold.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1010"/> And ſome I ſee (whoſe venome doth</l>
                     <l>Delite but in a throng)</l>
                     <l>Vnleauing of the firſt from corps</l>
                     <l>To corps to ſlide along,</l>
                     <l>As the Ameriquain, and als</l>
                     <l>The Leproſie, and Byle,</l>
                     <l>The Phtiſie, meſels, and the peſts</l>
                     <l>Red Charbucle and vyle.</l>
                     <l>And further ſome I ſee, which for</l>
                     <l>Sadd heritage, allace,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1020"/> We (ſeiklie) leaue our ſonnes, which they</l>
                     <l>From age to age embrace.</l>
                     <l>The Choakes and Goitre both into</l>
                     <l>That ranke they euer ſtood,</l>
                     <l>The Gout, the Grauell, Leproſie,</l>
                     <l>With all that ſpilles the blood,</l>
                     <l>Rumburſnes, white Hydropſie als,</l>
                     <l>The languiſhing Ptiſie eik,</l>
                     <l>The Epilepſie dead withall,</l>
                     <l>Bred of a vaprous reik.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1030"/> For the effect ſucceſsiue of thair</l>
                     <l>Venome vneſpied,</l>
                     <l>Is to the flowing Sperma of</l>
                     <l>Their fathers ſurelie tied.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:24"/>
                     <l>But ô allace: what ſtratagems,</l>
                     <l>What ſtrongeſt armes can we</l>
                     <l>Now vſe againſt thoſe warriours, who</l>
                     <l>Deceatfull traitours be.</l>
                     <l>I meane theſe traiterous paines whome art,</l>
                     <l>As moſt imperfite knowes</l>
                     <l>Not by the name, but onely by, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1040"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Effects that thereof growes.</l>
                     <l>Such as the ſuffocation of</l>
                     <l>The bruddie matrice quick,</l>
                     <l>The Swowning wan, and skunnering euill</l>
                     <l>That skailles conuentions thick.</l>
                     <l>When as a vapour, I know not what,</l>
                     <l>Long keeped cloſe I trow,</l>
                     <l>Into, I know not what a part,</l>
                     <l>It doth, I know not how.</l>
                     <l>Can he eſchew the cruelties <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1050"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Fulfild with craftie wyles</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe ſo obſtinate ills, who are,</l>
                     <l>Abuſers by their gyles</l>
                     <l>Of cunning med'ceners hands, and who</l>
                     <l>Once from the bodie chaſed,</l>
                     <l>Are in the half dead members vnder</l>
                     <l>An other name replaced.</l>
                     <l>Or rather Schollers euen of the</l>
                     <l>Fond Metempſichoſis ſtraunge.</l>
                     <l>Teacht by that SAMIEN learnd. The one <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1060"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Doth metamorphoſd change</l>
                     <l>In far worſe ill. Cum'd either of</l>
                     <l>Th'affinity that doth lye,</l>
                     <l>Twixt fattiſh humors or betwixt,</l>
                     <l>The members vext thereby:</l>
                     <l>Or els through the vnlearnd abuſe,</l>
                     <l>Or the malitious greed,</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe that of Apollos arte,</l>
                     <l>Are practiſers indeed.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:24"/>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1070"/> Euen as the ſturdie that transformd.</l>
                     <l>And changd is euerie way</l>
                     <l>In Falling-ill, the Rage into</l>
                     <l>Lethargie ſleeping ay.</l>
                     <l>The conſtitution ill into,</l>
                     <l>Hydropeſie full colde,</l>
                     <l>The Slee-ping dulnes oft transform'd</l>
                     <l>In Palſie doth vs holde.</l>
                     <l>Short ADAM like a Hart is who</l>
                     <l>Doth in a wodds nuik ſtay,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1080"/> And thruſting in into the ſoile</l>
                     <l>Is at the latter bay</l>
                     <l>All teared with lyam-hounds, whome of</l>
                     <l>The one doth bite his back,</l>
                     <l>One pulles his flanke, an other at</l>
                     <l>His breaſt dooth buſsie ſnack:</l>
                     <l>One ſcoupes vnto his throate, and one</l>
                     <l>His fouch is loath to leaue</l>
                     <l>One holds his eare, and one vnto</l>
                     <l>His neck doth hinging cleaue.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1090"/> He als is like a mightie Bull,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe pridefull horne doth egg,</l>
                     <l>The ſleeprie byting little ſwarmes</l>
                     <l>Of manie a ſpitefull cleg:</l>
                     <l>Who bumming do come out, and their</l>
                     <l>Aſſailer do aſſaile,</l>
                     <l>And valiauntlie doe on his skin</l>
                     <l>Their Squadre campe and naile,</l>
                     <l>The Bull doth with his forked head,</l>
                     <l>The windes beat euery where,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1100"/> The ground ſcraps with his cloves, his taile</l>
                     <l>His ſydes beates heere and there.</l>
                     <l>And flying longs both forreſts, rocks,</l>
                     <l>And forcie ſtreames and clenches,</l>
                     <l>The place where he receaued his hurt,</l>
                     <l>But not his hurts eſchewes.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:25"/>
                     <l>In end, with needels ouercled,</l>
                     <l>Behoues him to be ſlaine,</l>
                     <l>Or at the leaſt as dead into</l>
                     <l>That place for to remaine.</l>
                     <l>For man he is inuaded with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1110"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>A thouſand langors ſore,</l>
                     <l>And euery other liuing thing</l>
                     <l>It gets a proofe no more</l>
                     <l>But of a verie few of euils:</l>
                     <l>The falln-ill onlie aſſailes,</l>
                     <l>The Squadres gatherers of the hoat</l>
                     <l>And the Venerian Quailes.</l>
                     <l>The ſheepe doth feare the skab, and als</l>
                     <l>The dulling Sturdie ſtill,</l>
                     <l>The dog-ill, and the Madneſſe they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1120"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Oppres the maſtiſh will.</l>
                     <l>And further, euerie one of them</l>
                     <l>Before his birth doth beare,</l>
                     <l>Of ſtrongeſt ſimples knawledge ſuch</l>
                     <l>As they haue need to leare.</l>
                     <l>And neuer doth he feele his euill</l>
                     <l>Steale neare to him ſo ſoone,</l>
                     <l>But he als ſone the remedie</l>
                     <l>Hath readie to be done.</l>
                     <l>For the ſlow-paſt Shelpaddock hath <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1130"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Humlock icie-colde,</l>
                     <l>To ſerue for ſoueraigne remedy.</l>
                     <l>The Ramme doth rightlie hold</l>
                     <l>The Rhew his counter-poiſon, and</l>
                     <l>The Sacred Lawrell tree,</l>
                     <l>For Reubarb ſerues to Partrich, Merle,</l>
                     <l>And Gea that painted be,</l>
                     <l>The Beare for medicine meet for him,</l>
                     <l>The Mandragore obſerues.</l>
                     <l>And the Marcellian crommie for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1140"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Lucinas Goates it ſerues.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:25"/>
                     <l>But we are ignorant of all,</l>
                     <l>Euen after hauing had</l>
                     <l>Acquired in bookes a knowledge, that</l>
                     <l>Sophiſtique is and bad.</l>
                     <l>An art ay ſnappring, and withall,</l>
                     <l>A knowledge quite vnknowne,</l>
                     <l>Which neuer enters but into</l>
                     <l>The hoarie heads, and thrown</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1150"/> Of men who worne, and broken with</l>
                     <l>A labour too ingrate,</l>
                     <l>In ſeeking others healthes, they leeſe</l>
                     <l>Their owne, ſuch is their ſtate:</l>
                     <l>Or rather, who do make themſelues,</l>
                     <l>By others perrils ſore,</l>
                     <l>Full famous Doctors, and by drinks</l>
                     <l>Vntimous doe they ſtore,</l>
                     <l>And fill with Hillocks the Church-yard,</l>
                     <l>And lacking feare or ſhame,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1160"/> Do bourreaus make themſelues be paid,</l>
                     <l>For murthers made by thame.</l>
                     <l>I doe not ſpeake heere of the good,</l>
                     <l>The learned and the wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Into whoſe hearts, the feare of God</l>
                     <l>Imprinted deepely lies,</l>
                     <l>And who doe skilfully within</l>
                     <l>Our bodies ſtay and tie,</l>
                     <l>Our ſpreits of life, that otherwiſe,</l>
                     <l>Were readie out to flie:</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1170"/> For I doe ſurely honor theſe,</l>
                     <l>As heauenly men celeſt,</l>
                     <l>Healthes leaning ſtocks, and banniſhers</l>
                     <l>Of euery death and Peſt.</l>
                     <l>Dame Natures counſellers, and the</l>
                     <l>Almighties agents ay,</l>
                     <l>And Stewards, and Store-maiſters wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Of flouriſhing age alway.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:26"/>
                     <l>But if that any paine by art</l>
                     <l>Of man may ſlaked be,</l>
                     <l>Theſe learned learn'd it haue euen of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1180"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Their Colledge dumme we ſee:</l>
                     <l>For we doe the Phaebotomie</l>
                     <l>Of the Sea-horſſes take,</l>
                     <l>Of the wilde Goats the Recipeis</l>
                     <l>That for the eies we make.</l>
                     <l>Of Ibis and the Heron we</l>
                     <l>The Laxatiue cliſters haue,</l>
                     <l>Of Beares and Lyons the Auſtere</l>
                     <l>Great diets we receaue.</l>
                     <l>Now all theſe Campions fearce they do, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1190"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>The bodie but perſew.</l>
                     <l>Some inwardly do make aſſault,</l>
                     <l>And outwardlie anew:</l>
                     <l>Or if that any take them to</l>
                     <l>The ſoule moſt pleaſant faire,</l>
                     <l>That no waies is directlie but</l>
                     <l>For that they will not ſpare</l>
                     <l>To croſſe her feeble Officers,</l>
                     <l>And ſpoile her worklumes fine,</l>
                     <l>Whereby ſhe (learn'd) ſo many works <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1200"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Makes ſubtilie deuine.</l>
                     <l>BVT LO foure fearefull Captaines now,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe furie hoat aſſaies,</l>
                     <l>To dreſſe a batterie great againſt</l>
                     <l>The Spreit in many waies:</l>
                     <l>His conſtancie in a brangle puts,</l>
                     <l>And promptlie drawes apace,</l>
                     <l>Euen from the path of reaſon quite,</l>
                     <l>Their judgement blind alace,</l>
                     <l>Opinions Children who thought they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1210"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Inuiſible be cleine,</l>
                     <l>Yet they their harmefull motions through,</l>
                     <l>The bodies makes to ſheine.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:26"/>
                     <l>The firſt is irkſomnes, the which</l>
                     <l>A drumlie cloud doth holde,</l>
                     <l>And from the crowne euen of the head</l>
                     <l>Vnto the foot doth folde:</l>
                     <l>Doth rauing drant both night and day,</l>
                     <l>Growes old or age be neere,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1220"/> The longeſt skorie rinckles on</l>
                     <l>His face as Furres appeare:</l>
                     <l>And in a dowiſome quiet nooke</l>
                     <l>He carefull euer thriſts,</l>
                     <l>Als manie ſighs out of his breaſt,</l>
                     <l>As teares from eies out briſts.</l>
                     <l>He guides the tarndneſſe, which to eat</l>
                     <l>The ſelfe doth neuer faile,</l>
                     <l>The weeping pitie, and withall</l>
                     <l>The heauie ſadnes paile:</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1230"/> And the enrag'd diſpair, which with</l>
                     <l>Straiks blea-hewde beats the ſell,</l>
                     <l>Who with Coales, Aſpiks, Tedders als</l>
                     <l>For Armour meet doth mell.</l>
                     <l>The throwart eied enuie withall</l>
                     <l>Fat of the leanes ay</l>
                     <l>Of deareſt friends, who reſtleſlie</l>
                     <l>Doth gnaw her ſelfe away:</l>
                     <l>Like famiſht POLIPVS, who in</l>
                     <l>Vnhaps doth bath her ſtill,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1240"/> And (moſt ill willie) but on teares</l>
                     <l>Her wrath doth feed and fill.</l>
                     <l>And als the jelouſie, which but</l>
                     <l>To ſlumber once doth feare,</l>
                     <l>And euer (moſt ſuſpicious) hath</l>
                     <l>The Flea into the eare:</l>
                     <l>And farre mo eies then he who being</l>
                     <l>By HERMES witcht at laſt,</l>
                     <l>Did the Inachien beautie let</l>
                     <l>Be ſtolne he ſleeping faſt.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:27"/>
                     <l>THE Second Captaine ſure is joy, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1250"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Exceſsiuelie to glade,</l>
                     <l>Who skoups, and lightlie ſtarties, and</l>
                     <l>Whome to the ſtreet that made</l>
                     <l>By APPIVS was, to narrow is,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſences all they do</l>
                     <l>Euen at the wiſhes als enjoy</l>
                     <l>Moſt pleaſant pleaſures to:</l>
                     <l>Who guides effronted vanterie that</l>
                     <l>Doth euer faine and lie,</l>
                     <l>A flatterer, and importune, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1260"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>That euer crying be:</l>
                     <l>And pride brow-bender Gyant who</l>
                     <l>Wings on his backe doth beare,</l>
                     <l>And with his loftie forhead hits,</l>
                     <l>The Starrie ſylring cleare:</l>
                     <l>And many others like the Bels,</l>
                     <l>Who boldned in a raine,</l>
                     <l>Do ſwelling emptie riſe vpon</l>
                     <l>The wake and humid plaine.</l>
                     <l>The feare whoſe ſides inceſſantly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1270"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Do busſie beat apace,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe boſome hath no heart, nor vaines</l>
                     <l>Haue blood in any caſe:</l>
                     <l>Nor ſpreit hath counſaile, yet ſhe daunts</l>
                     <l>Vs quite that feeble dame,</l>
                     <l>Euen with the terrour pale, and with</l>
                     <l>The Land-wart bluſhing ſhame:</l>
                     <l>And ſwearneſſe als at ſloweſt pace</l>
                     <l>Which euer comes and creepes,</l>
                     <l>The which with willing yrnes her armes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1280"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>At all times faſtned keepes:</l>
                     <l>Who laſhlie dreames both night and day,</l>
                     <l>A barren, vndought eik,</l>
                     <l>A vile paralitique feeble one,</l>
                     <l>Who begging aid doth ſeeke.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:27"/>
                     <l>And thou ô Couetouſnes the which</l>
                     <l>The earth, nor yet the aire,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſea, or heauen can euer fill</l>
                     <l>Or ſtanch thy luſting caire.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1290"/> Who crookes for eyes, and groundleſſe deepes,</l>
                     <l>For entrailles carries ay,</l>
                     <l>And clookes for hands, thou fences with</l>
                     <l>Poore ADAM euery way,</l>
                     <l>Thou does vnto the combate bring,</l>
                     <l>Ambition boudned vaine,</l>
                     <l>That burnes in ſlow and ſoaking fire,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe paſsion to containe</l>
                     <l>Or bound in EPICVRVS worlds,</l>
                     <l>Is booteleſſe to eſſay,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1300"/> Who in his hand doth Scepters als</l>
                     <l>In paintrie carrie ay.</l>
                     <l>Thou brings the greedie Auarice,</l>
                     <l>Enarmed all with cleekes,</l>
                     <l>And cled with glew, who neuer briggs</l>
                     <l>For her ſafe paſſage ſeekes,</l>
                     <l>Both through CHARIBDIS baying, and</l>
                     <l>Through traitrous SYRTES fell,</l>
                     <l>Who growes the miſerabler the more</l>
                     <l>Her wealth growes with her ſell.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1310"/> A monſter fierce without reſpect,</l>
                     <l>Or loue, or faith, who will</l>
                     <l>Her neighbours ſorelie harme, but yet</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf more euer ſtill.</l>
                     <l>Who puts her hand in euerie thing,</l>
                     <l>Moechanicklie too vyle.</l>
                     <l>Lyke TANTALYS in middſt of goods,</l>
                     <l>Full poore euen all the whyle.</l>
                     <l>Who nombers neuer what ſhe hath,</l>
                     <l>But what ſhe lak'th doth count,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1320"/> A foule, who though well winged, yet</l>
                     <l>She hie doth neuer mount.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Thou wrathfull contrare ADAM does</l>
                     <l>Lead forward to the warre,</l>
                     <l>The wrath, the which alreadie goes</l>
                     <l>Then thunder ſwifter farre.</l>
                     <l>Who ſullen like a Sanglier makes</l>
                     <l>Her awfull teeth to crack,</l>
                     <l>Her haire ſtarts woudderſhunes, and whiles</l>
                     <l>Her burning eyes doth make</l>
                     <l>To reill, whiles tieth to the ground: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1330"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe horrible face it will</l>
                     <l>Whiles paill, whiles firie, rout with voice</l>
                     <l>Moſt wilde and elrage ſtill:</l>
                     <l>The ground ſtamps with her feet, her hands</l>
                     <l>On other raſh apace:</l>
                     <l>She poiſon, fire, and cruell ſworde,</l>
                     <l>Into that foming cace</l>
                     <l>Beares in her hand, them for to kill,</l>
                     <l>Whome ſyne ſhe doth lament,</l>
                     <l>And lightlies death prouiding that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1340"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Her fellow alſo went:</l>
                     <l>Like as a hinging wall which by</l>
                     <l>The winde louſe ſhaken bene,</l>
                     <l>Doth bruze the ſelf on that, the which</l>
                     <l>Vnder it all bruz'd is clene.</l>
                     <l>Thou makes vnto the fight to come</l>
                     <l>Squar'd arrowes bearing loue,</l>
                     <l>Which tyrants painting will I not</l>
                     <l>After all th'Apelleſis proue</l>
                     <l>That FRANCE hath borne, and ſhortlie then, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1350"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Beneath thy Standarts faire,</l>
                     <l>Thou makes als manie Soldats els</l>
                     <l>For to be marching there</l>
                     <l>As there be verry goods, or for</l>
                     <l>Reſemblance ſo doth trow</l>
                     <l>The King of beaſts who of him ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Is not the maiſter now.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:28"/>
                     <l>But if theſe paſsions that purſewes</l>
                     <l>And touches vs ſo neere,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1360"/> Would ſwiftlie paſſe away as doth,</l>
                     <l>A glancing lightening cleere</l>
                     <l>Then were it nothing, but allace</l>
                     <l>They oftentimes doe leaue</l>
                     <l>The venomed ſting into the ſoule</l>
                     <l>Which hurting they deceaue:</l>
                     <l>From that ſo drumlie ſpring doth flow,</l>
                     <l>The deadlie poiſons fell,</l>
                     <l>The SODOMIES, thefts, and inceſts,</l>
                     <l>And treaſons vile to tell.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1370"/> The blaſphemies, the falſe contracts,</l>
                     <l>Conſpiring, drunkeneſſe eik,</l>
                     <l>The Sacriledge, wait-laying, murther,</l>
                     <l>And Reafe that praies do ſeek.</l>
                     <l>Allace theſe langors (that be worſe</l>
                     <l>Then thouſand deaths be farr,)</l>
                     <l>Are different from the langores that</l>
                     <l>Makes with the bodie warre.</l>
                     <l>Who are auowedlie enemies,</l>
                     <l>And by their malice do,</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1380"/> Giue to the Patient manie a ſigne</l>
                     <l>Of healthes attaining to.</l>
                     <l>Whiles by the brangling pulſe, and whiles</l>
                     <l>Euen by their colour viue,</l>
                     <l>Whiles by the ſtinging needels of</l>
                     <l>Strong dolour that doth grieue.</l>
                     <l>So as well knowing once the euill,</l>
                     <l>That doth vs brooke and binde,</l>
                     <l>It is not too difficill ſyne,</l>
                     <l>The remedie to finde.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1390"/> But theſe our euils for that they in</l>
                     <l>Our vnderſtanding raigne,</l>
                     <l>Who onelie ought and may diſcerne</l>
                     <l>Of them, they do remaine</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:29"/>
                     <l>Vnknowne at all and for that cauſe</l>
                     <l>Doth PODALIRIVS ſtay,</l>
                     <l>To runne to ANTICIRE to get</l>
                     <l>His health in anie way.</l>
                     <l>And furthermore the Feuerous man,</l>
                     <l>We feuerous do him call,</l>
                     <l>Hydropique we hydropique name, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1400"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Diſsimuling not at all</l>
                     <l>Inunder the deceatfull maſque,</l>
                     <l>Of fained words the paine</l>
                     <l>That crewell, doth our members with</l>
                     <l>Her torments ſharpe demaine.</l>
                     <l>Contrariwiſe, the Spreit is of</l>
                     <l>The ſelf the flatterer ay,</l>
                     <l>The owne skabb clawes, and with a ſtyle</l>
                     <l>That lyar is alway</l>
                     <l>By cloaking of his vices lets <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1410"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>The Vlcer blinde to feare,</l>
                     <l>The Cautere needles quite for it</l>
                     <l>Of reaſon for to heare:</l>
                     <l>And ſure if euer vice did cleith</l>
                     <l>The ſelf in anie where</l>
                     <l>With the vnſpotted famous cloak</l>
                     <l>Of holie vertue faire</l>
                     <l>It certainlie is in our age</l>
                     <l>Worſe by a hundreth folde,</l>
                     <l>Then when on all the earth the waues <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1420"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Quite vniuerſal rolde.</l>
                     <l>Of ſinnes diſcourſe I will not that</l>
                     <l>Are vildeſt in degree,</l>
                     <l>Wherewith the bedds infamous of</l>
                     <l>The greateſt ſpotted be.</l>
                     <l>For feare that in offending of</l>
                     <l>The holies tender eare,</l>
                     <l>I rather ſeeme to teach them then</l>
                     <l>To wiſh them to forbeare.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:29"/>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1430"/> They who vpon their bodies with</l>
                     <l>Grangores gnawne and deformed,</l>
                     <l>Beares Woods, faire Meidowes, Caſtles als</l>
                     <l>In threads of Gold transformed.</l>
                     <l>And whoſe hands prodigall into</l>
                     <l>Once ſhifting of the Cairts,</l>
                     <l>One Iuſting proud, one Banquet great,</l>
                     <l>Doe waſt with glorious hearts</l>
                     <l>The treaſures gathered by the paines</l>
                     <l>And niggard trauels ſore.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1440"/> Of their forebeers occurrars, cal'd,</l>
                     <l>Are liberall euermore.</l>
                     <l>They whoſe affected going, and</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fairded deintie cheekes,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe accent all effeminat,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe bonnie blincks and keeks,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe feeble coward heart and ſpreit,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſoft and ſouple weed</l>
                     <l>Declares, that they are onelie men</l>
                     <l>Of outward ſhew indeed.</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1450"/> O theſe be courtlie proper and feat,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe who from bed to bed</l>
                     <l>Like Goat-bucks wander vagabonds,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe charming mouthes haue led</l>
                     <l>And chaſte SVSANNAES tyſted halfe</l>
                     <l>And euer famiſht, flee</l>
                     <l>To euerie pray: ô ſurely theſe</l>
                     <l>Are Louers cal'd we ſee.</l>
                     <l>They who by falſe contracts, and by</l>
                     <l>Vnlawfull meaſures do</l>
                     <l> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1460"/> Acquire (oppreſſours) ſubſtance, yea,</l>
                     <l>And princely riches too:</l>
                     <l>And goes Sophiſticating all</l>
                     <l>The ſimple ſtrangers ay,</l>
                     <l>And hundreths doe for hundreths lend,</l>
                     <l>Are Stewards good they ſay.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:30"/>
                     <l>Who in reuenges badd deſire,</l>
                     <l>Do euer thriſt and burne,</l>
                     <l>Who bathes themſelues in blood, and puts</l>
                     <l>No difference in their turne</l>
                     <l>Of ranke, of Sexe, of age, but ſtill <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1470"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Moſt cruell they defile,</l>
                     <l>Colde blooded into euery corps</l>
                     <l>Their murthering hands and vile,</l>
                     <l>Are men of moſt magnanime ſpreit.</l>
                     <l>O would to God that FRANCE</l>
                     <l>Were voyd of men of ſpreit, ſince that</l>
                     <l>Our manhead doth aduance,</l>
                     <l>And fight for our ilwillers, and</l>
                     <l>Suckes out our blood apace,</l>
                     <l>Makes waſt our Cities, and doth breſh <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1480"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Our verie ſides allace.</l>
                     <l>O would to God the Targe, the Pike,</l>
                     <l>The Sword might changed be</l>
                     <l>In ploughs for to mannure the Land.</l>
                     <l>O ſhall I neuer ſee</l>
                     <l>The Spiders long and threadie feet</l>
                     <l>Full buſie for to weaue,</l>
                     <l>Within the holloweſt of a healme</l>
                     <l>Deckt with a pennage braue?</l>
                     <l>But if ye French-men greene ſo faſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1490"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>To Battailes for to go,</l>
                     <l>And if that awfull Ennyon ſeethes</l>
                     <l>Into your bowels ſo,</l>
                     <l>What gaine or profite holdes you heere,</l>
                     <l>And makes you ſtay ſo long?</l>
                     <l>Our fields of beſtiall voyd, of wealth</l>
                     <l>Are all our Cities ſtrong.</l>
                     <l>Then go ye, runne ô warlike youth</l>
                     <l>Whome no diſtreſſe can dant,</l>
                     <l>Another Gaulien Greece into <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1500"/> 
                     </l>
                     <l>Natolia for to plant:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:30"/>
                     <l>Go run in Flanders, and do yee</l>
                     <l>Moſt mercifull releeue</l>
                     <l>Your brethren Belges from the yoake</l>
                     <l>Of Spaine that doth them greeue.</l>
                     <l>Run vnto Portugale, and people</l>
                     <l>Of new Gallicia now,</l>
                     <l>And do your names engraue againe</l>
                     <l>In PORT-VLISSES brow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THus louing Reader as thou ſees,</l>
                     <l>Now haue I made an end,</l>
                     <l>Vnto this worke which man did write,</l>
                     <l>But by the Lord is pend:</l>
                     <l>Wherein as I haue preaſt to make</l>
                     <l>The Authour knowne to all,</l>
                     <l>That into Brittaine Ile remaine,</l>
                     <l>Where he before was thrall</l>
                     <l>Within the onelie bounds of France,</l>
                     <l>So doubt I not thou will</l>
                     <l>Excuſe my blotting of his face,</l>
                     <l>And blame my lacke of skill</l>
                     <l>Which letted me to imitate</l>
                     <l>His hard and loftie verſe,</l>
                     <l>His arrowes headed blunt by me,</l>
                     <l>As earſt could no waies pearce.</l>
                     <l>But ſince both profite may heerein,</l>
                     <l>And pleaſure reaped be,</l>
                     <l>Though metamorphos'd all I grant,</l>
                     <l>And quite transform'd by me:</l>
                     <l>Yet ought thou juſtlie loue and like</l>
                     <l>My painefull trauels bent,</l>
                     <l>It is ſufficient vnto me,</l>
                     <l>Thou know my good intent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:31"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:31"/>
                  <p>THE LEPAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO OF IAMES the ſixt, King of Scotland.</p>
                  <p>AT EDINBVRGH PRINTED BY <hi>Robert Walde-graue</hi> Printer to the Kings Maiestie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cum priuilegio Regali.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>title page border not found in McKerrow: at left, Truth holding a book and pen (?) with a king's or prince's body under her foot; at right, Chastity with Cupid beneath her foot</figDesc>
                     <p>VERI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TAS.</p>
                     <p>CASTI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TAS.</p>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="authors_preface_to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:32"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE AVTHORS</hi> PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T falles out often, that the effects of mens actions comes cleane contrarie to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Authour. The ſame finde I by experience (beloued Reader) in my Poëme of <hi>LEPANTO:</hi> For although till now, it haue not bene imprinted, yet being ſet out to the publick view of many, by a great ſort of ſtoln Copies, purchaſt (in truth) without my knowledge or conſent, it hath for lack of a Praeface, bene in ſome things miſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrued by ſundry, which I of verie purpoſe thinking to haue omitted, for that the writing therof, might haue tended in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſome reproach of the skilfull learnednes of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as if his braines could not haue conceaued ſo vncuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a worke, without ſome maner of Commentarie, and ſo haue made the worke more diſpleaſant vnto him: it hath by the contrary falen out, that the lack therof, hath made it the more diſpleaſant to ſome, through their miſtaking a part of the meaning thereof. And for that I knowe, the ſpecial thing miſliked in it, is, that I ſhould ſeeme, far con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my degree and Religion, like a Mercenary Poët, to penne a worke, <hi>ex profeſſo,</hi> in praiſe of a forraine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt baſtard: I will by ſetting downe the nature and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:8720:33"/> of the Poëme, reſolue the ignorant of their error, &amp; mak the other ſort inexcuſable of their captiouſnes. The nature then of this Poëme, is an argument, <hi>à minore ad majùs,</hi> largely intreated by a Poetike compariſon, beeing to the writing hereof mooued, by the ſtirring vppe of the league and cruell perſecution of the Protestants in all countries, at the very firſt raging wherof, I compiled this Poëme, as the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the perſecuted in the hinmoſt eight lines thereof doth plainely teſtifie, being both begun and ended in the ſame Summer, wherein the league was publiſhed in France. The order of the Cantique is this: Firſt, a Poetique Praeface, declaring the mater I treat of: wherein, I name not <hi>DON-IOAN,</hi> neither literally nor any waies by deſcription, which I behooued to haue doone, if I had penned the whole Poëme in his praiſe, as <hi>VIRGIL, Arma virumque cano, &amp; HOMER, Dic mihi muſa virum,</hi> of whoſe imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had not bene aſhamed, if ſo my purpoſe had bene framed. Next followes my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation to the true God only, and not to all the He and She Saints, for whoſe vaine honors, <hi>DON-IOAN</hi> fought in all his wars. Next after my inuocation, follows the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etique History of my compariſon, wherin following furth the ground of a true History, (as <hi>VIRGIL</hi> or <hi>HOMER</hi> did) like a painter ſhadowing with vmbers a portrait els drawn in groſſe, for giuing it greter viuenes, ſo I eike or paire to the circumſtaunces of the actions, as the rules of the poeticke art will permit: which Historicke compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon continues till the ſong of the Angels: in the which I compare and applie the former compariſon to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſtate, taking occaſion thereupon to ſpeake ſome what of our religion. Laſtlie the Epilogue of the whole in the
<pb facs="tcp:8720:33"/> laſt eight lines, declares fully my intention in the whole, and explaines ſo fullye my compariſon and Argument, from the more to the leſse, as I cannot without ſhamefull repetition ſpeake anie more therof. And in a word: what ſo euer praiſe I haue giuen to <hi>DON-IOAN</hi> in this Poëme, it is neither in accompting him as firſt or ſecond cauſe of that victorie, but onely as of a particular man, when hee falles in my way, to ſpeake the truth of him. For as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes not the honour of my eſtate, like an hireling, to pen the praiſe of any man: So becomes it far leſſe the highnes of my rancke and calling, to ſpare for the feare or fauor of whomſoeuer liuing, to ſpeake or write the trueth of anie. And thus crauing pardon (beloued Reader) for this long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Apologie (beeing driuen thereto, not by nature, but by neceſsitie) I bid you hartely fare-well.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:34"/>
                  <head>THE LEPANTO OF IAMES THE SIXT, <hi>King of Scotland.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Sing a wondrous worke of God,</l>
                  <l>I ſing his mercies great,</l>
                  <l>I ſing his juſtice heere-withall</l>
                  <l>Powr'd from his holy ſeat.</l>
                  <l>To wit, a cruell Martiall warre,</l>
                  <l>A bloodie battell bolde,</l>
                  <l>Long doubtſome fight, with ſlaughter huge</l>
                  <l>And wounded manifold.</l>
                  <l>Which fought was in LEPANTOES gulfe</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the baptiz'd race,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> And circumſiſed Turband Turkes</l>
                  <l>Rencountring in that place.</l>
                  <l>O onely God, I pray thee thriſe,</l>
                  <l>Thriſe one in perſons three,</l>
                  <l>Alike Eternall, like of might,</l>
                  <l>Although diſtinct yee be.</l>
                  <l>I pray thee Father, through thy Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Thy word immortall ſtill,</l>
                  <l>The great ARCHANGEL of records</l>
                  <l>And worker of thy will,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> To make thy holie Spreit my Muſe,</l>
                  <l>And eik my pen inflame,</l>
                  <l>Aboue my skill to write this worke</l>
                  <l>To magnifie thy name.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:35"/>
                  <l>INTO the turning ſtill of times,</l>
                  <l>I erre, no time can be,</l>
                  <l>Where was and is, and times to come,</l>
                  <l>Confounded are all three.</l>
                  <l>I meane before great God in Heauen,</l>
                  <l>(For Sunne and Moone deuides</l>
                  <l>The times in Earth by houres and dayes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſeaſons ſtill that ſlides.)</l>
                  <l>Yet Man, whome Man muſt vnderſtand,</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſpeake into this cace,</l>
                  <l>As man, our fleſh will not permit,</l>
                  <l>Wee heauenlie things imbrace.</l>
                  <l>Then, as I els began to ſay,</l>
                  <l>One day it did fall out,</l>
                  <l>As glorious God in gliſtering throne,</l>
                  <l>With Angells round about</l>
                  <l>Did ſit, and Chriſt at his right hand, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>That craftie Satan came,</l>
                  <l>Deceauer, Lyar, hating man,</l>
                  <l>And Gods moſt ſacred name.</l>
                  <l>This olde abuſer ſtood into</l>
                  <l>The preſence of the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Then in this manner Chriſt accus'de,</l>
                  <l>The ſower of diſcord.</l>
                  <l>I know thou from that City comes,</l>
                  <l>CONSTANTINOPLE great,</l>
                  <l>Where thou haſt by thy malice made <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>The faithles Turkes to freat.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt inflamde their maddeſt mindes</l>
                  <l>With raging fire of wraith,</l>
                  <l>Againſt them all that doe profeſſe</l>
                  <l>My name with feruent fayth.</l>
                  <l>How long ô Father ſhall they thus,</l>
                  <l>Quite vnder foote be tred,</l>
                  <l>By faithles folkes; who executes</l>
                  <l>What in this ſnake is bred.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:35"/>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> Then Satan anſwerd, Fayth? quoth he,</l>
                  <l>Their Faith is too too ſmall,</l>
                  <l>They ſtriue me thinke on either part,</l>
                  <l>Who fartheſt backe can fall,</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou not giuen them in my hands,</l>
                  <l>Euen boath the ſides I ſay,</l>
                  <l>That I, as beſt doth ſeeme to me,</l>
                  <l>May vſe them euery way?</l>
                  <l>THEN IEHOVA, whoſe nod doth make,</l>
                  <l>The heauens and mountaines quake,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> Whoſe ſmalleſt wrath the centres makes,</l>
                  <l>Of all the Earth to ſhake.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worde did make the worlde of nought,</l>
                  <l>And whoſe approouing ſyne,</l>
                  <l>Did ſtabliſh all even as wee ſee,</l>
                  <l>By force of voice deuine.</l>
                  <l>This God began from thundering throte,</l>
                  <l>Graue wordes of waight to bring,</l>
                  <l>All chriſtians ſerues my Sonne though not</l>
                  <l>Aright in everie thing.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> No more ſhall now theſe Chriſtians be</l>
                  <l>With Infidels oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>So of my holie hallowed name</l>
                  <l>The force is great and bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Deſiſt ô tempter. GABRIEL come</l>
                  <l>O thou ARCHANGEL true,</l>
                  <l>Whome I haue oft in meſſage ſent</l>
                  <l>To Realmes and Townes anew.</l>
                  <l>Go quicklie hence to Venice Towne,</l>
                  <l>And put into their minds</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="90"/> To take reuenge of wrongs the Turks</l>
                  <l>Haue done in ſundrie kinds.</l>
                  <l>No whiſling winde with ſuch a ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>From hilles can hurle ore heugh,</l>
                  <l>As he whoſe thought doth furniſh ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>His thought was ſpeed aneugh.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:36"/>
                  <l>This Towne it ſtands within the Sea,</l>
                  <l>Fiue miles or there about,</l>
                  <l>Vpon no Ile nor ground, the Sea</l>
                  <l>Runnes all the ſtreets throughout.</l>
                  <l>Who ſtood vpon the Steeple head <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="100"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Should ſee a wondrous ſight,</l>
                  <l>A Towne to ſtand without a ground,</l>
                  <l>Her ground is made by ſlight:</l>
                  <l>Strong Timber props dung in the Sea</l>
                  <l>Do beare her vp by art,</l>
                  <l>An Ile is all her market place</l>
                  <l>A large and ſpacious part,</l>
                  <l>A Duke with Senate joynd doth rule,</l>
                  <l>Saint MARKE is patron chiefe,</l>
                  <l>Ilk yeare they wedde the Sea with rings <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="110"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>To be their ſure reliefe.</l>
                  <l>The Angell then ariu'd into</l>
                  <l>This artificiall Towne,</l>
                  <l>And chang'd in likenes of a man,</l>
                  <l>He walkes both vp and downe,</l>
                  <l>While time he met ſome man of ſpreit,</l>
                  <l>And then began to ſay,</l>
                  <l>What doe we all? me thinke we ſleepe:</l>
                  <l>Are we not day by day</l>
                  <l>By cruell Turks and infidels <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="120"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Moſt ſpitefullie oppreſt?</l>
                  <l>They kill our Knights, they braſh our forts,</l>
                  <l>They let vs neuer reſt.</l>
                  <l>Go too, go too, once make a proofe:</l>
                  <l>No more let vs deſiſt</l>
                  <l>To bold attempts God giues ſucceſſe,</l>
                  <l>If once aſſay we liſt:</l>
                  <l>With this he goes away, this man</l>
                  <l>Vnto another tels <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="130"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>The purpoſe whereunto they both</l>
                  <l>Agree among them fels.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:36"/>
                  <l>This other to another tels,</l>
                  <l>And ſo from hand to hand</l>
                  <l>It ſpreads and goes, and all that heard</l>
                  <l>It, neceſſare it fand.</l>
                  <l>And laſt of all, it comes vnto</l>
                  <l>The Duke and Senates eare,</l>
                  <l>Who found it good, and followed furth</l>
                  <l>The ſame as ye ſhall heare.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="140"/> THE Towne was driuen into this time,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a piteous ſtrait</l>
                  <l>By Mahometiſts, that they had els</l>
                  <l>Giuen ouer all debait:</l>
                  <l>The Turke had conqueſt Cyprus Ile,</l>
                  <l>And all their lands that lay</l>
                  <l>Without the bounds of Italie,</l>
                  <l>Almoſt the whole I ſay:</l>
                  <l>And they for laſt refuge of all,</l>
                  <l>Had moou'd each Chriſtian King</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="150"/> To make their Churches pray for their</l>
                  <l>Reliefe in euerie thing.</l>
                  <l>The Towne with piteous plaints did call</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Lord of might,</l>
                  <l>With praying ſtill and faſting oft,</l>
                  <l>And groning all the night,</l>
                  <l>Was nothing heard but ſobs and ſighs,</l>
                  <l>Was nothing ſeene but teares,</l>
                  <l>Yea ſorrow draue the braueſt men</l>
                  <l>With mourning to their beares.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="160"/> The women ſwound for ſorrow oft,</l>
                  <l>The babe for woe did weepe,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the mother giuing milke</l>
                  <l>Such dolefull geſture keepe.</l>
                  <l>Young men and maids within the towne</l>
                  <l>Were ay arraid in blacke,</l>
                  <l>Each Eau'n the Sunne was ſooner hid</l>
                  <l>Then earſt, the night to macke.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:37"/>
                  <l>No VENVS then, nor CVPID falſe</l>
                  <l>durſt kyth or once appeare,</l>
                  <l>For paile diſtreſſe had baniſht them, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="170"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>By ſadde and ſory cheare.</l>
                  <l>As Seas did compaſſe them about,</l>
                  <l>So Seas the Streets did ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>So Seas of teares did ever flowe,</l>
                  <l>The houſes all within.</l>
                  <l>As Seas within were joynd with howles,</l>
                  <l>So Seas without did raire,</l>
                  <l>Thair carefull cries to Heauen did mount</l>
                  <l>Reſounding in the aire.</l>
                  <l>O ſtay my Muſe, thou goes too farre, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="180"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Shewe where we left before,</l>
                  <l>Leſt trikling teares ſo fill my penne</l>
                  <l>That it will write no more.</l>
                  <l>THEN VENICE being in this ſtate,</l>
                  <l>When GABRIEL there was ſent,</l>
                  <l>His ſpeaches ſpred abroad, made Towne</l>
                  <l>And Senat both ſo bent</l>
                  <l>To take reuenge, as they implorde</l>
                  <l>The Chriſtian Princes ayd,</l>
                  <l>Of forces ſuch, as eaſilie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="190"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>They might haue ſpard and maid.</l>
                  <l>At laſt, ſupport was granted them,</l>
                  <l>The holie league was paſt,</l>
                  <l>Als long to ſtande, as twixt the Turkes</l>
                  <l>And Chriſtians warre ſhoulde laſt.</l>
                  <l>It was agreed, that into March,</l>
                  <l>Or Aprill every yeare,</l>
                  <l>The armie ſhoulde on eaſterne Seas,</l>
                  <l>Convene from farre and neare.</l>
                  <l>THVS bent vpon their interpriſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="200"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>The principalls did conveene,</l>
                  <l>Into MESSENA to conſult,</l>
                  <l>What order ſhould haue beene,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:37"/>
                  <l>Obſeru'd in all their armie great:</l>
                  <l>There DON IOAN d'AVSTRIA came,</l>
                  <l>Their Generall great, and VENIER als</l>
                  <l>Came there in Venice name.</l>
                  <l>From GENES ANDREA DOREE came</l>
                  <l>And Rome COLONNE ſent,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="210"/> When they with others many daies</l>
                  <l>Had into counſaile ſpent,</l>
                  <l>In end ASCAGNIO DE LA CORNE</l>
                  <l>A Martiall man and wiſe</l>
                  <l>His counſaile gaue, as ye ſhall heare</l>
                  <l>Vpon their enterpriſe.</l>
                  <l>THREE cauſes be (ô Chieftaines braue)</l>
                  <l>That ſhould a Generall let,</l>
                  <l>On Fortunes light vncertaine wheele</l>
                  <l>The victorie to ſet:</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="220"/> Firſt, if the loſſe may harme him more,</l>
                  <l>Then winning can auaile,</l>
                  <l>As if his Realme he doe defend</l>
                  <l>From them that it aſſaile:</l>
                  <l>The next is when the contrare Hoſt</l>
                  <l>Is able to deuide</l>
                  <l>For ſicknes ſore or famine great</l>
                  <l>Then beſt is to abide.</l>
                  <l>The third and laſt, it is in caſe</l>
                  <l>His forces be too ſmall,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="230"/> Then better farre is to delay,</l>
                  <l>Then for to periſh all:</l>
                  <l>But ſince of theſe two former points</l>
                  <l>We need not ſtand in doubt,</l>
                  <l>Then though we leeſe, we may defend</l>
                  <l>Our Countries round about.</l>
                  <l>As to the laſt, this armie is</l>
                  <l>So awfull ſtrong and faire,</l>
                  <l>And furniſht ſo with neceſſares</l>
                  <l>Through your foreſeing cair,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:38"/>
                  <l>That nought doth reſt but courage bolde. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="240"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Then ſince your ſtate is ſuch,</l>
                  <l>With truſt in God aſſay your chance</l>
                  <l>Good cauſe availeth much.</l>
                  <l>But ſpeciallie take heede to this,</l>
                  <l>That ere yee make away,</l>
                  <l>Ye order all concerning warre,</l>
                  <l>Into their due array:</l>
                  <l>For if while that yee ſee your foes,</l>
                  <l>Yee ſhall continewe all,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall their ſuddaine ſight with feare <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="250"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Your braueſt Spreits appall,</l>
                  <l>Each one commande a ſundry thing,</l>
                  <l>Aſtoniſht of the cace,</l>
                  <l>And everie ſimple Soldat ſhall</l>
                  <l>Vſurpe his Captaines place.</l>
                  <l>This counſall ſo contents them all,</l>
                  <l>That everie man departs,</l>
                  <l>With whiſpering much, and ſo reſolues</l>
                  <l>With bolde magnanime harts.</l>
                  <l>THEIR preparations being made, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="260"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>They all vpon a day,</l>
                  <l>Their biting ankers, gladlie wayed,</l>
                  <l>And made them for the way.</l>
                  <l>The Grecian Fleet, for HELENS cauſe,</l>
                  <l>That NEPTVNS town did ſack:</l>
                  <l>In braue array, or gliſtring armes,</l>
                  <l>No match to them could mak.</l>
                  <l>There came eight thouſand Spaniards braue,</l>
                  <l>From hotte and barren SPAINE,</l>
                  <l>Good ordour kepars, cold in fight, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="270"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>With proud diſdainfull braine.</l>
                  <l>From pleaſant fertill ITALIE,</l>
                  <l>There came twelue thouſand als,</l>
                  <l>With ſubtill ſpreites bent to reuenge,</l>
                  <l>By craftie meanes and fals.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:38"/>
                  <l>Three thouſande ALMANS alſo came,</l>
                  <l>From Countries colde and wide,</l>
                  <l>Theſe monney men with awfull cheare</l>
                  <l>The chok will dourelie bide.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="280"/> From diuers partes did alſo come,</l>
                  <l>Three thouſand venturers braue,</l>
                  <l>All voluntaires of conſcience mou'd,</l>
                  <l>And would no wages haue.</l>
                  <l>Armde Galleyes twice a hundr'and eight,</l>
                  <l>Six ſhippes all wondrous great,</l>
                  <l>And fiue and twentie loadned Shipps</l>
                  <l>With baggage and with meate.</l>
                  <l>With fourtie other little barkes</l>
                  <l>And prettie Galeots ſmall,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="290"/> Of theſe aforeſaide was compound</l>
                  <l>The Chriſtian Nauie all.</l>
                  <l>THIS cloude of Gallies thus began</l>
                  <l>On NEPTVNS back to rowe,</l>
                  <l>And in the Shippes the marriners,</l>
                  <l>Did skippe from towe to towe</l>
                  <l>With willing mindes they hailde the Tyes,</l>
                  <l>And hoiſt the flaffing Sayles,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrongeſt towes, from higheſt maſtes,</l>
                  <l>With force and practique hayles.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="300"/> The Forceats lothſomlie did rowe,</l>
                  <l>In Gallies gainſt their will,</l>
                  <l>Whome Galley maſters oft did beat,</l>
                  <l>And threaten euer ſtill.</l>
                  <l>The foming Seas did bullor vp,</l>
                  <l>The risking Oares did raſhe,</l>
                  <l>The Soldats peeces for to clenge</l>
                  <l>Did ſhoures of ſhotts delaſhe.</l>
                  <l>BVT as the Deuill is reddie bent,</l>
                  <l>Good workes to hinder ay,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="310"/> So ſowd he in this Nauie ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Their good ſucceſſe to ſtay:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:39"/>
                  <l>Yet did the wiſdomes of the Chiefes</l>
                  <l>And of the generall moſt,</l>
                  <l>Compound all quarrels and debates</l>
                  <l>That were into that Hoſt,</l>
                  <l>Preferring wiſely as they ought,</l>
                  <l>The honor of the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Vnto their owne, the publicke cauſe,</l>
                  <l>To priuate mens diſcord.</l>
                  <l>THE feathered fame of wondrous ſpeed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="320"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>That doth delite to flee</l>
                  <l>On tops of houſes pratling all</l>
                  <l>That ſhe can heare or ſee,</l>
                  <l>Part true, part falſe: this monſter ſtrange</l>
                  <l>Among the Turks did tell,</l>
                  <l>That diuers Chriſtian Princes joynd,</l>
                  <l>Reſolu'd with them to mell.</l>
                  <l>Then ſpies were ſent abroad, who tolde</l>
                  <l>The matter as it ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Except in Arithmetique (as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="330"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>It ſeemd) they were not good,</l>
                  <l>For they did count their number to</l>
                  <l>Be leſſe then was indeed,</l>
                  <l>Which did into the great Turks mind</l>
                  <l>A great diſdaining breed:</l>
                  <l>A perrillous thing, as euer came</l>
                  <l>Into a Chieftaines braine,</l>
                  <l>To ſet at nought his foes (though ſmall)</l>
                  <l>By lighleing diſdaine.</l>
                  <l>Then SELYM ſent a nauie out, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="340"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Who wanderd without reſt,</l>
                  <l>Whill time into LEPANTOES gulfe</l>
                  <l>They all their Ankers keſt.</l>
                  <l>IN ſeaſon when with ſharpeſt hooks</l>
                  <l>The buſie ſhearers cowe</l>
                  <l>The fruitfull yallow lockes of golde,</l>
                  <l>That doe on CERES growe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:39"/>
                  <l>And when the ſtrongeſt Trees for weight</l>
                  <l>Of birth do downward bow</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="350"/> Their heauie heads, whoſe colourd knops</l>
                  <l>In ſhowers raines ripelie now,</l>
                  <l>And Husband-men with woodbind crownes</l>
                  <l>To twice borne BACHVS dance,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pleaſant poyſon ſweet in taſt,</l>
                  <l>Doth caſt them in a trance:</l>
                  <l>Into this riping ſeaſon ſure,</l>
                  <l>The Chriſtian Hoſt I ſay,</l>
                  <l>Were all aſſembled for to make</l>
                  <l>Them Readie for the way:</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="360"/> But or they from MESSENA came,</l>
                  <l>The Vines were ſtanding bair,</l>
                  <l>Trees voyd of fruit and CERES polde,</l>
                  <l>And lacking all her hair:</l>
                  <l>But when that leaues, with ratling falles</l>
                  <l>In banks of withered boughes,</l>
                  <l>And carefull laborers do begin,</l>
                  <l>To yoke the painefull ploughes</l>
                  <l>The Nauies neere to other drew,</l>
                  <l>And VENIER (ſent before)</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="370"/> Gaue falſe Alarum, ſending word,</l>
                  <l>The Turks had skowp'd the ſcore,</l>
                  <l>That fiftie Galleis quite were fled,</l>
                  <l>This word he ſent expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>To make the Chriſtians willinglie</l>
                  <l>To battell them adreſſe,</l>
                  <l>As ſo they did, and enterd all,</l>
                  <l>(Moou'd by that ſamin ſlight.)</l>
                  <l>Into LEPANTOES gulfe, and there</l>
                  <l>Preparde them for the fight.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="380"/> WHILL this was doing heere on earth,</l>
                  <l>Great God who creats all,</l>
                  <l>(With wakrife eie preordoning</l>
                  <l>What euer doth befall.)</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:40"/>
                  <l>Was ſitting in his pompous Throne,</l>
                  <l>In hieſt Heauen aboue,</l>
                  <l>And gloriouſlie accompanied</l>
                  <l>With juſtice and with loue:</l>
                  <l>The one hath ſmiling countenance,</l>
                  <l>The other frowning cheare.</l>
                  <l>The one to mercie ſtill perſwades <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="390"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Him as a Father deare,</l>
                  <l>The other for to powre his plagues</l>
                  <l>Vpon repining ſinne,</l>
                  <l>And fill the fields with wofull cries,</l>
                  <l>The houſes all with dinne,</l>
                  <l>But yet the Lord ſo temperates them,</l>
                  <l>That both doe brooke their place,</l>
                  <l>For Iuſtice whiles obtaines her will,</l>
                  <l>But euermore doth grace:</l>
                  <l>IEHOVA als hath ballances, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="400"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Wherewith hee weighs aright</l>
                  <l>The greateſt and the heauieſt ſinnes</l>
                  <l>With ſmaller faults and light,</l>
                  <l>Theſe grace did mooue him for to take,</l>
                  <l>And ſo he weighed in Heauen,</l>
                  <l>The Chriſtian faults with faithleſſe Turkes,</l>
                  <l>The ballance ſtood not eauen,</l>
                  <l>But ſweid vpon the faithleſſe ſide:</l>
                  <l>And then with awfull face,</l>
                  <l>Frownd God of Hoſts, the whirling Heauens <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="410"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>For feare did tremble apace,</l>
                  <l>The ſtaieſt Mountaines ſhuddred all,</l>
                  <l>The grounds of earth did ſhake,</l>
                  <l>The Seas did bray, and PLVTOES Realme</l>
                  <l>For horrour colde did quake.</l>
                  <l>Hovv ſoone AVRORAS ioyfull face,</l>
                  <l>Had ſhead the ſhadie night,</l>
                  <l>And made the chiuering Larks to ſing</l>
                  <l>For gladnes of the light,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:40"/>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="420"/> And PHOEBE with inconſtant face,</l>
                  <l>In Seas had gone to reſt;</l>
                  <l>And PHOEBVS chaſing vapours moiſt,</l>
                  <l>The Skie made blew celeſt:</l>
                  <l>The Generall of the Chriſtian Hoſt</l>
                  <l>Vpon his Galley Maſt,</l>
                  <l>The bloodie ſigne of furious MARS</l>
                  <l>Made to bee fixed faſt.</l>
                  <l>Then as into a ſpacious towne,</l>
                  <l>At breaking of the day,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="430"/> The buſie worke-men doe prepare</l>
                  <l>Their Worklumes euery way,</l>
                  <l>The Wright doth ſharpe his hacking Axe,</l>
                  <l>The Smith his grinding File,</l>
                  <l>Glaſſe-makers beets their fire that burnes</l>
                  <l>Continuall not a while,</l>
                  <l>The Painter mixes colours viue,</l>
                  <l>The Printer Letters ſets,</l>
                  <l>The Maſon clinckes on Marble Stones,</l>
                  <l>Which hardlie dreſt he gets:</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="440"/> Euen ſo, how ſoone this Warriour world</l>
                  <l>With earneſt eies did ſee</l>
                  <l>You ſigne of Warre, they all prepard</l>
                  <l>To winne or els to die:</l>
                  <l>Heere Hagbutters prepard with ſpeed</l>
                  <l>A number of Bullets round,</l>
                  <l>There Cannoners, their Canons ſteild</l>
                  <l>To make diſtroying ſound,</l>
                  <l>Here Knights did dight their burniſht brands,</l>
                  <l>Their Archers bowes did bend,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="450"/> The Armorers on Corſlets knockes,</l>
                  <l>And Harneſſe hard did mend,</l>
                  <l>The feirie Marriners at once</l>
                  <l>Makes all their tackling clair</l>
                  <l>With whiſpering dinne, and cries confus'de,</l>
                  <l>Preparing here and there:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:41"/>
                  <l>As buſie Bees within their Hyues</l>
                  <l>With murmuring euer ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Are earn'ſt vpon their fruitfull worke</l>
                  <l>Their emptie holes to fill.</l>
                  <l>The Flags and Enſeigneis were diſplaid, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="460"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>At ZEPHYRS will to waue,</l>
                  <l>Each painted in the colours cleere</l>
                  <l>Of euery owner braue.</l>
                  <l>BVT all this time in carefull minde,</l>
                  <l>The Generall euer rolde,</l>
                  <l>What manner of array would beſt</l>
                  <l>Fit ſuch an Armie bolde,</l>
                  <l>To pance on this it paind him more,</l>
                  <l>This more did trouble his breſt,</l>
                  <l>Then Canons, Corſe-lets, Bullets, tackle, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="470"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſwordes, and bowes, the reſt,</l>
                  <l>And at the laſt with ripe aduiſe,</l>
                  <l>Of Chieftaines ſage and graue</l>
                  <l>He ſhead in three in Creſſents forme,</l>
                  <l>This martiall Armie braue:</l>
                  <l>The Generall in the battaile was,</l>
                  <l>And COLONNE vndertooke</l>
                  <l>The right wing with the force of GENES,</l>
                  <l>The left did VENIER brooke.</l>
                  <l>WHEN this was done, the Spaniſh Prince <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="480"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Did row about them all,</l>
                  <l>And on the names of ſpeciall men</l>
                  <l>With louing ſpeach did call,</l>
                  <l>Remembring them how righteous was</l>
                  <l>Their quarrell, and how good,</l>
                  <l>Immortall praiſe, and infinit gaines,</l>
                  <l>To conquer with their blood,</l>
                  <l>And that the glorie of God in earth,</l>
                  <l>Into their manhead ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Through juſt reliefe of Chriſtian ſoules <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="490"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>From cruell Pagans hands:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:41"/>
                  <l>But if the ennemie triumphed</l>
                  <l>Of them and of their fame,</l>
                  <l>In millions men to bondage would</l>
                  <l>Profeſsing Ieſus name.</l>
                  <l>The SPANIOL Prince exhorting thus</l>
                  <l>With glad and ſmiling cheare,</l>
                  <l>With ſugred wordes, and geſture good,</l>
                  <l>So pleas'd both eie and eare</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="500"/> That euerie man cryed victorie:</l>
                  <l>This word abroad they blew,</l>
                  <l>A good preſage that victorie</l>
                  <l>Thereafter ſhould enſew.</l>
                  <l>THE Turquiſh Hoſt in maner like</l>
                  <l>Themſelues they did array,</l>
                  <l>The which two, BASHAAS did command</l>
                  <l>And order euerie way.</l>
                  <l>For PORTAN BASHA had in charge,</l>
                  <l>To gouerne all by land,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="510"/> And ALI-BASHA had by Sea</l>
                  <l>The onely cheife command.</l>
                  <l>Theſe BASHAAS in the Battaile were,</l>
                  <l>With mo then I can tell,</l>
                  <l>And MAHOMET BEY the right wing had,</l>
                  <l>The left OCHIALI fell.</l>
                  <l>Then ALI-BASHA viſied all</l>
                  <l>With bolde and manly face,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe tongue did vtter courage more</l>
                  <l>Then had alluring grace:</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="520"/> He did recount amongſt the reſt</l>
                  <l>What victorie Turks obtaind</l>
                  <l>On catife Chriſtians, and how long</l>
                  <l>The OTTOMANS race had raignd.</l>
                  <l>He told them als, how long themſelues</l>
                  <l>Had victours euer bene,</l>
                  <l>Euen of theſe ſame three Princes ſmall,</l>
                  <l>That now durſt ſo conuene,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:42"/>
                  <l>And would yee then giue ſuch a lie</l>
                  <l>Vnto your glories paſt,</l>
                  <l>As let your ſelues be ouerthrowne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="530"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>By looſers at the laſt?</l>
                  <l>This victorie ſhall Europe make</l>
                  <l>To be your conqueſt pray,</l>
                  <l>And all the rare things therein till,</l>
                  <l>Ye carry ſhall away:</l>
                  <l>But if ye leeſe, remember well</l>
                  <l>How ye haue made them thrall,</l>
                  <l>This ſamin way, or worſe ſhall they</l>
                  <l>Demaine you one and all,</l>
                  <l>And then ſhall all your honours paſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="540"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>In ſmoke euaniſh quite,</l>
                  <l>And all your pleaſures turne in paine</l>
                  <l>In dolour your delite:</l>
                  <l>Take courage then, and boldlie to it,</l>
                  <l>Our MAHOMET will aid,</l>
                  <l>Conducting all your ſhots, and ſtroakes,</l>
                  <l>Of Arrow, Dart, and blaid:</l>
                  <l>For nothing care but onely one</l>
                  <l>Which onelie doth me fray,</l>
                  <l>That ere with them we euer meet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="550"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>For feare they flee away:</l>
                  <l>This ſpeach did ſo the Armie pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſo their minds did mooue,</l>
                  <l>That clincks of Swordes, and rattle of Pikes,</l>
                  <l>His ſpeaches did approoue.</l>
                  <l>THE gliſtering cleare of ſhining Sunne</l>
                  <l>Made both the Hoſts ſo glance,</l>
                  <l>As fiſhes eies did reele to ſee</l>
                  <l>Such hewes on Seas to dance:</l>
                  <l>But TITAN ſhinde on eies of Turkes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="560"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>And on the Chriſtian backes,</l>
                  <l>Although the wauering wind the which</l>
                  <l>But ſeldome ſetling tackes,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:42"/>
                  <l>The Turkes did ſecond euer ſtill</l>
                  <l>Whill but a little ſpace</l>
                  <l>Before the chocke, ô miracle,</l>
                  <l>It turnd into their face,</l>
                  <l>Which Chriſtians joyfull as a ſeale</l>
                  <l>And token did receaue,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="570"/> That God of Hoſts had promis'd them</l>
                  <l>They victorie ſhould haue.</l>
                  <l>Hovv ſoone a Cannons ſmokie throat</l>
                  <l>The Seas did dindle all,</l>
                  <l>And on BELLONA bold and wiſe,</l>
                  <l>And bloodie MARS did call,</l>
                  <l>And that the ſounding cleare of braſſe</l>
                  <l>Did als approoue the ſame,</l>
                  <l>And kindled courage into men</l>
                  <l>To winne immortall fame.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="580"/> But what? Me thinke I doe intend</l>
                  <l>This battaile to recite,</l>
                  <l>And what by Martiall force was done</l>
                  <l>My pen preſumes to write,</l>
                  <l>As if I had you bloodie God,</l>
                  <l>And all his power ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Yea to deſcriue the God of Hoſts</l>
                  <l>My pen had able beene:</l>
                  <l>No, no, no man that witnes was</l>
                  <l>Can ſet it out aright,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="590"/> Then how can I by heare-ſay do,</l>
                  <l>Which none could do by ſight:</l>
                  <l>But ſince I raſhlie tooke in hand,</l>
                  <l>I muſt aſſay it now,</l>
                  <l>With hope that this my good intent</l>
                  <l>Ye Readers will allow:</l>
                  <l>I alſo truſt that euen as he</l>
                  <l>Who in the Sunne doth walke</l>
                  <l>Is colourd by the ſamin Sunne,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall my following talke</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:43"/>
                  <l>Some ſauour keepe of Martiall acts, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="600"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Since I would paint them out,</l>
                  <l>And God ſhall to his honour als</l>
                  <l>My pen guide out of dout.</l>
                  <l>THIS warning giuen to Chriſtians they</l>
                  <l>With Turks yoake heere and there,</l>
                  <l>And firſt the ſixe aforeſaid Ships</l>
                  <l>That were ſo large and fair,</l>
                  <l>And placed were in the former ranks,</l>
                  <l>Did firſt of all perſew</l>
                  <l>With Bullets, Raiſers, Chaines, and nailes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="610"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>That from their peeces flew:</l>
                  <l>Their Cannons rummiſht all at once,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe mortall thudding draue,</l>
                  <l>The fatall Turks to be content</l>
                  <l>With THETIS for their graue.</l>
                  <l>The Fiſhes were aſtoniſht all,</l>
                  <l>To heare ſuch hideous ſound,</l>
                  <l>The Azur Skie was dim'd with Smoke,</l>
                  <l>The dinne that did abound,</l>
                  <l>Like thunder rearding rumling raue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="620"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>With roares the higheſt Heauen,</l>
                  <l>And pearſt with pith the gliſtering vaults</l>
                  <l>Of all the Planets ſeauen:</l>
                  <l>The piteous plaints, the hideous howles,</l>
                  <l>The greeuous cries and mones,</l>
                  <l>Of millions wounded ſundrie waies,</l>
                  <l>But dying all at ones,</l>
                  <l>Conjoynd with former horrible ſound,</l>
                  <l>Diſtemperd all the aire,</l>
                  <l>And made the Seas for terrour ſhake <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="630"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>With braying euery where:</l>
                  <l>Yet all theſe vnacquainted roares,</l>
                  <l>The feareful threatning ſound,</l>
                  <l>Ioynd with the groning murmuring howles</l>
                  <l>The courage could not wound</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:43"/>
                  <l>So farre of Turquiſh Chieftaines braue,</l>
                  <l>As them to let or fray</l>
                  <l>With boldeſt ſpeed their greeuous harmes</l>
                  <l>With like for to repay,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="640"/> Who made their Cannons bray ſo faſt</l>
                  <l>And Hagbuts cracke ſo thicke,</l>
                  <l>As Chriſtians dead in number almoſt</l>
                  <l>Did countervaile the quicke,</l>
                  <l>And ſent full many carcages</l>
                  <l>Of Seas to loweſt ground,</l>
                  <l>The Cannons thuds and cries of men</l>
                  <l>Did in the skie reſound:</l>
                  <l>But Turks remaind not long vnpaid</l>
                  <l>Euen with their proper coyne,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="650"/> By bitter ſhots which Chriſtians did</l>
                  <l>To former thundring ioyne:</l>
                  <l>Dead drop they downe on euery ſide,</l>
                  <l>Their ſighing Spreits eſchews,</l>
                  <l>And croſſes Styx into diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>To heare infernall newes:</l>
                  <l>Yea skarcelie could the ancient bote</l>
                  <l>Such number of ſoules containe,</l>
                  <l>But ſobbed vnderneath the weight</l>
                  <l>Of Paſſengers prophane.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="660"/> While here the Father ſtood with Sonne,</l>
                  <l>A whirling round doth beare</l>
                  <l>The lead that dings the Father in droſſe</l>
                  <l>And fils the Sonne with feare,</l>
                  <l>Whill there a Chieftaine ſhrillie cries,</l>
                  <l>And Soldats doth command,</l>
                  <l>A ſpeedie Pellet ſtops his ſpeach,</l>
                  <l>And ſtaies his pointing hand,</l>
                  <l>Whill time a cluſtered troupe doth ſtand</l>
                  <l>Amasſt together all,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="670"/> A fatall Bullet them among</l>
                  <l>Makes ſome ſelected fall:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:44"/>
                  <l>The hideous noiſe ſo deaf'd them all,</l>
                  <l>Increaſing euer ſtill,</l>
                  <l>That readie Soldats could not heare</l>
                  <l>Their wiſe commanders will,</l>
                  <l>But euery man as MARS him mou'd,</l>
                  <l>And as occaſion ſeru'd</l>
                  <l>His dutie did the beſt he might,</l>
                  <l>And for no perrill ſweru'd,</l>
                  <l>Their olde commanders precepts paſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="680"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>They put in practiſe then,</l>
                  <l>And onely memorie did command</l>
                  <l>That multitude of men.</l>
                  <l>THVS after they with Cannons had</l>
                  <l>Their dutie done a farre,</l>
                  <l>And time in end had wearied them</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch embaſſad warre,</l>
                  <l>A rude recounter then they made,</l>
                  <l>Together Galleis clipt,</l>
                  <l>And each on other raſht her noſe,</l>
                  <l>That in the Sea was dipt: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="690"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>No manner of man was idle then,</l>
                  <l>Each man his armes did vſe,</l>
                  <l>No skaping place is in the Seas</l>
                  <l>Though men would MARS refuſe:</l>
                  <l>The valiant Knight with Coutlaſſe ſharpe</l>
                  <l>Of fighting foe doth part</l>
                  <l>The bloodie head from bodie pale:</l>
                  <l>Whill one with deadlie dart</l>
                  <l>Doth pearce his enemies heart in twaine, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="700"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>An other fearce doth ſtrike</l>
                  <l>Quite through his fellowes Arme or Leg,</l>
                  <l>With pointed brangling Pike:</l>
                  <l>The Cannons leaues not thundering of,</l>
                  <l>Nor Hagbuts ſhooting ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And ſeldome Powder waſts in vaine</l>
                  <l>But either wound or kill:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:44"/>
                  <l>Yea euen the ſimple forceats fought</l>
                  <l>With beggers boltes anew,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="730"/> Wherewith full manie principall men</l>
                  <l>They wounded ſore and ſlew:</l>
                  <l>Whill time a Chriſtian with a ſworde,</l>
                  <l>Lets out a faithleſſe breath,</l>
                  <l>A Turke on him doth with a darte,</l>
                  <l>Reuenge his fellowes death,</l>
                  <l>Whill time a Turk with arrow doth,</l>
                  <l>Shoot through a Chriſtians arme,</l>
                  <l>A Chriſtian with a Pike dooth pearce</l>
                  <l>The hand that did the harme:</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="720"/> Whill time a Chriſtian Cannon killes</l>
                  <l>A Turke with threatning ſound,</l>
                  <l>A Hagbut hittes the Cannoner,</l>
                  <l>Who dead, falles to the ground:</l>
                  <l>The beggers boltes by forceates caſten,</l>
                  <l>On all hands made to flie,</l>
                  <l>Iaw-bones and braines of kild and hurt,</l>
                  <l>Who wiſht (for paine) to die:</l>
                  <l>The clinkes of ſwords, the rattle of Pikes,</l>
                  <l>The whirre of arrowes light,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="730"/> The howles of hurt, the Captaines cryes</l>
                  <l>In vaine do what they might,</l>
                  <l>The cracks of Gallies broken and bruzd,</l>
                  <l>Of Gunns the rumbling beire</l>
                  <l>Reſounded ſo, that though the Lord</l>
                  <l>Had thundered none could heare:</l>
                  <l>The Sea was verniſhed red with blood,</l>
                  <l>And fiſhes poyſond all,</l>
                  <l>As IEHOVA by MOSES rod</l>
                  <l>In Aegipt made befall.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="740"/> THIS cruell fight continued thus</l>
                  <l>Vncertaine all the while,</l>
                  <l>For Fortune oft on either ſide,</l>
                  <l>Did frowne and after ſmile,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:45"/>
                  <l>It ſeem'd that MARS and PALLAS both <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="780"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Did thinke the day too ſhort</l>
                  <l>With bloodie practiſe thus to vſe</l>
                  <l>Their olde acquainted ſport:</l>
                  <l>For as the ſlaughter ay increaſt,</l>
                  <l>So did the courage ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Of Martiall men whome loſſe of friends</l>
                  <l>Enarm'd with eigre will,</l>
                  <l>The more their number did decreaſe</l>
                  <l>The more that they were harmd,</l>
                  <l>The more with MARS then were they fild</l>
                  <l>With boldning ſpite inarm'd: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="790"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Now vp now downe on either ſide,</l>
                  <l>Now Chriſtians ſeemd to winne,</l>
                  <l>Now ouerthrowne, and now againe,</l>
                  <l>They ſeem'd but to beginne.</l>
                  <l>My pen for pitie cannot write,</l>
                  <l>My haire for horrour ſtands,</l>
                  <l>To thinke how many Chriſtians there</l>
                  <l>Were kild by Pagane hands.</l>
                  <l>O Lord throughout this Labyrinth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="800"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Make me the way to vew,</l>
                  <l>And let thy holy three-folde Spreit</l>
                  <l>Be my conducting clew:</l>
                  <l>O now I ſpie a bleſſed Heauen,</l>
                  <l>Our landing is not farre:</l>
                  <l>Lo good victorious tidings comes</l>
                  <l>To end this cruell warre.</l>
                  <l>IN ALL the time that thus they fought,</l>
                  <l>The Spaniſh Prince was clipt</l>
                  <l>With ALI-BASHA, whome to meet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="810"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>The reſt he had oreſlipt:</l>
                  <l>And euen as throughout both the Hoſts,</l>
                  <l>Dame Fortune varied ſtill,</l>
                  <l>So kythde ſhe twixt thoſe Champions two,</l>
                  <l>Her fond inconſtant will:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:45"/>
                  <l>For after that the Caſtels foure</l>
                  <l>Of Galleis both, with ſound,</l>
                  <l>And ſlaughter huge, their Bullets had</l>
                  <l>In other made rebound,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="820"/> And all the ſmall Artillerie</l>
                  <l>Conſumde their ſhots below</l>
                  <l>In killing men, or els to cut</l>
                  <l>Some Cable ſtrong or Towe:</l>
                  <l>Yet victorie ſtill vncertaine was,</l>
                  <l>And Soldats neuer ceaſt</l>
                  <l>(With interchange of Pikes and Darts.)</l>
                  <l>To kill, or wound at leaſt.</l>
                  <l>In end, when they with blood abroad</l>
                  <l>Had bought their meeting deare,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="830"/> The victorie firſt on Spaniſh ſide</l>
                  <l>Began for to appeare:</l>
                  <l>For euen the Spaniſh Prince himſelfe</l>
                  <l>Did hazard at the laſt,</l>
                  <l>Accompanied with boldeſt men</l>
                  <l>Who followd on him faſt,</l>
                  <l>By force to winne the Turquiſh decke,</l>
                  <l>The which he did obtaine,</l>
                  <l>And entered in their Galley ſyne</l>
                  <l>But did not long remaine:</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="840"/> For ALI-BASHA proou'd ſo well,</l>
                  <l>With his aſsiſters braue,</l>
                  <l>That backward faſter then they came</l>
                  <l>Their valiant foes they draue,</l>
                  <l>That glad they were to skape themſelues,</l>
                  <l>And leaue behind anew</l>
                  <l>Of valiant fellowes carcaſes,</l>
                  <l>Whom thus their enemies ſlew.</l>
                  <l>The Generall boldned then with ſpite,</l>
                  <l>And verniſht redde with ſhame,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="850"/> Did rather chuſe to leeſe his life</l>
                  <l>Then tine his ſpreading fame:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:46"/>
                  <l>And ſo of new encouraged</l>
                  <l>His Souldiers true and bolde,</l>
                  <l>As now for eigreneſſe they burne</l>
                  <l>Who earſt were waxed colde:</l>
                  <l>And thus they entred in againe</l>
                  <l>More fiercelie then before,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe rude aſſault could ALI then</l>
                  <l>Reſiſt not anie more,</l>
                  <l>But fled vnto the forte at STEVIN. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="860"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>For laſt refuge of all,</l>
                  <l>Abiding in a doubtſome feare</l>
                  <l>The chance he did befall.</l>
                  <l>A MACEDONIAN ſouldier then</l>
                  <l>Great honour for to win,</l>
                  <l>Before the reſt in earneſt hope</l>
                  <l>To BASHA bold did rin,</l>
                  <l>And with a Cutlace ſharp and fyne</l>
                  <l>Did whip mee off his head,</l>
                  <l>Who lackt not his reward of him <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="870"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>That did the Nauie lead:</l>
                  <l>The Generall ſyne caus'd fixe the head</l>
                  <l>Vpon his Galley Maſt,</l>
                  <l>At ſight whereof, the faithleſſe Hoſt</l>
                  <l>Were all ſo ſore agaſt,</l>
                  <l>That all amas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gaue backe at once,</l>
                  <l>But yet were ſtaid againe,</l>
                  <l>And neuer one at all did ſcape,</l>
                  <l>But taken were or ſlaine</l>
                  <l>OCHIALI except, with three times ten <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="880"/> 
                  </l>
                  <l>Great Galleis of his owne,</l>
                  <l>And many of the Knights of MALT</l>
                  <l>Whome he had ouerthrowne:</l>
                  <l>But if that he with his conuoy</l>
                  <l>Had miſt a ſafe retreat,</l>
                  <l>No newes had SELYM but by brute</l>
                  <l>heard euer of this defeat.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:46"/>
                  <l>WHEN thus the victorie was obteind,</l>
                  <l>And thankes were giuen to God,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="890"/> Twelue thouſand Chriſtians counted were</l>
                  <l>Releeu'd from Turquiſh rod.</l>
                  <l>O Spaniſh Prince whome of a glance</l>
                  <l>And ſuddainlie away</l>
                  <l>The cruell fates gaue to the world</l>
                  <l>Not ſuffering thee to ſtay.</l>
                  <l>With this the ſtill night ſad and blacke</l>
                  <l>The earth ouer ſhadowed then,</l>
                  <l>Who MORPHEVS brought with her and reſt</l>
                  <l>To ſteale on beaſts and men.</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="900"/> BVT all this time was Venice Towne</l>
                  <l>Reuoluing what euent</l>
                  <l>Might come of this prepared fight,</l>
                  <l>With doubtſome mindes and bent:</l>
                  <l>They long'd, and yet they durſt not long</l>
                  <l>To heare the newes of all,</l>
                  <l>They hoped good, they feard the euill,</l>
                  <l>And keſt what might befall:</l>
                  <l>At laſt the joyfull tidings came,</l>
                  <l>Which ſuch a gladnes bred,</l>
                  <l> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="910"/> That Matrons graue, and Maids modeſt,</l>
                  <l>The Market place beſpred:</l>
                  <l>Anone with chearefull countenance</l>
                  <l>They dreſſe them in a ring,</l>
                  <l>And thus the formeſt did begin</l>
                  <l>Syne all the reſt to ſing.</l>
                  <div type="chorus">
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:47"/>
                     <head>CHORVS VENETVS.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SIng praiſe to God both young and olde</l>
                        <l>That in this towne remaine,</l>
                        <l>With voice, and euerie Inſtrument,</l>
                        <l>Found out by mortall braine:</l>
                        <l>Sing praiſes to our mightie God,</l>
                        <l>Praiſe our deliuerars name,</l>
                        <l>Our louing Lord, who now in need,</l>
                        <l>Hath kythd to be the ſame,</l>
                        <l>The faithles ſnares did compaſſe vs,</l>
                        <l>Their netts were ſet about,</l>
                        <l>But yet our deareſt Father in Heauen,</l>
                        <l>He hath redeemd vs out.</l>
                        <l>Not onlie that, but by his power,</l>
                        <l>Our enemies feet they ſlaid,</l>
                        <l>Whome he hath trapt, and made to fall</l>
                        <l>Into the pit they made:</l>
                        <l>Sing praiſes then both young and olde,</l>
                        <l>That in this towne remaine,</l>
                        <l>To him that hath releeued our necks,</l>
                        <l>From Turquiſh yoak prophaine.</l>
                        <l>Let vs waſh off our ſinnes impure,</l>
                        <l>Caſt off our garments vile,</l>
                        <l>And hant his Temple euerie day,</l>
                        <l>To praiſe his name a while.</l>
                        <l>O praiſe him for the victorie,</l>
                        <l>That he hath made vs haue,</l>
                        <l>For he it was reuengd our cauſe,</l>
                        <l>And not our armie braue:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8720:47"/>
                        <l>Praiſe him with Trumpet, Piphre, and drumme,</l>
                        <l>With Lutes, and Organes fine,</l>
                        <l>With Viols, Gitterns, Ciſtiers als,</l>
                        <l>And ſweeteſt voices ſyne:</l>
                        <l>Sing praiſe, ſing praiſe both young and olde,</l>
                        <l>Sing praiſes one and all,</l>
                        <l>To him who hath redeemd vs now,</l>
                        <l>From cruell Pagans thrall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>IN HEARING of this ſong mee thinks</l>
                        <l>My members waxes faint,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet from dulnes can I keepe,</l>
                        <l>My minde by no reſtraint.</l>
                        <l>But lo my Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nie head doth nod,</l>
                        <l>Vpon my Adamant breſt,</l>
                        <l>My eie-lidds will ſtand vp no more,</l>
                        <l>But falles to take them reſt.</l>
                        <l>And through my weak and wearie hand,</l>
                        <l>Doth ſlide my pen of lead,</l>
                        <l>And ſleep doth els poſſeſſe mee all,</l>
                        <l>The ſimilitude of dead.</l>
                        <l>The God with golden wings through ports,</l>
                        <l>Of horne doth to me creepe,</l>
                        <l>Who changes ofter ſhapes transformd</l>
                        <l>Then PROTEVS in the deepe.</l>
                        <l>How ſoone he came, quite from my minde,</l>
                        <l>He worldlie cares remou'd,</l>
                        <l>And all my members in my bed,</l>
                        <l>Lay ſtill in reſt beloud.</l>
                        <l>And ſyne I heard a joifull ſong</l>
                        <l>Of all the fethered bands</l>
                        <l>Of holie Angels in the heauen,</l>
                        <l>Thus ſinging on all hands.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="chorus">
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:48"/>
                     <head>CHORVS ANGELORVM.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SIng let vs ſing with one accord</l>
                        <l>HALLELV-IAH on hie,</l>
                        <l>With euery elder that doth bow</l>
                        <l>Before the Lambe his knee:</l>
                        <l>Sing foure and twentie all with vs</l>
                        <l>Whill Heauen and earth reſound</l>
                        <l>Repleniſht with IEHOVAS praiſe</l>
                        <l>Whoſe like cannot be found:</l>
                        <l>For he it is, that is, and was,</l>
                        <l>And euermore ſhall be,</l>
                        <l>One onelie one vnſeparate,</l>
                        <l>And yet in perſons three.</l>
                        <l>Praiſe him for that he creat hath</l>
                        <l>The Heauen, the earth and all,</l>
                        <l>And euer hath preſeru'd them ſince</l>
                        <l>From their ruine and fall:</l>
                        <l>But praiſe him more if more can be,</l>
                        <l>That ſo he loues his name,</l>
                        <l>As he doth mercie ſhew to all</l>
                        <l>That doe profeſſe the ſame:</l>
                        <l>And not alanerlie to them</l>
                        <l>Profeſsing it aright,</l>
                        <l>But euen to them that mixe therewith</l>
                        <l>Their owne inuentions ſlight:</l>
                        <l>As ſpecially this ſamin time</l>
                        <l>Moſt plainlie may appeare,</l>
                        <l>In giuing them ſuch victorie</l>
                        <l>That not aright him feare:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8720:48"/>
                        <l>For ſince he ſhewes ſuch grace to them</l>
                        <l>That thinks themſelues are juſt,</l>
                        <l>What will he more to them that in</l>
                        <l>His mercies onelie truſt?</l>
                        <l>And ſith that ſo he vſes them</l>
                        <l>That doubt for to be ſau'd,</l>
                        <l>How much more them that in their hearts</l>
                        <l>His promiſe haue engrau'd?</l>
                        <l>And ſince he doth ſuch fauour ſhew</l>
                        <l>To them that fondlie pray</l>
                        <l>To other Mediatours then</l>
                        <l>Can helpe them any way:</l>
                        <l>O how then will he fauour them,</l>
                        <l>Who praiers do direct</l>
                        <l>Vnto the Lambe, whome onely he</l>
                        <l>Ordaind for that effect?</l>
                        <l>And ſince he doth reuenge their cauſe</l>
                        <l>That worſhip God of bread,</l>
                        <l>(An errour vaine the which is bred,</l>
                        <l>But in a mortall head)</l>
                        <l>Then how will he reuenge their cauſe</l>
                        <l>That onelie feare and ſerue,</l>
                        <l>His deareſt Sonne, and for his ſake</l>
                        <l>Will for no perrils ſwerue:</l>
                        <l>And ſince that ſo he pities them</l>
                        <l>That beare vpon their brow,</l>
                        <l>The marke of Antichriſt the whoore</l>
                        <l>That great abuſer now,</l>
                        <l>Who does the trueſt Chriſtians</l>
                        <l>With fire and ſword inuade,</l>
                        <l>And make them holie Martyrs that</l>
                        <l>Their truſt in God haue laid,</l>
                        <l>How will he them that thus are vſde,</l>
                        <l>And beares vpon their face</l>
                        <l>His ſpeciall marke, a certaine ſigne</l>
                        <l>Of euerlaſting grace?</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8720:49"/>
                        <l>Put end vnto the traueils (Lord)</l>
                        <l>And miſeries of thy Sancts,</l>
                        <l>Remouing quite this blindnes groſſe</l>
                        <l>That now the world ſo dants:</l>
                        <l>Sing praiſes of his mercie then</l>
                        <l>His ſuperexcellence great,</l>
                        <l>Which doth exceed euen all his works</l>
                        <l>That lie before his ſeat:</l>
                        <l>And let vs ſing both now and ay</l>
                        <l>To him with one accord,</l>
                        <l>O holie, holie, God of Hoſts,</l>
                        <l>Thou euerliuing Lord.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THVS ended was the Angels ſong,</l>
                        <l>And alſo heere I end:</l>
                        <l>Exhorting all you Chriſtians true</l>
                        <l>Your courage vp to bend,</l>
                        <l>And ſince by this defeat ye ſee,</l>
                        <l>That God doth loue his name</l>
                        <l>So well, that ſo he did them aid</l>
                        <l>That ſeru'd not right the ſame.</l>
                        <l>Then though the Antichriſtian ſect</l>
                        <l>Againſt you do conjure,</l>
                        <l>He doth the bodie better loue</l>
                        <l>Then ſhadow be ye ſure:</l>
                        <l>Do ye reſiſt with confidence,</l>
                        <l>That God ſhall be your ſtay</l>
                        <l>And turne it to your comfort, and</l>
                        <l>His glorie now and ay.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="sonnet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:49"/>
                  <head>SONET.</head>
                  <l>THe azur'd vaulte, the cryſtall circles bright,</l>
                  <l>The gleaming fyrie torches powdred there,</l>
                  <l>The changing round, the ſhyning beamie light,</l>
                  <l>The ſad and bearded fyres, the monſters faire:</l>
                  <l>The prodiges appearing in the aire,</l>
                  <l>The rearding thunders, and the bluſtering winds,</l>
                  <l>The foules, in hew, in ſhape, and nature raire,</l>
                  <l>The prettie notes that wing'd muſiciens finds:</l>
                  <l>In earth the ſau'rie floures, the mettal'd minds,</l>
                  <l>The wholeſome hearbes, the hautie pleaſant trees,</l>
                  <l>The ſyluer ſtreames, the beaſts of ſundrie kinds,</l>
                  <l>The bounded roares, and fiſhes of the ſeas:</l>
                  <l>All theſe, for teaching man, the LORD did frame,</l>
                  <l>To do his will, whoſe glorie ſhines in thame.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I. R. S.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="fre">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:50"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:50"/>
                  <p>LA LE PANTHE DE IAQVES VI. ROY D'ESCOSSE, Faicte francoiſe par le Sieur <hi>Du BARTAS.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>IMPRIME A EDINBVRG PAR <hi>ROBERT WALDE-GRAVE,</hi> Imprimeur du Roy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno Dom. 1591.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Auec Priuilege de ſa Majeſté.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:51"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:51"/>
                  <head>AV LECTEVR.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ECTEVR, ne penſe point qu'un deſir d'augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter ma reputation m'ait pouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſé à trauailler apres ceſte verſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que poureté d'eſpritqu'il y ait en moy, ſi ſuis-je, par la grace de Dieu, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coup plus fecond en matiere, qu'en motz: &amp; l'inuention me couſte moins, que l'elocution. C'eſt pourquoy i'auoy fait voeu à mes plus ſainctes Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, de ne mettre jamais la main à traduction ou para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe quelco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que. Mais, que ne pourroit ſur moy, je ne dis pas la grandeur, ains l'admirable eſprit du Roy d'Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſſe? La graue douceur, la belle &amp; artificieuſe liaiſon, les viues &amp; parlantes deſcriptions de ſa Lepa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>the m'ont tellement rauy, que j'ay eſte contraint de fauſſer mon ſerment. Accepte donques, ie te prie, ceſte plante que l'Apollon de noſtre temps a ſemé de ſa propre main, &amp; les Graces ont arrouſé du nectar plus diuin qui coule de leur bouche. Et bien que pour eſtre tranſportée en autre ſolage, elle ait perdu ſes plus belles fleurs: touteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fois ſon eſtoc, ſes branches, &amp; la plus part de ſes fueil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les luy ſont demeurées. Le peintre peut bien exprimer &amp; le pourfil, &amp; les couleurs d'un beau viſage: mais non l'air, le geſte, &amp; moins encor la parolle. Que ſi meſme quand au ſens tu trouues que ceſt extraict ne reſpond point entierement à ſon original, propoſe toy que ceſt ouurage ne faiſoit que ſortir encores tout blueta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t de la forge Royale, quand je luy donnay la façon françoiſe: &amp; que depuis ſa Majeſté l'a rebattu, &amp; relimé, &amp; breffait tel, qu'il ſemble eſtre ſorti de la boutique d'Homere.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="translators_preface_to_the_author">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:52"/>
                  <head>PREFACE DV TRADVCTEVR <hi>A LAVTHEVR.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>IAQVES,</hi> ſi tu marchois d un pied mortel ça bas,</l>
                     <l>Hardy i'entreprendroy de tallonner tes pas:</l>
                     <l>I'estendroy tous mes nerfs, &amp; ma courſe ſacrée</l>
                     <l>Loing, loing lairroit à dos les aiſles de Borée.</l>
                     <l>Mais puis qu Aigle nouueau tu te guindes és cieux,</l>
                     <l>Collé bas, ie te ſuy ſeulement de mes yeux:</l>
                     <l>Mais plustost du deſir: ou, ſi ie me remuë,</l>
                     <l>Ombre ie vole en terre, &amp; toy dedans la nuë.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hé! fuſſe-ie vrayment, ô Phoenix Eſcoſſois,</l>
                     <l>Ou lombre de ton corps, ou l'Echo de ta voix.</l>
                     <l>Si ie n'auoy l'azur, l'or, &amp; l'argent encore</l>
                     <l>Dont ton plumage astré brillantement s'honnore,</l>
                     <l>Au moins i'auroy ta forme: &amp; ſimon rude vers</l>
                     <l>N'exprimoit la douceur de tant d'accords diuers,</l>
                     <l>Il retiendroit quelque air de tes voix plus qu'humaines,</l>
                     <l>Mais, Pies, taiſez vous pour ouyr les Camoenes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:52"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LA LEPANTHE</hi> DE IAQVES VI. ROY D'ESCOSSE, FAICTE Françoiſe par le S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Du BARTAS.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>E chante du grand Dieu la iuſtice &amp; bonté,</l>
                     <l>Vn exploit de ſes mains non encore chanté:</l>
                     <l>Vn combat hazardeux, vne dure iournée:</l>
                     <l>Ie deſcry dans ces vers la bataille donnée</l>
                     <l>Sur le flot <hi>LEPANTHOIS,</hi> qui ſe vid arrousé</l>
                     <l>Et du ſang Circoncis, &amp; du ſang baptizé.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>VIEN,</hi> vien donques, Seigneur, ô Maiesté diuine,</l>
                     <l>Tout-puiſſante, immortelle, vne en trois, en vn trine,</l>
                     <l>O Pere de ce Tout, ie te prie trois fois,</l>
                     <l>Par ton vnique Fils, ton immortelle voix,</l>
                     <l>Le bras de ton vouloir, l'Ange du teſmoignage,</l>
                     <l>Que ton Eſprit ſacré ſur l'or de ceſte page</l>
                     <l>Face couler vn vers, en graces ſi parfaict,</l>
                     <l>Qu'il paſſe merùeilleux les merueilles du faict.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le trois-fois Saint ayant pour throne le haut Pole,</l>
                     <l>Les Anges pour archers, à ſon flanc ſa Parole,</l>
                     <l>L'Eternel vid vn iour, (l'erre car deuant <hi>DIEV</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Le Temps enfant du Ciel, ne peut point auoir lieu.</l>
                     <l>Le temps deſia paſſé, qui paſsera, qui paſſe,</l>
                     <l>Touſiours confus ne ſont qu'un temps deuant ſa face.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:53"/>
                     <l>Mais quoy? l'homme mortel pour parler clairement</l>
                     <l>Aux hommes, eſt contraint parler humainement:</l>
                     <l>La chair n'attaint au ciel, &amp; les langues mortelles</l>
                     <l>Beguayent en parlant des choſes eternelles.)</l>
                     <l>Il vid, di-ie, au milieu de la troupe celeſte</l>
                     <l>L'ennemi de ſon nom, &amp; des hommes la peſte:</l>
                     <l>Le Saint vid a ſes pieds le premier impoſteur,</l>
                     <l>De crimes forgeron, ſeme-yuraye, menteur,</l>
                     <l>Auquel Chriſt parle ainſi: Monſtre plein d'impudence,</l>
                     <l>Tu viens (le ſçay-ie pas?) de l'antique Byzance</l>
                     <l>Pour remplir boute-feu, d'ire &amp; forcenement,</l>
                     <l>Du Turc porte-turban le fier entendement</l>
                     <l>Contre ceux qu'à mon nom l'humble genouil flechiſſent.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>PERE</hi> permettras-tu que ces chiens les pestriſſent</l>
                     <l>Sous leurs profanes pieds? que ceux qui ſont ſans foy</l>
                     <l>Triomphent des humains qui t'adorent en moy</l>
                     <l>D'une foy viue armez? qu'en deſpit de ton ire</l>
                     <l>Ils ſoient executeurs de tout ce qu'il conſpire?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Quelle foy? dit Satan: ne ſçay-tu pas qu'ils font,</l>
                     <l>Impudens, à qui mieux couronnera ſon front</l>
                     <l>Du laurier de reuolte? a tu pas exposée</l>
                     <l>Et la gent Muzulmane, &amp; la gent baptizée</l>
                     <l>Entre mes rouges mains, a fin que leur ſupplice</l>
                     <l>Reſponde à leur forfait, reſponde à ma malice?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Adonques l' Eternel qui du ſeul croulement,</l>
                     <l>De ſon chef rayonneus meutiusqu' au fondement</l>
                     <l>Les montagneux rochers, fait chanceler le Pole,</l>
                     <l>Bouleuerſe l'Enfer: ce <hi>DIEV</hi> dont la Parole</l>
                     <l>D'un rien fit de ce Tout l'ouurage ſi parfait,</l>
                     <l>Et le maintient encore en l'eſtat qu'il l'afait,</l>
                     <l>Prononça, non des motz, ains des bruyants tonnerres:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dragon crache-venin, ruzé fufil des guerres,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:53"/>
                     <l>Vilain, lasche la prise, espargne les Chreſtiens,</l>
                     <l>Et n'oſe, ô Tentateur, t'attaquer plus aux miens.</l>
                     <l>Tout Chreſtien ſert mon Fils, &amp; bien qu'en mainte ſorte,</l>
                     <l>Il demente aueuglé le ſacré nom qu'il porte,</l>
                     <l>Qu'il erre en pluſieurs points: ſi veux-ie toutes-fois</l>
                     <l>Que le nom de mon Chriſt luy ſerue de pauois:</l>
                     <l>Tant ce doux nom m'eſt ſainct: tant ie veux qu'on ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nore</l>
                     <l>Ce beau nom que l'Enfer, le Ciel, la Terre adore.</l>
                     <l>Affronteur ceſse donc. Mais toy Force de <hi>DIEV</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Qui de zele empenné diſcours de lieu en lieu,</l>
                     <l>Comme mon ambaſsade, ô loing-volant Archange</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>GABRIEL,</hi> l'un des chefs de l'aſtreuse phalange,</l>
                     <l>Va t'en viſte à Venice, &amp; graue dans le coeur</l>
                     <l>De leur graue Senat vne guerriere ardeur,</l>
                     <l>De venger tant de torts que les dextres cruelles</l>
                     <l>Des raſez Muzulmans ont fait à mes fideles.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Il court toſt, &amp; pluſtoſt qu'un vent roule caillous</l>
                     <l>Ne haſte entre deux monts ſon murmurant courrous.</l>
                     <l>Sa pensée luy ſert d' vne viſteſse extreme,</l>
                     <l>Car il n'eſt à peu pres que penſée luy-meſme.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>La trafiqueuse mer de tous coſtez enferme</l>
                     <l>Ceſte ville, qui n'eſt Iſle, ny terre ferme,</l>
                     <l>Ville, qui flotte en l'eau, ville ſans fondement,</l>
                     <l>Qu'une foreſt plantée en l'onde artistement</l>
                     <l>A grands coups de belier ſupporte, &amp; porte aux nuës,</l>
                     <l>Grand'ville qui n'a point moins de mers, que de ruës.</l>
                     <l>Montéſur vne tour à cent bouches d'airain,</l>
                     <l>Tu vois vne mer ſeche, vn champ fait à la main,</l>
                     <l>Vn abbregé du monde, vne iſle riche &amp; grande,</l>
                     <l>Ou preſide vn ſeul Duc, ou le Senat commande.</l>
                     <l>Saint <hi>MARC</hi> eſt leur Patron: &amp; leur eſpouſe encor</l>
                     <l>La marchande Thetis, que d'une bague d'or,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:54"/>
                     <l>Ils estrenent chaſqu' an. Le meſsager celeste</l>
                     <l>Arriué là dedans prend la forme, &amp; le geſte</l>
                     <l>D'vn bourgeois ia chenu: ſe promeine, &amp; trouuant</l>
                     <l>Vn ſage citadin, met ces motz en auant.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Helas! que faiſons nous? ſommes nous lethargiques?</l>
                     <l>Nous ſommes oppreſsez, par ces cruels Ethniques,</l>
                     <l>Et ne le ſentons point? noz forts ſont mis à bas,</l>
                     <l>Noz guerriers eſgorgez, &amp; ne le voyons pas?</l>
                     <l>Allons, que tardez vous? chargeons ceſte racaille,</l>
                     <l>Vuidons noz vieux debats par vn iour de bataille.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>DIEV</hi> ſecourt les hardis Cela dit, ils enfuit.</l>
                     <l>Ce propos courageus de bouche en bouche ſuit</l>
                     <l>Tous le coins de la ville: Il paruient à l'oreille</l>
                     <l>De l'auguſte Senat: qui ſoudain ſe reueille</l>
                     <l>De ſon profond ſommeil: l'approuue, &amp; ſage faict</l>
                     <l>Ce qu'il doit, ce qu'il peut pour le mettre en effect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ce peuple eſtoit tenu par les lunez gendarmes</l>
                     <l>De ſi court qu'ilz n'auoient que les ſeuls voeus pourarmes:</l>
                     <l>La Cypre eſtoit ia priſe, &amp; le bord mugiſſant</l>
                     <l>D'Adrie, eſtoit le bord de ſon ſceptre impuiſſant.</l>
                     <l>Il ſupplie l'Egliſe eſparſe par la terre,</l>
                     <l>Qu'en priant elle arrache au Seigneur le tonnerre</l>
                     <l>Qui gronde ſur ſon chef: La ville engemiſsant,</l>
                     <l>Importune ſans fin le trois-fois-Tout-puiſſant:</l>
                     <l>Tous les iours elle ieuſne: elle ioint ſes mains ſainctes:</l>
                     <l>On ne voit rien que pleurs: on n'entend rien que plaintes.</l>
                     <l>Les hommes plus guerriers ſont mandez au cercueil</l>
                     <l>Frappez tant ſeulement du fer mouſſe du dueil:</l>
                     <l>La femme donne laict de triſteſſe ſe paſme:</l>
                     <l>L'enfançon qui le void de ducil rend preſque lame.</l>
                     <l>La plus gaye ieuneſſe a d'vn noir veſtement,</l>
                     <l>Affublé tout ſon corps: le plus riche ornement</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:54"/>
                     <l>De l'azur eſtoillé, le clair cierge du monde,</l>
                     <l>Pluſtoſt qu'il ne ſouloit ſe replonge en ſon onde</l>
                     <l>D'vn front rebarbatif, affreux, &amp; renfrongné:</l>
                     <l>La blaffarde Miſere a tout d'vn coup donné</l>
                     <l>La chaſse à Cupidon. Dans leurs maiſons dorées</l>
                     <l>Flottent les tiedes pleurs: autour, les mers irées.</l>
                     <l>Les eaux bruyent autour: dedans, les hurlements:</l>
                     <l>Leur cri deſ-eſperé perçant les Elements</l>
                     <l>Monte iuſques au Ciel. <hi>MVSE,</hi> tourne en arriere</l>
                     <l>Et, ſage, remetz toy ſur ta route premiere.</l>
                     <l>Crains-tu pas que les pleurs ſur mon papier coulants,</l>
                     <l>Effaçent les noirs traitz de mes diſcours ſanglants?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>TELLE</hi> eſtoit la Cité, quand l'empenné meſsage</l>
                     <l>De ſon peuple marin r'allume le courage.</l>
                     <l>Noz Roys, ſollicitez par elle tous les iours,</l>
                     <l>Vont en fin accordant le demandé ſecours.</l>
                     <l>La ſaincte ligue est faicte: &amp; ſur la verte riue</l>
                     <l>Du fort <hi>MESSENIEN</hi> tout l'ost Chreſtien arriue.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Là, comme General <hi>DON-IEAN</hi> l' Auſtrichien</l>
                     <l>Luit ainſi qu'vn Soleil: l'honneur Venitien</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>VENIER</hi> s'y trouue auſsi: le Geneuois <hi>DORIE,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Et <hi>COLOMNE</hi> pilier du pilier d'Heſperie,</l>
                     <l>De la ville à ſept monts. Or pluſieurs iours s'estant</l>
                     <l>Entre ces braues chefs paſsez en conſultant,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ASCAIGNE</hi> de la Corne, homme prudent &amp; braue</l>
                     <l>Auance ce diſcours non moins facond que graue:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>SEIGNEVRS,</hi> on ne doit pas hazarder vn eſtat</l>
                     <l>Sur le rouët leger d'vn incertain combat</l>
                     <l>Quand la guerre ſe fait dans les propres entrailles</l>
                     <l>De noſtre cher païs: quand des dures batailles</l>
                     <l>Le bien-heureux ſuccez n'apporte tant de fruict</l>
                     <l>Auxvainqueurs, qu'aux vaincuz vne grand'route nuit:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:55"/>
                     <l>Et beaucoup moins encor quand l'armée ennemie</l>
                     <l>Combatuë du Ciel, de faim, d'Epidemie</l>
                     <l>Peu à peu ſe desbande: ou quand plus d'eſtendarts</l>
                     <l>Marchent en l'oſt hayneux, qu'aux nostres des ſoudarts.</l>
                     <l>Lors certes il vaut mieux laiſser cuuer leurrage,</l>
                     <l>Et caler voile vn peu, que faire entier naufrage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O genereux Heros, puis que nous nefaiſons</l>
                     <l>Laguerre à Soliman ſur l'huis de noz maiſons,</l>
                     <l>Que ſon ost ne ſe rompt: &amp; que nostre exercite</l>
                     <l>Superbe est composé de tant d'hommes d'eſlite,</l>
                     <l>Si fort, ſi bien muny: que pour eſtre vainqueur</l>
                     <l>Sans doute rien ne peut luy manquer que le coeur:</l>
                     <l>Attaquons l'ennemi, iectants ſus lapuiſsance</l>
                     <l>Du <hi>DIEV</hi> donne-lauriers l'ancre de l'eſperance.</l>
                     <l>Bon droit vaut mieux que force. Il est vray que pluſtoſt</l>
                     <l>Que nous venons aux mains, il faut policer l'oſt,</l>
                     <l>L'aſseurer, l'exercer: de peur qu'à l'impourueuë</l>
                     <l>Du Barbareſque arroy l'esblouiſsante veuë</l>
                     <l>N'esbranle les plus fiers: que les commandements</l>
                     <l>Diuers n'aillent troublant noz croiſez regiments:</l>
                     <l>Et le ſoldat couché freſchement ſur le rolle</l>
                     <l>N'vſurpe de ſon chef l'office &amp; la parolle.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Il finit: &amp; ſoudain par vn murmure doux</l>
                     <l>Son genereux conſeilest approuué de tous.</l>
                     <l>Ilz s'en vont ſatisfaicts: &amp; dans les creux nauires</l>
                     <l>R'emportent eſchauffez des genereuſes ires.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ce camp, par qui iadis <hi>ILION</hi> fut razé,</l>
                     <l>En armes &amp; valeur cedoit au baptizé.</l>
                     <l>Là, l'Eſpaigne roſtie, areneuſe, infertile,</l>
                     <l>De ſes filz baſanez en faict venir huict mile:</l>
                     <l>Superbes, bien reglez, de leur honneur ialoux,</l>
                     <l>Froids au co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, mais chauds aux meilleurs coups.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:55"/>
                     <l>L'Italie, tetin, &amp; verger de la terre</l>
                     <l>Y fait couler la fleur de ſes hommes de guerre:</l>
                     <l>Douze mille ſoldatz vindicatifz, gentilz,</l>
                     <l>A bien faire, à mal faire, eſgalement ſubtilz.</l>
                     <l>Puis on void ſur le dos de l'ondeuſe campaigne</l>
                     <l>Venir des vagues champs de la froide Allemaigne</l>
                     <l>De guerriers fourmilliere, &amp; boutique de <hi>MARS,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Trois mille champions, venaux, mais bons ſoudarts.</l>
                     <l>Là ſe trouuent auſsi trois mille volontaires</l>
                     <l>Bouïllants d'vn zele ſainct: deux cents &amp; huict galeres,</l>
                     <l>Vingt &amp; cinq naus de charge, auec ſix grands vaiſſeaux,</l>
                     <l>Qui ſemblent des Palais, non des nefz ſur les eaux.</l>
                     <l>Et deus fois vingt encor fuſtes, fregates, barques</l>
                     <l>Portent le camp ſacré des fidelles Monarques.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>CE</hi> peuple vagabond, ceſte ville de bois</l>
                     <l>Commence à deſmarer le ſeptieſme du mois</l>
                     <l>Qui nage tout en mouſt. D'vn alaigre courage</l>
                     <l>Les nochers vont grimpant de cordage en cordage:</l>
                     <l>Hiſsant, hauſsant les draps: &amp; donnent, rois des eaux,</l>
                     <l>Par force &amp; par engin des aiſles aux vaiſseaux.</l>
                     <l>Seuls les forçats mi nuds d'vne rame ferrée</l>
                     <l>Rompent à contre coeur l'eſchine de Nerée:</l>
                     <l>Mais le Comite fier en front, en mine, en voix</l>
                     <l>Les menace tous-iour, &amp; les bat maintes-fois.</l>
                     <l>Ia d'auirons bruyans vne foreſt eſmuë</l>
                     <l>Par vn nombreux accord le Sel baueux remuë:</l>
                     <l>L'artillerie orage: &amp; les ſoldats diſpos</l>
                     <l>D'une greſle de plomb font empouler les flots.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>SATHAN,</hi> qui hait malin toute ſainte entrepriſe,</l>
                     <l>Le noir feu du diſcord dans l'ost Chrestien attiſe.</l>
                     <l>Le General l'esteint de l'eau de ſon bon ſens:</l>
                     <l>Et faict, bien aduisé, que les chefz plus puiſsans</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:56"/>
                     <l>Ne regardent qu'à <hi>DIEV:</hi> &amp; d'vn coeur heroique</l>
                     <l>A l'interest priué preferent le publique.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>LE RENOM</hi> loing volant (quiſus les hautes tours</l>
                     <l>D'vne langue d'airain caquetant tous les iours,</l>
                     <l>Dict le vray, dict le faux:) haste ſes peintes aiſles,</l>
                     <l>Et des appreſtz Chrestiens porte au Turc les nouuelles.</l>
                     <l>L'eſpion deſguisé, legier, ingenieux:</l>
                     <l>Dont le corps est couuert, &amp; d'oreilles &amp; d'yeux</l>
                     <l>Se fourre bien par tout: mais ſoniect ſemeſconte</l>
                     <l>Et fait que l'ennemi, deſdaigneus, ne tient conte</l>
                     <l>De l'exercite ſainct: vice qui ſouuent perd</l>
                     <l>Maint Capitaine en chef plus hazardeux qu'expert.</l>
                     <l>La f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>otte de <hi>SELIM</hi> au-gré des vents errante</l>
                     <l>Mouille l'ancre à la fin augoulphe de Lepanthe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le tanné moiſſonneur auoit deſia tondu</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>CERES</hi> aux cheueuxd'or: <hi>BACCHVS</hi> auoit perdu</l>
                     <l>Et ſon pampre &amp; ſes fruicts: les branches verdiſſantes</l>
                     <l>Ne craquent ſous le faiz des pommes rougiſſantes:</l>
                     <l>Le bois des premiers froids paſlement estonné</l>
                     <l>Laiſſe tomber ſon poil ſur le gazon fené:</l>
                     <l>Et ia le laboureur du ſoc de ſa charruë</l>
                     <l>Pour y ſemer du blé le pourri champ remuë,</l>
                     <l>Quand lapproche ſe faict Lors <hi>VENIER</hi> le ruzé,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>VENIER</hi> ſecond Vlyſse ayant l'ost abusé</l>
                     <l>Par vne fauſſe alarme, &amp; ſeméles nouuelles</l>
                     <l>De la bleſme terreur des ſoldatz infideles:</l>
                     <l>Qu'on ny void que diſcord, fuite, temerité:</l>
                     <l>Et que cinq-fois dix naus ont leur camp ia quitté,</l>
                     <l>Faict que noz champions d'vn plus conſtant courage</l>
                     <l>Meſpriſent des Payens, &amp; le nombre &amp; la rage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Tandis le Sainct ouurier de ce rond bastiment,</l>
                     <l>Qui void tout, qui ſur tout commande abſolument,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:56"/>
                     <l>Aſsis au lieu plus haut de la voute empyrée</l>
                     <l>Void ſlanquer les piliers de ſa chaire dorée</l>
                     <l>De <hi>IVSTICE</hi> &amp; d'<hi>AMOVR.</hi> L'vn a le front riant,</l>
                     <l>Et l'autre renſrongné: l'vn vapour nous priant,</l>
                     <l>Et l'autre contre nous: l'vn à Pitié le pouſse,</l>
                     <l>L'autre fait que vengeur L'<hi>ETERNEL</hi> ſe courrouce,</l>
                     <l>Qu'il deſploye ſes fleaux, &amp; rempli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>se les chams</l>
                     <l>De hurlemens affreux, les toictz de cris trenchans.</l>
                     <l>Mais le <hi>DIEV</hi> touſiour-vn ſi dextrement accorde</l>
                     <l>Et la <hi>LOY</hi> porte-glaiue, &amp; la <hi>MISERICORDE:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Qu'encor que la premiere obtienne rarement,</l>
                     <l>De ſes breuetz ſanglants le iuſte appointement:</l>
                     <l>Et que l'autre touſiours parvienne à ſes attentes:</l>
                     <l>Elles ſont toutes-fois eſgualement contentes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Puis L'<hi>ETERNEL</hi> prenant la balance en ſes mains,</l>
                     <l>Et par grace y peſant les pechez des humains,</l>
                     <l>Des cruelz Sarraſins void trebucher les fautes:</l>
                     <l>Et celles des Chrestiens demeurer touſiours hautes.</l>
                     <l>Lors ilfronça ſon front dont la Terre trembla,</l>
                     <l>Pluton fremit de peur, &amp; la Mer ſe troubla</l>
                     <l>Bruyantement haueuſe Auſsi tost quel' Aurore</l>
                     <l>Peinte d'or, de ſafran, de vermeillon encore,</l>
                     <l>A bani la nuict ſombre: &amp; qu'en tire-lirant</l>
                     <l>L'allouëtte a donné d'un bec doux-ſouſpirant</l>
                     <l>Vngay bon-iour au iour: que Phoebé change-face</l>
                     <l>Dans le parc de Thetis ſes moreaus vistes chaſse:</l>
                     <l>Que Phoebus diſsipe-ombre a d'un feu tremblotant</l>
                     <l>Frappé l'acier fourbi du caſquet eſclatant:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>IEAN</hi> d'<hi>AVSTRE</hi> va plantant ſur la hunc venteuſe</l>
                     <l>De <hi>MARS</hi> fauche-ſoudars l'enſeigne furieuſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ainſi que les ouuriers diligemment ſubtils,</l>
                     <l>Sur la pointe du iour preparent leurs outilz:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:57"/>
                     <l>Son feu touſiour viuant là le vitrier attise:</l>
                     <l>L'artiste menuiſier là ſes rabotz aiguise:</l>
                     <l>Le ſerrurier ſa lime: &amp; là le bon maçon,</l>
                     <l>Au rebelle Porphyre oſer donner façon.</l>
                     <l>Là ſes viues couleurs l'aigu peintre meſlange:</l>
                     <l>Et là ſes plombs parlants le prompt Imprimeur range:</l>
                     <l>Ce monde de ſoldats ne void ſi tost flotter</l>
                     <l>Le ſignal du combat, qu'il s'en court apprester</l>
                     <l>Ses instruments guerriers: &amp; gaillard boult d'enuie</l>
                     <l>Ou de gaigner la Palme, ou de perdre la vie.</l>
                     <l>Le braue Cheualier ſon glaiue raieunit,</l>
                     <l>Ses armes l'armeurier: Le ſoldat ſe munit</l>
                     <l>Et de corde &amp; de plomb: &amp; l'artilleur ia couche</l>
                     <l>Des Canons briſe-nefz la ruineuſe bouche:</l>
                     <l>L'Archer bande ſon arc: &amp; les nochers criars,</l>
                     <l>A leur oeuure attentifs courent de toutes parts.</l>
                     <l>Tous, tous ſont occupez, ainſi que les auettes,</l>
                     <l>Qui peintes voletant ſur l'eſmail des fleurettes</l>
                     <l>Suççottent là deſsus l'alme ſueur du ciel,</l>
                     <l>Qu'en leurs troux doux-bruyans elles changent en miel.</l>
                     <l>On ne void rien parmi les troupes marinieres</l>
                     <l>Que drapeaux bou-boufans, gonfanons, &amp; bannieres,</l>
                     <l>Ou zephyreſe iouë, orgueilleux de meſler</l>
                     <l>Son aiſle enfante-fleurs, doux eſuantail de l'air,</l>
                     <l>Parmi tant de couleurs, armoiries, deuiſes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>IEAN</hi> d'<hi>AVSTRE</hi> cependant, oiſif tu ne meſpriſes</l>
                     <l>L'ordre de la bataille: &amp; ton entendement</l>
                     <l>N'eſt pas moins trauaillé de ce chaud penſement,</l>
                     <l>Que le reste du camp a ſes mains occupées</l>
                     <l>Aux cordes, traitz, canons, bales, armes, eſpées.</l>
                     <l>Tu menes la bataille, &amp; fais que le Romain</l>
                     <l>A main droite combat, <hi>VENIER</hi> à lautre main.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:57"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>CE</hi> chef rodant autour de la floite fidelle</l>
                     <l>Par nom &amp; par ſurnom les plus vaillants appelle:</l>
                     <l>De leur deuot deſſein propoſe l'equité,</l>
                     <l>Le butin de Turquie, &amp; limmortalité.</l>
                     <l>Dict que l'honneur diuin gist comme en leur courage:</l>
                     <l>Que leur ſeule valeur peut d'vn cruel ſeruage</l>
                     <l>Affranchir leurs germains: mais en tournant le front,</l>
                     <l>Ils trahiſsent leur gloire: &amp; miſerables font</l>
                     <l>Que le peuple qui ſainct la Foy de Chriſt embraſse</l>
                     <l>Gemira dans les ceps de l'<hi>OTTHO MANE</hi> race.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>De ce noble orateur l'auguſte royauté</l>
                     <l>Le front fierement beau, le port, la grauité</l>
                     <l>Dore tant de ſes mots la coulante merueille:</l>
                     <l>Que tout le camp raui par l'oeil, &amp; par l'oreille</l>
                     <l>Dict Victoire, victoire, ô victoire: &amp; le flot,</l>
                     <l>D'vn language bruyant redit trois-fois ce mot.</l>
                     <l>I e t'accepte, ô mot ſainct (crie le Prince ſage)</l>
                     <l>Mot ſacré, ie te pren pour vn heureux preſage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>LE</hi> Turc range de meſme en bataille ſes osts,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>PORTAV</hi> commande en terre, <hi>ALY</hi> deſsus les flots.</l>
                     <l>Fier il conduit le gros des troupes infidelles,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>OCHIAL</hi> &amp; <hi>MEEMET</hi> gouuernent les deux aiſles.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Lors <hi>ALY</hi> le <hi>BASCHA</hi> ſoigneux va viſitant</l>
                     <l>D'vn viſage aſſeuré l'exercite flottant:</l>
                     <l>Et practiquant guerrier, vne maſle eloquence,</l>
                     <l>Ilraconte comment la Turqueſque vaillance</l>
                     <l>A touſiour triomphé du peuple porte croix:</l>
                     <l>Qu'eux meſmes ont vaincu ia deſia tant de fois</l>
                     <l>Ces chefs qui leur font teste: &amp; la longue durée</l>
                     <l>Des ſceptres d'<hi>OTTHOMAN</hi> race en terre adorée.</l>
                     <l>He! voulez vous (dit il) rompuz, desfaicts, chaſsez,</l>
                     <l>Dementir le renom de voz gestes paſsez?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:58"/>
                     <l>Faire cent-fois vainqueurs à voz vaincuz hommage?</l>
                     <l>Et du terroir Chreſtien meſpriſer le pillage?</l>
                     <l>Mais perdant, vous ſerez accablez de gros fers:</l>
                     <l>Et gehenez nuict &amp; iour ſeruirez à voz ſerfz:</l>
                     <l>Voz heurs deuiendront pleurs: &amp; ceſte renommée</l>
                     <l>Qui pouſse au Ciel voz faitz ira toute en fumée.</l>
                     <l>Courage donc Soldats: <hi>MAHOM</hi> ſera pour nous,</l>
                     <l>Et de noz fers trenchants guidera tous les coups.</l>
                     <l>Que s'il fault auoir peur, ayez peur que la crainte</l>
                     <l>Du burin de Nature en leur poictrine empreinte</l>
                     <l>Ne leur donne pluſtoſt que de venir aux mains,</l>
                     <l>Et la iambe des cerfz &amp; laiſlé pied des dains.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le ſon enflambe-coeurs de ces motz heroiques</l>
                     <l>Est ſuiui quand &amp; quand d'vn branſlement de piques,</l>
                     <l>Du tin tin des eſtocs, &amp; d'vne voix qui ſort</l>
                     <l>De tout l'ost ſans ardeur, ſans force, ſans accord.</l>
                     <l>Les rayons clair-luiſans de la torche du monde</l>
                     <l>Donnant deſsus l'acier font berluer ſous l'onde</l>
                     <l>Les troupeaux eſcaillez. Le Soleil radieux</l>
                     <l>Frappe les Sainctz à dos, &amp; le Turc ſur les yeux.</l>
                     <l>Et les vents vagabonds qui deuant la meſlée</l>
                     <l>Des Byzantins cruels chocquoient la pouppe aiſlée,</l>
                     <l>Si tost qu'on vint aux coups (ô miracle!) donna</l>
                     <l>Sur leur viſage fier. Le Turc ſ'en estonna</l>
                     <l>Et le Chreſtien le prit pour augure fidelle,</l>
                     <l>Que le <hi>DIEV</hi> des combatz defendroit ſa querelle.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Si toſt que le goſier bruyantement fumeux,</l>
                     <l>Des longs canons troubla l'Ocean eſcumeux:</l>
                     <l>Que fier iladiourna <hi>BELLONE</hi> au grand courage:</l>
                     <l>Et <hi>MARS</hi> le furieux, ſanglant, aime-carnage:</l>
                     <l>Que de l'airain plié le ſon haut-reſonnant</l>
                     <l>Eut embrazé les coeurs d'vn deſir bouillonnant</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:58"/>
                     <l>De renom eternel. Pouuret, que veux-tu dire?</l>
                     <l>Veux-tu d'vn digne vers ces durs aſſautz deſcrire?</l>
                     <l>Ozes-tu peindre au vif <hi>DIEV</hi> tout tel qu'il eſtoit</l>
                     <l>Quand ſon bras tempesteux pour ſes filz combattoit?</l>
                     <l>L'oculaire teſmoin n'y pourroit point ſuffire:</l>
                     <l>Et toy qui n'en ſçais rien que par vn ouir-dire</l>
                     <l>En viendras bien à bout? mais ie l'ay proiecté,</l>
                     <l>Ie l'ay deſia promis, le ſort en est iecté,</l>
                     <l>Croyant que le lecteur viſera, fauorable,</l>
                     <l>Moins à mes rudes vers, qu'àmon deſir louable.</l>
                     <l>Que comme ceux qui vont tous les iours au ſoleil</l>
                     <l>Sont teincts des rais ardents qui partent de ſon oeil:</l>
                     <l>Mes propos retiendront quelque couleur naïfue</l>
                     <l>Du <hi>MARS</hi> qu'ils veulent peindre: &amp; que la ſource viue</l>
                     <l>D'eloquence &amp; ſçuoir, le grand <hi>DIEV,</hi> dont ie veux</l>
                     <l>La gloire icy chanter, accomplira mes voeus.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le ſigne eſtant donné, la bataille commence,</l>
                     <l>Les ſix plus grandes nefz vers la teſte on auance:</l>
                     <l>On afuſte, on prent mire, on tire des canons,</l>
                     <l>D'ou ſortent des cailloux, bouletz, ramez, chainons,</l>
                     <l>Qui donnent dans les Turcs: &amp; ſous les eaux pourprées</l>
                     <l>Enterrent à lopins leurs bandes demembrées.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le peuple ſans poulmon és abyſmes s'enfuit</l>
                     <l>Tout d'vn coup, estonné d'vn tant horrible bruit:</l>
                     <l>Le cielest affeublé de cent nuës fumeuſes:</l>
                     <l>On oit bruire àl'entour cent bouches ſalpetreuſes,</l>
                     <l>Et leur ton ton-tonant erre: &amp; prompt,<note place="margin">I'ay voulu icy imiter l'Onomato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poee de l'au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theur.</note> rompt le rond</l>
                     <l>Du plancher eſtoillé. Les hurlements que font</l>
                     <l>Tant &amp; tant de bleſsez qui par cent mille portes</l>
                     <l>Font leurs ames ſortir deſpiteuſement fortes,</l>
                     <l>Conioincts aux premiers bruitz, chamaillis, trembleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</l>
                     <l>Troublent tout en vn couples craintifz elements.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:59"/>
                     <l>Mais non les chefs des Turcs, qui vont pleins de courage</l>
                     <l>C'est orage chaſser par vn contraire orage:</l>
                     <l>Et leurs bouletz ardents abattent tant de corps,</l>
                     <l>Que le nombre eſt eſgal des viuans &amp; des morts.</l>
                     <l>Les Turcs ſont repayez en la meſme monnoye:</l>
                     <l>Noſtre canon les bat, les briſe, les foudroye.</l>
                     <l>Rompuz qui çà qui là tombent dedans les flots:</l>
                     <l>Leur eſprit dedaigneux ſort auec les ſanglots,</l>
                     <l>Trauerſe en blaſphemant la riuiere infernale,</l>
                     <l>Et viſited'Enfer la nuict ſombrement pale.</l>
                     <l>Du paſsager <hi>CHARON</hi> le gemiſsant bateau</l>
                     <l>De trop d'ombres chargé s'enfondre dedans l'eau.</l>
                     <l>Tandis qu'un pere ardent apres le fier carnage</l>
                     <l>Et de geſte, &amp; de voix, donne à ſon filz courage,</l>
                     <l>Vn boulet empenné d'une ardente vapeur</l>
                     <l>Donne au pere la mort, donne à l'enfant la peur.</l>
                     <l>Tandis que de la main, tandis que de la bouche</l>
                     <l>Vn chef co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande aux ſiens, vn volant plomb luy bouche</l>
                     <l>Les conduits du language, &amp; roidit, inhumain,</l>
                     <l>Les nerfz iadis ſi forts de ſa parlante main.</l>
                     <l>Tandis qu'vn eſcadron emplotoné ſe ſerre,</l>
                     <l>Le murmurant effort d'vn enſoulfré tonnerre,</l>
                     <l>Fatal, n'en choiſit qu'vn, effleurant le chapeau</l>
                     <l>Du voiſin, doz de l'autre, &amp; d'vn autre la peau.</l>
                     <l>Cest effroiable ſon, faict que des Capitaines</l>
                     <l>Bien qu'ilz orient fort haut, les parolles ſont vaines.</l>
                     <l>Chaſcun mene les mains ſelon qu'il est pouſsé</l>
                     <l>Ou de l'obiect preſent, ou d vn <hi>MARS</hi> inſensé.</l>
                     <l>Il est chef &amp; ſoldat: &amp; ſes mains exercées,</l>
                     <l>Font proufit ſeulement des batailles paſsées.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>S'estant donc ſaluez ſur les champs ondoyants,</l>
                     <l>Par des ambaſsadeurs mortellement bruyants</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:59"/>
                     <l>On parle de plus pres: l'vn &amp; l'autre ost approche:</l>
                     <l>La nef choque la nef, la nef la nef accroche:</l>
                     <l>Tout bras, tout glaiue aigu, tout dard est employé:</l>
                     <l>Celuy qui fuit les coups, est dans la mer noyé.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Icy le Cheualier trenche net vne teste,</l>
                     <l>Et là quand vn guerrier magnanime s'appreste</l>
                     <l>A creuer d'vn eſpieu le coeur d'vn fier ſoudart,</l>
                     <l>Vn tiers d'vn bois tremblant l'outre de part en part.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Touſiour le canon tonne, &amp; l'harquebuſe pette:</l>
                     <l>Iamais du fer creusé la foudreuſe tempeste</l>
                     <l>Ne les menace en vain: chaque plomb a ſon blanc:</l>
                     <l>Et s'il ne tuë point, il verſe aumoins du ſang.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le forçaire au doux ſon du ſainct mot de franchiſe</l>
                     <l>Vne guerriere ardeur dans ſa poitrine attiſe:</l>
                     <l>Et s'armant de crochetz, de barres, d'auirons,</l>
                     <l>Bleſse, aſsomme tous ceux qu'il trouue aux enuirons.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Cependant qu'vn Chreſtien priue ce Turc de vie,</l>
                     <l>La vie du Chreſtien est par vn Turc rauie.</l>
                     <l>Lors que d'vn traict Turquois vn ſainct bras est attaint,</l>
                     <l>Le bras decoche traict eſt percé d'vn bois ſainct.</l>
                     <l>Et ſur le meſme poinct que d'une forte bale</l>
                     <l>L'artilleur Muſulman pouſse en l'onde infernale</l>
                     <l>Vn baptizé ſoldat, l'harquebuſier croisé</l>
                     <l>Tuë le canonier, qui mire peu ruzé</l>
                     <l>Le beau coup qu'il a faict: &amp; donne trop grand priſe</l>
                     <l>A cil qui ſeulement contre ſa teste viſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Des freſnes aiguiſez le dru tremouſsement,</l>
                     <l>Le chamaillis du fer, des traicts le friſsement,</l>
                     <l>Des bleſsés languiſſants l'effroiable language,</l>
                     <l>L'entrechoc des vaiſseaux, &amp; des canons l'orage,</l>
                     <l>Meſlés s'en vont ſi haut ſur les eaux reſonnant,</l>
                     <l>Qu'on ne peut meſme ouir le bruit du ciel tonnant.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:60"/>
                     <l>La mer n'eſtrien que ſang: &amp; la race eſcaillée</l>
                     <l>S'enyure du poiſon de ſon onde ſouillée:</l>
                     <l>Et ſemble qu'à ce coup de L' Amramide ſainct,</l>
                     <l>Le deuorant baston eut tout ce goulphe teint.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Leur valeur rend long temps douteuſe la meſlée:</l>
                     <l>Meſme ost &amp; gaigne &amp; perd. Et la fortune aiſlée</l>
                     <l>Void chaſque bataillon de picques heriſsé</l>
                     <l>Or d'vn riant viſage, or d'vn oeil courroucé.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>MARS</hi> trouue le iour court pour practiquer ſa rage:</l>
                     <l>Le maſſacre croiſsant, fait croistre le courage:</l>
                     <l>Plus le nombre deſcroit, plus deſcroit la pitié:</l>
                     <l>La perte des amis cauſe vne inimitié,</l>
                     <l>Qui rend chaſque ſoldat durant ce triſte eſclandre</l>
                     <l>Fort à donner les coups, inſenſible à les prendre.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Quand ie penſe combien de Chreſtiens ſont tombez</l>
                     <l>Sous l'homicide fil des coutelas courbez</l>
                     <l>Du peuple Byzantin, d'horreur mon poil ſe dreſse,</l>
                     <l>Ma plume ne peut peindre vne telle tristeſse.</l>
                     <l>O <hi>DIEV</hi> par ton eſprit eſclaire mes eſprits:</l>
                     <l>Et d'un ſaint peloton guide moy par les plis</l>
                     <l>De ce Daedale obſcur: courage, terre, terre:</l>
                     <l>Ie descouure vn bon port: Ie voy finir la guerre.</l>
                     <l>Ia l'oreille me corne, &amp; dans les creuſes naux</l>
                     <l>Semble que i'oy desia mille chants triomphaux.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>L'Eſpagnol Cheualier qui courageux deſire</l>
                     <l>Du Colonnel Payen attaquer la nauire,</l>
                     <l>Hurte, paſſe à trauers flotz, prouës, eſperons,</l>
                     <l>Bales, piques, eſpieux, dardz, flesches, auirons:</l>
                     <l>Agraffe nef à nef, eſprouue ſa vaillance.</l>
                     <l>Mais le ſort n'est pas moins conſtant en inconſtance,</l>
                     <l>En ce duël priué, qu'és combatz generaux.</l>
                     <l>On tire inceſsamment des chasteaux des deux naux.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:60"/>
                     <l>Les canons plus en coup qu'en murmure effroyables</l>
                     <l>Rompent corps, iambes, bras, maſtz, antennes &amp; cables.</l>
                     <l>On rend les traicts iectez: &amp; du commencement</l>
                     <l>L'entr'approche des chefs s'achepte cherement.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A la fin toutes-fois la victoire commence</l>
                     <l>Regarder d'vn bon aeil l'Eſpagnole vaillance.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>DON-IEAN</hi> accompagné des plus braues guerriers,</l>
                     <l>Prodigue de ſon ſang, entre des beaus premiers</l>
                     <l>Dans le vaiſseau vaincu du <hi>BASCHA,</hi> qui colere</l>
                     <l>Se deſpitant de veoir les croix dans ſa galere,</l>
                     <l>Rechaſse les vainqueurs, &amp; fait qui'ls laiſsent morts</l>
                     <l>Sur ſon tillac ſanglant pour gage pluſieurs corps.</l>
                     <l>Le Prince eſperoné de deſpit &amp; de honte,</l>
                     <l>Et chez qui l'amour ſainct de la gloire ſurmonte</l>
                     <l>L'amour doux de la vie, encourage ſi bien</l>
                     <l>Et d'exemple &amp; de voix le bataillon Chreſtien</l>
                     <l>Que ſon craintif glaçon en vn braſier s'allume,</l>
                     <l>Et qu'il r'entre dedans plus fier que de couſtume.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Le Turc de tant de gents à la fin combattu</l>
                     <l>Gaigne pour ſe ſauuer la prouë au bec-pointu.</l>
                     <l>Vn ſoldat Grec l'attaque: &amp; fait ſaulter par terre</l>
                     <l>Son ſacrilege chef d'vn coup de cimeterre.</l>
                     <l>Le coup n'est ſans guerdon: &amp; le chef degoutant</l>
                     <l>Est fiché ſur le maſt de ſon vaiſseauflotant.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ce trophée estonna les Turcs de telle ſorte,</l>
                     <l>Que la volante peur loing des coups les emporte.</l>
                     <l>Mais ils ſont toſt apres par noz voiles r'attaints.</l>
                     <l>Et ſans qu'vn <hi>OCHIAL</hi> trompa noz longues mains</l>
                     <l>Gaignant vn ſeur Aſyle auec trente galeres,</l>
                     <l>Ou maint Heros Malthois eſprouuoit les miſeres</l>
                     <l>Du forçat qui battu battoit touſiour Neptun,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>SELIM</hi> n'en euſt rien ſçeu que par vn bruit commun.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:61"/>
                     <l>La bataille gagnée au <hi>SEIGNEVR</hi> on rend graces:</l>
                     <l>On ſuit barques, eſquifs, houlques, galeres, naſses:</l>
                     <l>On y trouue enferrez douze mille de ceux</l>
                     <l>Que <hi>CHRIST</hi> le grand Paſteur dans ſon parc a rec eus.</l>
                     <l>On haut-loue <hi>DON-IEAN</hi> vray foudre de la guerre,</l>
                     <l>Dont le ciel a voulu faire monſtre à la terre:</l>
                     <l>Et puis la retiré, non ſans cauſe ialoux</l>
                     <l>Qu'vn aſtre ſi luiſant flamboiast parminous.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>La Nuict reſpand adonc ſur les choſes mortelles</l>
                     <l>Pour couuer le repos ſes doux-peſantes aiſles:</l>
                     <l>Va tous les animaux de ſon miel enchantant:</l>
                     <l>Et mene auecques ſoy Morphée linconſtant.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Venize est en ſuſpens, &amp; d'vne ame flottante</l>
                     <l>Attend l'euenement de l'attaque ſanglante.</l>
                     <l>Elle ſe veut promettre, &amp; n'oſe toutes-fois</l>
                     <l>(Tant le paſsé l'eſmeut) la mort de l'ost Turquois.</l>
                     <l>De ioye &amp; de douleur ſa poitrine eſt attainte:</l>
                     <l>Elle eſere le bien, &amp; du mal elle a crainte.</l>
                     <l>En fin du bon ſuccez de ce cruel combat</l>
                     <l>Le meſſage certain paruient iuſqu'au Senat:</l>
                     <l>Du Senat, à la Ville. Vne ioye incroiable</l>
                     <l>Saiſit le coeur de tous. La troupe venerable</l>
                     <l>Des Dames aux vieux ans, &amp; des Vierges encor,</l>
                     <l>Reprenant ſes carquans, bagues, &amp; chaines d'or,</l>
                     <l>Et ſe tournant en rond dans la place publique</l>
                     <l>Au branle de ſes pieds marient ce Cantique.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="chorus">
                     <pb facs="tcp:8720:61"/>
                     <head>CHOEVR VENETIEN.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>CHante, ô peuple, ton <hi>DIEV:</hi> Ieunes &amp; vieux chantez,</l>
                        <l>De voix &amp; d'inſtruments celebrez ſes bontez.</l>
                        <l>De <hi>CHRIST</hi> le grand Sauueur chantez l'amour extreme,</l>
                        <l>Sauueur qui s'est monſtré vray Sauueur à vous-meſme.</l>
                        <l>Le laqs des ennemis nous tenoit enſerrez,</l>
                        <l>Les Turcs autour de nous auoient tendu leurs retz:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>DIEV</hi> nous a mis au large, &amp; leur propre artifice,</l>
                        <l>Miſerable, a ſerui de foſſe à leur malice.</l>
                        <l>Chante, ô peuple, ton <hi>DIEV:</hi> Ieunes &amp; vieux chantez,</l>
                        <l>Vieux &amp; ieunes de <hi>DIEV</hi> celebrez les bontez.</l>
                        <l>Qui du profane ioug de la gent Sarraſine</l>
                        <l>N'aguere a deſchargé voſtre ſaigneuſe eſchine.</l>
                        <l>Lauez tous voz pechez dans l'eau du repentir:</l>
                        <l>Nets entrez dans ſon Temple: &amp; faictes retentir</l>
                        <l>Ceste route des Turcs, victoire renommée</l>
                        <l>Que nous tenons de luy, &amp; non de noſtre armée.</l>
                        <l>Chreſtiens, ſaiſiſſez-vous de voz luths doux-ſonnants,</l>
                        <l>Prenez cistres, tabours, fifres haut-reſonnants,</l>
                        <l>Donnez aux orgues vent: embouchez voz trompettes:</l>
                        <l>Animez violons, guiterres, eſpinettes:</l>
                        <l>Chantez tous d'vn accord: Ieunes &amp; vieux chantez,</l>
                        <l>Et de vostre Sauueur celebrez les bontez.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>DECE</hi> Cantique ſainct la douce melodie</l>
                        <l>Rend &amp; mon corps peſant, &amp; mon ame engourdie.</l>
                        <l>Ia ma teſte de fer s'encline doucement</l>
                        <l>Vne, deux, &amp; trois fois deuers mon ſein d'aymant:</l>
                        <l>La paupiere est du tout ſur mon oeil abaiſsée,</l>
                        <l>Et ma plume de plomb chet de ma main laſsée.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8720:62"/>
                        <l>Et bref, mon corps viuant proprement ne vit pas:</l>
                        <l>Caril eſt poſsedé du frere du Treſpas.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lors le <hi>DIEV</hi> Sommeilleux, le viſte, le peint Ange,</l>
                        <l>Qui plus ſouuent de front, qu'vn vain Protée change,</l>
                        <l>Morphée aux aiſles d'or s'escoule lentement</l>
                        <l>Par la porte de corne en mon entendement.</l>
                        <l>Chez ſoy l'ame ſi toſt ne luy permit l'entrée</l>
                        <l>Que de tous ſoings humains elle fut ſeque ſtrée:</l>
                        <l>Et qu'elle ouit ces vers doucement animez</l>
                        <l>Par le charmeur goſier des courriers emplumez.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="chorus">
                     <head>CHOEVR DES ANGES.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>CHantons freres volants: chantons tous d'vn accord,</l>
                        <l>Le los de l'Immortel, le los du <hi>DIEV</hi> tresfort.</l>
                        <l>Anciens qui marchants ſur les voutes plus hautes,</l>
                        <l>Deux-fois-douze adorez l'Agneau efface-fautes,</l>
                        <l>Louez le auecques nous: &amp; faictes que les cieux</l>
                        <l>Ne reſonent voutez, que ſon nom glorieux.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>SEVL</hi> il est, il ſera, il fut touſiour en eſtre,</l>
                        <l>Des eſtres la fontaine, &amp; des estres le maiſtre:</l>
                        <l>Vn en trois, trois en vn, diſtinct, non diuisé:</l>
                        <l>Qui dans le rien d'vn rien ce Tout a composé,</l>
                        <l>Et le tient en eſtat: ô Citadins porte-aiſles,</l>
                        <l>O vous vies ſans corps, ô troupes immortelles</l>
                        <l>Louez le de ceſte oeuure: &amp; ſi faire se peut,</l>
                        <l>Louez le encore plus de ce que doux il veut</l>
                        <l>N'eſpandre ſeulement les ruiſſeaux de ſa grace</l>
                        <l>Sur celuy qui deuot ſon pur ſeruice embraſse:</l>
                        <l>Ains ſur celuy qui meu de telle quelle foy</l>
                        <l>Mille menuz fatras meſle parmiſa loy.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8720:62"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>DIEV</hi> le monſtre à ce coup. Mais quoy? ſes vrais fidelles</l>
                        <l>Sentiront plus à plein ſes faueurs eternelles.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>DIEV, DIEV</hi> ſera leur bras. Carpuis qu'il eſt ainſi</l>
                        <l>Que, clement, il pourſuit d vn paternel ſoucy</l>
                        <l>Ceux qui, Phariſiens, s'enflent de leur iuſtice,</l>
                        <l>Que feroit-il à ceux qui confeſsent leur vice?</l>
                        <l>A ceux de qui l'eſprit par l'Eſprit Saint dompté</l>
                        <l>Ne veulent recourir qu'à ſa ſaincte bonté?</l>
                        <l>Puis qu'il aide à celuy dont le ſalut chancele,</l>
                        <l>Et que doit eſperer celuy quil Eſprit ſéele</l>
                        <l>Du cachet de ſalut? Puis qu'il p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rte faueur</l>
                        <l>A celuy qui ſe feint Sauueur deſsus Sauueur,</l>
                        <l>Et s'adreſse aux Dieux vains: ô qu'il ſera propice</l>
                        <l>A cil qui fait ſes voeus au Soleil de Iuſtice!</l>
                        <l>A l'Agneau ſacré ſainct, à qui ſeul le Seigneur</l>
                        <l>A donné de tout temps l'eſtat de Moienneur!</l>
                        <l>Chreſtiens, s'il eſt ainſi que ſa dextre combatte</l>
                        <l>Pour celuy qui, bigot, adore vn Dieu de paſte:</l>
                        <l>(Erreur par trop groſsier) pourra il meſpriſer</l>
                        <l>Ses vrais adorateurs? pourra-il refuſer</l>
                        <l>Aide à cil qui zelé de ſon feu ſeul s'enflame,</l>
                        <l>Et qui fait pour ſon nom bon marché de ſon ame?</l>
                        <l>Puis qu'il cherit celuy qui porte au front eſcrit,</l>
                        <l>Trompé des faux docteurs, le ſéel de l'Antechriſt:</l>
                        <l>De la grande Putain, de qui les mains cruelles,</l>
                        <l>Et par fer &amp; par feu pourſuiuent les fidelles:</l>
                        <l>He! n'aimera-il pas cil qui pour ſon amour</l>
                        <l>Est des cruels tyrans mal mené nuict &amp; iour?</l>
                        <l>Qui luy rend teſmoignage? &amp; qui deſsus ſa face</l>
                        <l>Porte eternellement la marque de ſa grace?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O <hi>SEIGNEVR</hi> fay ceſser, fay ceſser les trauaux</l>
                        <l>Qui torturent les Saincts: donne fin à leur maux:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:8720:63"/>
                        <l>Et chaſse, ô trois-fois Bon, l'ignorance profonde,</l>
                        <l>Qui d'vn nuage eſpais affeuble tout lemonde.</l>
                        <l>Et nous ſes meſsagers d'astres clairs reueſtus</l>
                        <l>Celebrons ſa bonté, gloire de ſes vertus.</l>
                        <l>Chantons tous d'vne voix, ô bandes emplumées,</l>
                        <l>Chantons, ô Sainct, ô Sainct, ô Sainct <hi>DIEV</hi> des armées.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Leur chant prendicy fin. Icy prend fin le mien.</l>
                        <l>O toy qui nes de faict moins que de nom Chreſtien,</l>
                        <l>Bon coeur, eſpere en <hi>DIEV,</hi> qui meſme fauoriſe</l>
                        <l>Ceux qui n'ont ſeulement qu'vn vain titre d'Egliſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Que ſi de l'Antechriſt le blaſphemant courroux</l>
                        <l>Plus felon que iamais coniure or contre nous:</l>
                        <l>Sçache que <hi>DIEV</hi> cherit plus le corps que l'ombrage</l>
                        <l>Chreſtien, monſtre à ce coup inuaincu ton courage,</l>
                        <l>Et t'aſseure que <hi>CHRIST</hi> fera de ton ennuy,</l>
                        <l>Sortir proufit pour toy, ſortir honneur pour luy.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8720:63"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
